[Music]
this is a story of a bizarre murder and
a crime scene that yields few Clues and
it is the story of a small town cop who
refuses to give
up even after his only suspects
vanish with the help of inter pole he
tracks them across the globe to bring
them to justice and uncover the truth
behind their lethal
Obsession jurisdiction the world when
crimes are committed an international
organization unites police officers to
deliver Justice interpole investigates
[Music]
Bedford County
Virginia on April 3rd 1985 Deputy Ricky
Gardner drives back to the Bedford
County Sheriff's
Office just after 4 p.m. a call comes
over the
radio it's a gner 104 the bed County
Sheriff Office received a call from a
group of ladies who had gone to the
residence of Derk and Nancy haome for a
bridge
game the women didn't get an answer when
they knocked on the door our deputies
had been sent to the residents for will
beinging
checked Gardner notices something
strange about the call they didn't come
back on the radio the officers call in
their report on the telephone so they
can't be overheard this procedure is
only used in the most serious
situations for detective Gardner it is
an ominous
sign so I knew then I said well that
doesn't sound exactly right so I started
listening a little bit more
intently the dispatcher orders all units
to respond to the jome home
immediately Derek and Nancy hesome live
in a modest house in an expensive part
of
town crime seen in investigators are
already on the scene when Gardner
arrives when I entered the residence uh
observed a uh male subject laying on the
floor to the left of the front door as
you go
in uh laying in a large pool of dried
blood Derek Ham's throat has been
[Music]
slit he's been stabbed dozens of times
times from the condition of the body it
looks like he's been dead for several
days Deputy Gardener follows a trail of
dried blood into the
kitchen there he finds Nancy H's body
there was a large amount of blood dried
blood surrounding her body as
well like her husband Mrs asam's throat
has been
[Music]
cut she too has been stabbed
repeatedly I had only been an
investigator for about 6 months so this
was the first murder scene that I had
never been assigned to it was obvious to
a young investigator that it was a very
violent uh crime and that the victims
obviously put up a a
fight Garder questions the women who
first found the
bodies they tell him they played Bridge
with derck hm
regularly Derek was religious about his
weekly bridge game he never missed
it when he didn't answer the door that
afternoon they became
concerned to Gardner nothing about the
murders makes
sense they seem
random he questions the jum's neighbors
hoping they might have seen
something we didn't have a lot of luck
in the U neighborhood because it is such
a remote area and uh people could go and
come over there without really being
detected despite the violence of the
crime and the obvious signs of a
struggle no one has seen or heard
anything
unusual news of the murder leaks to the
Press Terren Samuel covered it for the r
Oak times we can't believe this has
happened here you know through were
these two dead people that's pretty
brutal there's blood everywhere um you
know reporters are desperate for any
kind of information you know where
they're kind of uh kind of milking
everybody who comes and leaves and
there's a sense that uh this is
something
big forensic texts from the Bedford
County Sheriff's Department analyze
every corner of the
house there is no sign of forced
entry Nancy H's purse in plain view is
still full of cash right out of the
shoot we were able to eliminate the
robbery as been a motive so we were
trying to figure out why were these two
people so brutally murdered check this
out what do you think in the dining room
investigators find a bloody handprint on
the upholstery of a
chair does it belong to one of the hasum
or did the killer leave it
behind investigators bag the Upholstery
and the handprint as evidence
forensic techs seal every door and
window in the house then fumigate the
interior with
Superglue cyanoacrylate an ingredient in
superglue clings to latent fingerprints
making them
visible next using luminol investigators
search the house for any hidden blood
evidence under a specialized light
source blood Trails emerge in the dark
Gardner notices strange
patterns it almost looks as if the
killer mopped the floor with
it whoever committed this crime spent
time in the home trying to cover his or
her tracks though
unsuccessfully bloody Footprints lead
away from Derek's
body one appeared to be made from a
tennis
shoe at least two three others were
either partial Barefoot Impressions or
one complete Barefoot
impression the trail of Prince leads
down the
hall into the
bedroom and ends in the master
bath Garder wonders if the killer tried
to clean himself up before he left the
house we sprayed the the showers the the
sinks and and also the area outside of
the front
door blood is everywhere whoever killed
the ases also washed up in their
bathroom we' never seen anything like
this before we really hadn't formulated
any kind of an idea on what really
happened inside the residence or how
many people how many perpetrators have
been
there emotionally it was just draining
to be involved in something like that
but yet at the same time the adrenaline
was still
flowing I knew that this was going to be
a very important
case after spending hours analyzing the
crime scene all Deputy Gardner uncovers
are more
questions he has mountains of evidence
to analyze limited resources and no real
leads we were collecting evidence and
sended it off to the lab and hoping that
the lab would would give us a uh some
idea on what we were we really
had as the Virginia State Crime Lab in
Richmond analyzes the evidence the
Bedford County Sheriff's Department
activates the regional homicide
Squad detectives from all over the state
study the crime scene
photos investigators now wonder if the
double homicide is a ritual cult
killing there were drawings in the blood
in the house that seemed to suggest some
kind of uh cultish
connection there was absolute confusion
and like who could have done this why
would they have done this um is is
something in this community completely
broken
down the media had had just focused in
on this and it the pressure from the
community was becoming pretty
intense with no suspect and no motive
the residents of Bedford County now fear
their Community is being stalked by Cult
[Music]
Killers where will they strike
next and who will they
[Music]
Target Bedford County
Virginia a brutal double homicide
terrifies residents of this small
community at the crime scene
investigators find a bizarre clue
it seems that whoever killed Derek and
Nancy hesome may have drawn pictures in
their
blood Deputy Ricky Gardner wonders if he
is dealing with a cult
[Music]
killer on Easter Sunday Gardner attends
a memorial service for the victims along
with their family and
friends Derek hesam was a retired
executive he had managed steel mills in
Africa and
Canada in 1959 he met and married
Nancy Nancy hem grew up in Virginia uh
her father was a geologist of some kind
he moved to he moved to Africa for his
work at some point she meets a man much
older Derek hesome uh they get married
they have one kid uh Elizabeth
haome he a good man
Derek had three children from a previous
marriage and Nancy had
two to Gardner the hesome seemed like
the perfect blended
family Elizabeth attends the University
of Virginia where she is an Eckles
scholar her half brothers are all
professionals James works as an engineer
in Canada years old Walter practices
medicine in
Texas Ronald is an architect
and Victor practices law in Nova
Scotia they had traveled all over the
world lived all over the world and in
fact their children still at that time
were living all over the world in
different countries and were scattered
across the country so we knew we had a
job cut out for us to try to put the
pieces of the puzzle together because it
was early on it was becoming a very
complicated
case desperate for leads investigators
talk to the people who knew knew the
victims best their
children the weekend of the memorial
service the
siblings came to Lynchburg obviously to
attend their parents memorial
service so we were able to to talk to
the the sons and the daughters and try
to put together some idea of you know
their
history Walter haome tells investigators
he was in Texas at the time of the
murders
the son was very cooperative and became
sort of the lon between the Sheriff's
Office the investigators and the family
members investigators talked to all six
asome children including the youngest
21-year-old
Elizabeth I some questions on she loved
her
parents and she couldn't understand why
anybody would would murder
them Elizabeth tells Deputy Gardner she
was out of town the weekend her parents
were
killed she and her boyfriend had gone to
Washington DC the weekend of uh March
the
30th uh in fact they had rented a car in
Charlottesville Virginia on Friday the
29th of
March and had driven to Washington DC
and spent the weekend into Washington
area touring and visiting
sites that afternoon they went to a
movie after they returned to the
hotel Elizabeth said she ordered dinner
from room
service Elizabeth and her boyfriend Yen
returned to Charlottesville on Sunday
night to get ready for classes on
Monday on Wednesday she learned her
parents had been killed
thing I think that brother Gardner asks
Elizabeth if her parents had any
enemies she tells him that before her
father retired he had been at the center
of an intense labor
dispute Mr haome had been involved in
the unions up in Nova Scotia we were
told that he had uh made some people mad
had had stood up to the
union um and there was some controversy
there I also mentioned that one of her
half Brothers had been engaged to a
woman with a history of emotional
problems he jilted her and married
somebody else she said y'all really need
to look at her you know she's psychotic
she could have killed my parents so I I
really need to look at
her Garder first checks out Elizabeth's
story credit card receipts confirm she
rented a car in Charlottesville Virginia
on March 29th
and her boyfriend paid for a hotel room
in Washington DC that
night Elizabeth has a solid
Alibi as do her
siblings Gardner interviews the young
Local woman Elizabeth mentioned in her
interview the woman had been engaged to
Elizabeth's half
brother her answers in the interview
troubled Gardner her behavior was
bizarre we didn't know if she
was some kind of a
sociopath she would make statements as
to you know the victims and the families
or whatnot and it was just um it was
just
[Music]
bizarre but not bizarre enough to make
her a murderer the ex- fiance is
eliminated as a suspect when her foot
impression does not match those taken at
the
scene Gardner reviews Elizabeth's
statement looking for anything he might
have
missed then he makes a startling
Discovery and we began looking at the
rental car agreement and we saw that
there the
mileage was whole lot more than it
should have been if in fact they had
driven from Charlottesville to
Washington Gardener calculates that the
round trip from Charlottesville Virginia
to Washington DC is about 230 MI
the runer car agreement showed that they
had traveled some
669 miles that
weekend Gardner again questions
Elizabeth this time about the mileage on
her rental
car she explains that she and her
boyfriend did a lot of sightseeing in
Washington
DC and they went here and they went they
got lost they ended up in
Maryland so I told her I said well we
need to collect some evidence from you
we need to get your fingerprints we need
to get your blood type and we need your
anatomical foot Impressions to compare
with what we found at the scene how do
you feel about doing that and she said
I'll do anything you want me to do it's
not a
problem so a couple days later I
traveled to shawville
and finger
Predator got a vile of her
blood ink the bottom of her
feet and got her to walk across a piece
of
paper she was
cooperating uh with our
investigation in the lab Elizabeth H's
fingerprints and blood are compared to
Sam collected at the crime
scene her fingerprints match prints
found in the home but that is to be
expected her blood type does not match
the blood found in the
bathroom her footprint is inconsistent
with the bloody footprints found at the
scene from the physical evidence Gardner
concludes that Elizabeth did not murder
her parents
uh about this period of time is when we
uh started asking about her
[Music]
boyfriend Gardner recalls that
Elizabeth's boyfriend Yen soring had a
bandage on his hand at the Ham's
memorial
service he decides to ask Yen a few
questions yen saring is 19 years old the
son of a German Diplomat working in the
United States back here
he wanted to convince us that he was
smarter than anybody else highly
intelligent um he dared us for even
talking him about being a
suspect Gardner questions Yen about the
extra mileage on the rental car the
weekend he and Elizabeth drove to
Washington Yen corroborates Elizabeth's
story they got lost and drove around
Washington for
hours and I remember making the
statement but Tim you were major lost
because you put 400 more miles on a car
than than it should have
been Yen sticks to his
story Deputy Gardner asks him to provide
the same samples Elizabeth did Blood
fingerprints and
Footprints Yen says he would like to
cooperate but he
can't he was afraid that his father was
going to be deported out of the country
because his his son yen was a murder
suspect Gardner reassures the young
student he only needs samples to
eliminate him as a
suspect Yen tells Gardner he is too busy
with upcoming
exams at the time he was one of the few
people uh if not the only person that we
had
confronted um about collecting physical
evidence and not received any
cooperation Yen's fin agrees to return
to Bedford on October 16th to provide
prints and blood
samples but on October 15th Deputy
Gardner receives a stunning phone
call it's Walter haome he flew in from
Texas to visit
Elizabeth well when he called the
apartment her roommate answered the
phone and he asked to speak to Elizabeth
and the roommate said well she's not
here and the brother said well when do
you expect her back and she says I don't
and he says well you mean you don't and
she said well she's not she doesn't live
here anymore she's
gone matter of fact when she left she
left you a
letter and also soaring left the
investigators a
letter and he said what do you mean
soaring left letters well he's gone too
Gardner can't believe it the only two
suspects in the brutal murder case have
fled and I drove to Lynchburg picked up
the brother and flew to
Charlottesville Elizabeth had gone yens
had gone and we're going I think we're
on the right track now because they they
have obviously
absconded the
brother that night was very upset with
us and our prosecutor because he thought
that we had let the murders get
away but without hard evidence pointing
to murder police can't arrest the
suspects we went over the the facts of
the case trying to convince the brother
that we did not have enough probable
cause to arrest either one of them yes
hi I'm at the apartment Deputy Gardner
talks to the
roommate she hands over the letters from
Elizabeth and
Yen Elizabeth's letter to her family
says she and Yen left for an unspecified
destination she urges them not to try to
find
her Yen also left a letter it's
addressed to Deputy
Garder Yen's uh left letter basically
saying that um he did not commit the
crimes against the H did not murder the
h
and that they had decided to start a
life on their own he and Elizabeth and
that he regretted the fact that
Elizabeth had supplied us with any
physical
[Music]
evidence Gardner is no longer looking at
a random cult killing he suspects the
brutal double homicide was carefully
planned 21-year-old Elizabeth haome and
19-year-old Yen soring are now the Prime
suspects with credit cards and a head
start by now they could be anywhere in
the
world now Deputy Gardner's Only Hope of
finding
them is
[Music]
interpole in Virginia Derek and Nancy
hesome are brutally
murdered stabbed to death in their own
home
there's a sense that okay whoever did it
wherever they've gone they're not going
to get far tend out not to be the
case as the investigation heats up the
couple's daughter Elizabeth suddenly
disappears along with her boyfriend Yen
saring Deputy Ricky Gardner of the
Bedford County Sheriff's Department
fears he may have lost his suspects and
that they may have gotten away with
murder 2 Days Later investigators
confirm their worst
fears Yen's car was located in a parking
garage at the airport and at that time
we had strong feelings that they had
left the
country I contacted interpole office in
Washington DC to alert them that these
two were suspects in the murders of her
parents
but investigators in the United States
don't have enough evidence to charge
Elizabeth hesome and Yen saring yet the
only thing we had was the the the
mileage and the fact that they
absconded that wasn't enough to convict
them in in court of double
homicide John mhof is the former
director of the US interpole office
unfortunately Ricky doesn't have
sufficient information for a red
notice had he had just a little bit more
time he could have developed the case so
that he could have collected forensic
evidence about yening to allow him to
have the arrest warrant
issued it is yet another blow to the
investigation if Gardner hopes to make a
case against the fugitives he needs more
than circumstantial
evidence he needs to establish a motive
for
[Music]
murder according to Elizabeth she adored
her
parents they doted on her and sent her
to an exclusive British boarding school
we
did but according to family members
Elizabeth ran away just before
graduation we found out that Elizabeth
was primet proper as she led us on to be
in the uh in the initial
interview we learned and in fact that
she had experimented with number of
types of drugs heroin
LSD she gets in trouble she uh takes off
at some point drops
out Elizabeth left wikim ABI with a
friend in Virginia Derek and Nancy
hesome did everything they could to find
their daughter but Elizabeth had
vanished
months later both girls appeared at the
British Consulate in
Berlin she was in a pretty bad situation
uh strung out basically living in
poverty so you know we found out that
Elizabeth was she was a bizarre
character the fact that she did all
these things did not make her make her a
murderer or a murder suspect but it was
inconsistent with the the the Elizabeth
that we talked to in the initial
[Music]
interview Elizabeth's parents arranged
for her to return to the United
States we were seeing two sides of
Elizabeth there the pure and the proper
the Wickham Abby Elizabeth asome and
then the the drug addict
Elizabeth so which one were we dealing
with
there in the fall of 1984
Derek and Nancy hesome enrolled
Elizabeth at the University of
Virginia she was even awarded a
prestigious
scholarship but Elizabeth was still a
troubled young
woman she resented her parents for
controlling her
life Deputy Gardner wonders how deep
that resentment went and how Yen figures
into the
equation really yeah he he questions
students at the University of Virginia
to learn
[Music]
more shortly after Elizabeth entered UVA
she attended a party for scholarship
students there she met Yen soring he was
the son of a German
Diplomat like Elizabeth he had grown up
all over the world he had always been a
bookor a
nerd and when he met Elizabeth with
haome in the fall of 84 he had never had
a romantic relationship before that and
she was
older um worldly with the European
accent he was absolutely
smitten uh he fell in love with
her I mean head over heels in love with
her Elizabeth and Yen were
inseparable they lived in a world of
Their Own
[Music]
Derek and Nancy hesome were as
opinionated about their daughter's
relationship as they were about her
education boyfriend they were against it
they rejected Yen
outright they didn't approve of him he
wasn't good enough for their
daughter Gardner feels he has finally
found a possible motive for the haome
murder if he is right then two brutal
killers are free somewhere in the
world in Bedford County Virginia a small
town cop suspects two college students
are responsible for a brutal double
murder Yen soring has fled the country
flying to
Europe his girlfriend Elizabeth haome
leaves the country on a different
flight deputy Ricky Gardner of the
Bedford County Sheriff's Office contacts
Interpol to help track down the
fugitives hopefully if yens and
Elizabeth were arrested stopped
somewhere overseas their names would pop
up in interpole
files and they would know to contact us
in Bedford
[Music]
County in Europe
Yen and Elizabeth alter their passports
creating false identities to elude
authorities the fake passports work
perfectly they easily travel to Paris
then on to Brussels and Luxembourg by
train in Luxembourg the couple rents a
car and drives to burn Switzerland a
fugitive really has a choice of anywhere
in the world to hide and Ricky Gardner
has a difficult situation with Yen
suring and Elizabeth asome on the Run he
knows they have great facility for
traveling
internationally from Switzerland the
fugitives drive to Bulgaria and finally
into Serbia and Montenegro then known as
Yugoslavia while in the mountains
Elizabeth loses control of the car
[Music]
both Elizabeth and Yen are injured in
the
crash but they can't afford to wait
around for the
police it is too
risky the fugitives abandon the wrecked
car and board a train to
Belgrade from there they take another
train and flee to
Austria in Vienna they run out of
money Elizabeth is forced to make a cash
withdrawal on a credit card in her own
name in the modern world uh credit card
transactions are recorded
instantaneously in 1985 you're four or
five days
from uh having feedback from a specific
credit card
transaction to throw authorities off
their Trail Elizabeth leaves a letter
addressed to one of her friends with a
hotel clerk in
salsburg she tells him to wait a few
days before he mails
it in the letter Elizabeth claims she
and yens are continuing their travels in
Europe in reality the couple flies to
Bangkok
[Music]
Thailand unable to find work their
credit cards maxed out they come up with
a new scheme to get
money first they create several sets of
false identification using local
photographers and print shops I
sophisticated uh a Savvy kid traveling
through southeast Asia would not have
great difficulty in finding somebody
willing to prepare false travel
documentation for them um I would
suspect that Yen suring being the son of
a diplomat was probably more aware of
how easy this
was they use the fake IDs to purchase
Travelers
checks they later report the checks as
stolen and receive cash
refunds on January 8th Elizabeth and Yen
returned to
England they quickly learn their
Travelers check scheme won't work in the
UK the checks are too carefully
scrutinized so they devise a new
scheme using their Forged IDs Yen and
Elizabeth open Accounts at different
banks all over
London they use counter checks and fake
IDs to make purchases at upscale
department stores and later return the
items for
cash the new scheme
Works back in Virginia Deputy Ricky
Gardner and the Bedford County Sheriff's
Office work day and night trying to to
find the fugitives and I'd worked on
this case for about 17 or 18 months and
I'd played out every possible scenario
in my mind about what had
happened everywhere you go people
talking about it asking you about it
living it and they're frustrated they're
frustrated for months and months and
months Terren Samuel is a reporter for
the Rowan Oak times covering the ongoing
investigation they don't know where they
are number one and number two they don't
know what to do when they get them
because they basically don't think they
have any evidence beyond the fact that
you know they
fled for seven long months the young
couple eludes
authorities but in May 1986 they make a
crucial
mistake they're in London they're
running
their check fraud going into department
stores buying stuff for a check
returning it for cash at a different
store
Yen and Elizabeth look
sophisticated they are very well
dressed but a security guard in a
Richmond London clothing store notices
something
strange although they arrive at the
store together they pretend they don't
know each
other they are detained for
questioning detective con Terry Wright
questions the couple at a police station
nearby they had ID cards and um they
were from Canada the names that they
gave at the time were Christopher plat
no and Tara Lucy
no Wright has no way of knowing who he
has in
custody uh these two young people they
just appeared to be young Travelers
young
students the couple claims they have
done nothing wrong
they even allow police to search their
flat inside the flat Wright finds bag
after bag of new
merchandise each one has a valid
department store
receipt but a thorough search of the
room turns up personal letters journals
several passports and a stack of
checkbooks each account is with a
different bank and under a different
name
Terry Wright plows through the couple's
papers looking for evidence of check
fraud we found their genuine passports
so of course now we
realized um that uh that this guy was
actually
yaning and that she was Elizabeth
haome at this point the these names
didn't mean anything to
us still the more right reads the more
uneasy he becomes
the couple's letters and journals
suggest they are on the
Run detective Wright wants to know
why two young murder suspects flee
across Europe and
Asia they use fake IDs to slip across
borders at
will Deputy Ricky Gardner of the Bedford
County Virginia Sheriff's department
works closely with Interpol
he has to find Yen soring and Elizabeth
haome to bring them to
justice in England Constable Terry
Wright arrests the couple for fraud but
he firmly believes there is more to Yen
saring and Elizabeth hesome than meets
the eye it seemed to me that they they
did have something to hide and that it
was obviously something serious and I
was telling people that I thought they'
done a murder even though they didn't
refer to murder death or anything and
everybody sort of said yeah okay well
carry on um and I did I carried on and I
went through
everything he checks to see if they are
wanted in other
countries I asked um Interpol if they
would uh circulate all of the details to
see if they were wanted anywhere I asked
them to I sent them a list of all of
their false identities which amounted to
uh about 15 in
total details of their genuine
identities from their passports um and
asked them if they would send these
details across various different
countries using the Diaries interpole
retraces the couple's travels they send
the information to the United States and
to the countries they traveled through
in Europe and into
Thailand when I got into work uh one
morning uh there was a teleprinter
message waiting for me which had come
through
interpo inter poll confirms right
suspicions Yen and Elizabeth not only
pass bad checks they're suspected
murderers they now knew that I'd
arrested or that we had arrested Yan
sing and Elizabeth H and they were
trying to make contact so that they uh
they could let me know that they were
strongly suspected of the murder of
Derek and Nancy hen the officers that
were trying to get a hold of me were uh
from Bedford County Sheriff's Department
uh in the United States and and uh the
officer in particular was uh an
investigator called Ricky
Gardner investigator Garder yes hello my
name is Terry rght I'm a detective with
the Metropolitan Police in London in
England you I'm almost speechless to the
day because that was a very emotional
telephone conversation because I had
lived this case for like 14 months and
for somebody to call me on a phone and
say that they had those two in jail and
had evidence that they committed a crime
and it was almost too good to be true it
Wright warns Deputy Gardner they must
move quickly in England the two students
are only charged with check fraud there
was a possibility that they could get
bail if they got baale we'd probably
never see them again they'd probably be
able to get hold of uh further false IDs
and just
disappear 5 days later Gardner flies to
England the entire case is at stake they
may never have this chance again
once again Elizabeth hen finds herself
facing Deputy Ricky
Gardner this time she tells him the
truth Elizabeth talked a great deal
about her hatred for her parents and
resentment um and they just they
absolutely controlled her life when she
was in Lynchburg and decided who she
could date and who she couldn't date um
and I think she she just got tired of it
she convinced yens that um he was in our
future but first he had to get rid of
her her parents and um he was willing to
do
that she planted a seed in his Vine and
he was willing to let it
grow as in her previous statements
Elizabeth tells Gardner she and yens
drove from Charlottesville Virginia to
Washington DC where they checked into a
hotel but now she claims Yen didn't go
to the movies
instead he dropped her off at the movie
theater and told her to buy two tickets
to establish an
alibi Yen then drove to the jum's home
in bomboro
Virginia she put that out Danny's head
and when he left Washington that day he
had 4 hours to change his mind and he
didn't he did it he went there and did
exactly what he was he planned to do if
they didn't accept him into Elizabeth's
[Music]
life and that was to
murder hours later Yen returned to the
theater he was covered with
blood he told her he had dealt with her
parents once and for all they were
finally free to live their lives
together she was shocked that he'd
actually gone through with
it she made the statement to me that
things changed the night that yans
murdered her parents because they
controlled and ruled her life up until
that point but after he murdered her
parents and picked her up and they got
back to the Marriott that night R
switched and he became the dominating
and controlling person in her
life so she lost her
parents but she gained
yens and he just took their
place Elizabeth haome is extradited to
the United States to stand
trial in August 1987 she tells a jury
what yens told her the night he returned
from
Charlottesville we said he got to the
residence after dropping Elizabeth off
in
Georgetown yes sir
come
in they invited him
in and offered him something to eat cuz
they were just finishing up dinner
themselves Yen brought up the topic of
his relationship with
Elizabeth he says you know I love your
daughter and I'm asking you for your
permission to date her and possibly get
married sometime and Mr haome was
adamantly opposed to that and he says no
son he says you're not good enough for
our daughter
I'm powerful enough to have you kicked
out of the
country I'll have you kicked out of the
university and that's when yens went and
tackled him and took him down and cut
his
throat Yen then attacks Nancy
[Music]
H investigators are now certain yen
saring is responsible for the brutal
stabbing deaths of Derek and Nancy
jome in August 1989 yen soring is
extradited back to Virginia at trial he
tries to pin the murders on Elizabeth
according to Yen's testimony he was the
one who set up The Alibi she was the one
who killed her own
parents forensic evidence collected at
the crime scene tells a much different
story Yen's foot impression matches a
bloody sock print found inside the asome
home his blood typo was also found in
the Ham's
bathroom in
1987 Elizabeth haome is found guilty of
accessory to
murder she is sentenced to 90
years in 1990 yen soring is found guilty
on two counts of first-degree murder due
to an agreement with the British
government us prosecutor do not seek the
death
penalty instead yen soring is sentenced
to spend the rest of his life in a
Virginia
prison the couple who killed to stay
together will spend the rest of their
lives separated by iron bars in the
early 1980s drug enforcement officers in
Los Angeles wage A desperate battle on
the front lines of the War on Drugs
[Music]
Jim Whitten Works narcotics for the LA
County Sheriff's
Department the market was getting
flooded when law enforcement pressure
increased in Florida the importing
shifted to the West Coast in reaction to
the Crackdown in the East the drug
cartels redirect their deadly traffic
through Mexico into
California La is a wash in
cocaine the Sher Department makes
approximately 100,000 arrests per year
narcotics arrests result in about 18 to
20,000 of those arrests we were seizing
more cash uh in the in the 80s than we'd
ever seen before large amounts of cash
in conjunction with large amounts of
Narcotics local police are overwhelmed
and the DEA steps up their support
there's a connection one of the men on
the front lines is DEA agent Darnell
Garcia all right that's all I got he's
an experienced cop who begins his career
with the LAPD then transfers to the DEA
in
1978 Garcia's friend and fellow drug
investigator Victor Guerrero still works
undercover for the FBI and his identity
must be hidden for his own safety he had
a very infectious personality
uh beamed with confidence and since he
had such an infectious personality and
such a likable name nature that he
instilled confidence in others Darnell
was always able to paint a very Rosy
picture the glasses always half full
never half empty Garcia is close with
two fellow agents Ed Williams and Brian
Hartford come on come on the three men
put their lives on the line every day
fighting what seems like a losing battle
to keep drugs off the
[Music]
street it is dangerous work
but it's work that Garcia does
well he was a very Street Savvy agent
and seemed to know exactly what he was
doing former assistant us Attorney Terry
Bowers worked with Garcia and as an
undercover agent he was able to uh work
the streets well and and come up with
results uh I think he also uh fostered a
bit of a tough guy uh Persona originally
from New York City Garcia moves with his
family to La where he attends high
school he joins the Army and serves 3
years during the Vietnam
era after he gets out of the army he
returns to LA to attend
college he becomes obsessed with martial
arts training with movie star and
martial arts Champion Chuck Norris he
goes on to become a champion himself
Darnell trained very hard and he was a
successful competitor when he was in the
martial arts circuit and eventually
winning the Internationals in Long Beach
Garcia eventually follows his teachers
footsteps Landing several movie roles
including one in the acclaimed Bruce Lee
Epic Enter the
Dragon his competitive nature makes him
a good
cop hands top but for Darnell Garcia
being a good cop isn't enough you know
in a city like La where you have such
extreme wealth and and extreme poverty
the the differential there is always
something you have to live with so with
uh a law enforcement officer who's out
there and exposed to large sums of cash
on a regular basis it's a big Temptation
uh and and I think they really have to
fight the urge particularly if they have
a family don't move Darnell wants to
live the good
life a life his DEA salary can't support
it was a shortcut to life he wanted an
expensive lifestyle he found a venue to
live this lifestyle he wanted to live
and he compromised his ethics as a
result of that Garcia starts taking cash
he justifies this extra income as
repayment for a dangerous and
frustrating job you know I'm out here uh
for the community putting my life on the
line every day and I'm not getting paid
well and I'm getting hassled and uh you
know if I skim couple bucks off the top
of a bag of uh Nar go cash uh who's
going to know and what's the problem
just be sure to check outside the door I
don't want to see anyone see him come in
Garcia enlists the help of his friends
Ed Williams and Brian
Hartford the three agents soon discover
that stealing drugs is as easy as
lifting
cash Darnell Garcia was your worst
nightmare um when people are out in the
field doing the undercover work uh if
they're there too long and they don't
have a real strong moral compass the
lines can start to blur a little bit
because of the millions to be made
dealing drugs in the80s police
corruption is rampant and Garcia and his
gang are in the middle of it operating
inside the
DEA the agency has no
idea he did not have a great deal of uh
respect for the agency that paid his
salary he found where there were some
administrative weaknesses where in fact
fact he could be successful at what he
planned to do and since the opening was
there he took it with each Heist Garcia
becomes
Boulder in January of 1983 Garcia and
his men steal approximately one pound of
cocaine from a DEA
seizure to hide their crime they rely on
expertise glean from years of busting
drug
dealers as an undercover operative you
see what they do on the
street if you're going to go over to
that side you can adopt the same
techniques and and things that they do
dealers on the street often cut their
cocaine with baking soda to increase the
volume of their product garciaa adopts
this tactic
himself after he empties the cocaine
from the evidence bag he replaces it
with baking soda he's careful to leave
just enough cocaine so that when the DEA
tests the bag they will find traces of
coke and never realize Garcia took the
drugs he was just using some of the
techniques he he observed while out uh
has an undercover agent the plan works
DEA officials never noticed that a
switch has been
made in the first 2 years Garcia's
operation makes 10 thefts of Narcotics
worth nearly $300,000
Garcia uses his inside knowledge of
working investigations to keep his
supply of drugs
flowing he Stakes out suspected drug
dealers and finds out where they hide
their drugs he then moves in to take the
drugs before the DEA can make a
bust it is a brilliantly simple
plan he was motivated to take the money
from a drug seizure cuz he thought he
can get away with it so I'm sure he was
very confident that the uh drug
trafficker was not going to bring it up
and neither was he hence no one to
report it no one to hear it Garcia plays
both sides he hides behind his badge to
protect him from any retaliation from
the
dealers former head of interpole in the
United States John mhof ran a narcotic
squad for the FBI in the
1980s they're always ready they're
always ready to prot protect their their
assets and they're ready with heavy
Weaponry for the most part generally
speaking uh drug dealers are are smart
enough not to shoot cops Garcia seems
Untouchable as months pass Harford
Williams and Garcia start their own
narcotics
[Music]
Enterprise he had success taking money
now he has success taking cocaine he had
a readymade market he just needed the
right marketer Garcia knows exactly
where to find them he turns to the
informants from his
investigations he now asks them to sell
his drugs on the
street and one of the great paradoxes of
working drug enforcement investigations
is that you're constantly associating
with the criminal element now your
objective as a legitimate enforcement
officer is to not get sullied by
that it's really surprisingly easy for a
narcotics enforcement officer to find
the route to sell drugs because they've
been dealing with drug dealers uh all
their careers Garcia and his gang create
a distribution Network rivaling any gang
in the
city business is good in fact too
good Garcia and his Partners amass
millions in
profits there's so much money involved
that money becomes
not the uh the be all and end all that
you started out for but a problem you
don't have any place that you can
legitimately stash it the government has
seen to it that if you are putting too
many uh dollars into a bank account
you're going to draw undue attention to
yourself so you have to deal with cash
as cash and it becomes cumbersome Garcia
has to find a place to hide all his
money always the ladies man he enlists
his girlfriend legal secretary Wendy
Bedford to help launder the profits I
thought you'd never make it she buys
cashier checks for
$99,900 a carefully chosen
amount the law requires Banks to report
anything over $10,000 to the
[Music]
government once Garcia collects enough
checks he looks for a place where he can
hide large sums of cash from the prying
eyes of the police
he finds it in
Switzerland in 1983 the three men
traveled to
Zurich here the banking industry is as
powerful as it is
[Music]
discreet and discretion is what clients
like Darnell Garcia count
on Garcia Hartford and Williams each
Open Secret individual bank
accounts in his first it Garcia turns
over 12 cashier checks totaling
$100,000 an impressive score but Garcia
is just getting
[Applause]
[Music]
started at the DEA offices in Los
Angeles Darnell Garcia uses his badge to
mask a drug trafficking operation think
I go back there and get that gym bag
yeah in 1984
Garcia lifts large amounts of drugs from
the
DEA 1 kilo at a
time he thinks the DEA will never notice
any of it is
missing he holds the agency in great
disdain according to his friend and
fellow undercover agent Victor
Guerrero he was always very critical of
the agency their shortcomings a lack of
resources and uh generally their
inexperience and ineffectiveness
I'll bring back in
1985 the agency transfers Garcia from LA
to Detroit but he refuses to go yeah you
know procedure the DEA fires him got to
keep all the records straight I cannot
characterize Darnell as a good Agent he
was a malc content from the onset of his
commencement of his career with
DEA Garcia fights back and brings a
discrimination suit against the
agency it is a Brazen accusation from a
man who has been stealing from the
agency for
years but Garcia wins the suit and the
DEA is forced to reinstate
him his success only emboldens
him in October of 1984 1 kilogram of
heroin is reported missing from the DEA
Evidence fault those are that's my
signature at first the agency confronts
the evidence custodian
but he denies all knowledge of the
crime according to signin sheets many
agents had access to the Vault including
Darnell
Garcia the DEA opens an internal
investigation and administers polygraph
tests to some of the
suspects several agents refuse to take
polygraph tests Garcia is one of them
he's able to walk away from the offer of
a polygraph uh that he clearly would
have failed uh you can't be forced to
take that paragraph So he gets to walk
away and he gets a thumb his nose at the
internal affairs
folks in 1985 within conclusive results
from the polygraph the DEA begins
investigating everyone who had access to
the evidence Locker the list includes
Brian Hartford and Darnell Garcia but
Garcia is not deterred greed had taken a
stronger hold of him he thought that DEA
would not even discover his
activities and as a result of being
overconfident he became Bolder and
Bolder as the weeks and months went
[Music]
by Garcia remains with the agency and in
November of
1985 after staking out a series of drug
safe houses the men are ready to make
their
move the agents have been targeting one
of LA's biggest
dealers the three men believe this bust
will make their
[Music]
careers inside Garcia makes the record
books find in 400 lb of cocaine with an
estimated street value of $18
million one of the largest stashes ever
uncovered in Los
Angeles you really don't know what
you're going to find most times it and
sometimes it's an amazing moment because
the amount of money and the amount of
product that you can come across in some
of these places it's just a stound but
there are no press conferences no photos
with the mayor
in fact Garcia never records the
bus the DEA has no idea it
happened Garcia takes all the coke to
fuel his own distribution
Network to hide their millions in
profits the men look
overseas their illegal money goes
straight into secret numbered bank
accounts in Europe Garcia and his gang
make their deposits in cash
just as the three men begin to think
they are unstoppable police get a
break in 1986 deputies from the Los
Angeles County Sheriff's Department
apprehend a pair of known drug
dealers the bust seems routine until the
drug dealers start
talking under interrogation they reveal
their drug
Source One of the suppliers is a man who
works in law
enforcement his name is Brian
Hartford the investigators run the name
through their database and learn
Hartford is a DEA agent working in
La the agents also run down information
on all hartford's Associates and learn
he is close with Darnell Garcia and Ed
Williams the DEA steps up surveillance
on the three men the agency has to be
extremely careful who they include in
the investigative
team investigating your own is is a
problem on a number of levels there
probably folks that you don't want to
bring into that investigation because
they are his friends he knows all of the
tools that can be brought to bear
against him and uh can take guard
against those things the agents learn
Hartford is a frequent guest at Garcia's
apartment in La near DEA
headquarters they question an employee
at the apartment complex and she tells
them Garcia always pays his rent in
cash but the more agents look into
Garcia and his friends the more complex
the man
becomes it seems his apartment is not
his primary
residence one of the big red flags is
unexplained affluence so uh you look or
a new big house or a new car or a boat
things of that nature that don't
necessarily match up with the salary of
the
agent they learned that in 1987 Garcia
built a new home for his family in
Rancho Pelos veres an exclusive suburb
in Southern
California in the early 80s DEA agents
probably earned somewhere around $40 to
$50,000 per
year they went and saw the home probably
worth about a half a million dollars at
the time I caution Darnell says that uh
better be careful about having some of
your co-workers conv visit you they're
going to wonder how you paid for this
Garcia assures his friend he inherited
the money for the down payment after the
death of a
relative he says he borrowed the
rest officials look at the people close
to Garcia hoping to find anything or
anyone that seems
incriminating when somebody's engaged in
a crime where they're generating large
sums of cash and they have to launder it
uh it generally is easier if you have a
cohort whether it's a spouse or a
girlfriend Garcia they discover has
both the handsome DEA agent is adept at
leading a double life at work and at
home though it is unclear what if
anything the women know of his illicit
activities if Garcia is in collusion
with anyone he hides it well the
detectives on his Trail do not see him
meet with any known drug
dealers all they have are suspicions so
far Garcia isn't giving them any hard
evidence they can use to link him to any
criminal
activity Ze William young
29 but his phone records show a
pattern Garcia is making frequent calls
to a number in New York
Bon the DEA contacts the NYPD and asks
for
help the number belongs to a former DEA
informant Howard calhon now a known drug
dealer
is how are the DEA questions
calone but he denies all knowledge of
Garcia Hartford or Williams could I have
a seat thank you skeptical of his story
the detective search his apartment
Williams some letters and a number
scribbled in his address book blow the
case wide open they are Garcia's
initials and phone
number faced with this evidence calhon
and his girlfriend
confess the DEA learns a large number of
overnight packages had been arriving at
Cal Hon's
apartment they trace the origin of the
packages to an address in Los Angeles
the packages were coming from Garcia and
his accomplice Brian
Hartford Howard calone tells the DEA
that Garcia and his men ship their drugs
to him in overnight
packages he said he would then sell the
drugs and ship the profits back to
California
overnight the system was low Tech but
effective the receipts from the
overnight delivery service are the proof
authorities need to arrest the Rogue
agents so Garcia and his men can't tip
each other off the DEA plans to take all
three men into custody at the same
time after three long years of
investigating Garcia and his gang on
November 22nd 1988 police make their
move Brian Hartford is arrested outside
his home without incident
Edward Williams is also
arrested like his partner he does not
[Music]
resist completing their Roundup
authorities surround the home of Darnell
Garcia
[Music]
Darnell home no he's
not look at the house you can't come in
there you have to arresting officers
find nothing to lead them to their
suspect only photos celebrating his fast
life Darnell Garcia the DEA agent turned
drug dealer seems to have
[Music]
vanished in November
1988 Federal agent and suspected drug
dealer Darnell Garcia vanishes just
hours before he was to be
arrested but how did he do it the only
way he could have known they were coming
to arrest him was if someone on the
inside tipped him
off agents talk to Garcia's friends and
discover yet another girlfriend employed
at the LA County Courthouse you have any
other questions she admits seeing his
arrest warrants and warning Garcia
but she has no idea where he
is well the initial frustration is that
they're gone it's just very frustrating
to have a case worked up as a prosecutor
and then you can't find the defendant
months pass and Federal grand juries in
Los Angeles issue three superseding
indictments the County of Los Angeles
charges Garcia with 26 counts including
conspiracy Poss I and distribution of
Narcotics multiple currency reporting
and tax
violations the DEA keeps up surveillance
on the missing agent but Garcia does not
return
home Donell Garcia is a sophisticated uh
Target But ultimately uh operating under
an alien is a very difficult thing to do
and even if you're a law enforcement
officer there are a lot of loose ends
that can be pulled uh in order to to let
law enforcement track you down the DEA
digs deep into Garcia's personnel file
and list of known
contacts they keep up the pressure and
talk with anyone who might know where he
has
fled no one has seen or heard from
[Music]
him then 2 months after Garcia's
disappearance police get a call that
someone has spotted him at a North
Hollywood
club hungry for for a break in the case
Federal and local law enforcement take
to the streets and the
skies they are determined not to let him
slip away
again it seems unlikely Garcia is still
in LA but with the crafty and arrogant
agent anything is
possible he felt the DEA was inept
couldn't find him he was smarter than
DEA and law
enforcement for the second time in 2
months officials come up
empty police are no closer to catching
their
man or grasping his
motives and by June of
1989 Garcia is still on the
lamb the DEA keeps his wife Anita and
his 12-year-old child under surveillance
but they also vanish Without a
Trace with his family now gone the DEA
suspects Garcia has broken all ties with
the US and he is going to try and
disappear
forever in today's world you can get
anywhere on the globe uh very quickly
and often very easily if you're willing
to uh lay out the necessary cash you
definitely want to try and track the
individual down as quickly as possible
to stop his flight investigators need to
find where Garcia is hiding his cash and
confiscate
it the DEA looks into his finances here
according to Garcia's Financial papers
he took a loan from an Italian
businessman to pay for his fancy new
home I don't know this they soon
discovered the loan was a fake you've
never heard the paper forged by Garcia
to cover the fact that he bought the
house with drug money so let me
understand clearly you don't recogn this
document nor the
signature further investigation reveals
the true source of funding a wired
transfer of
$420,000 from a bank in Switzerland made
in May of
1987 this is
scratched during the course of the
investigation the DEA asked Switzerland
to provide access to Garcia's
accounts but by the time authorities
identify the bank it is too late Garcia
closed the
account but the DEA continues to follow
the trail pouring over Garcia's
Financial
records the agents uncover the existence
of a second account in
Luxembourg they think they may have
found Garcia and turned to interpole for
help the interpole uh network is
virtually exhausted and when they
brought broadcast a message it goes out
to every one of those countries and most
of those countries have the means to
effectively disseminate that information
so that people staying in hotels there
people crossing the borders there people
uh conducting Financial transactions
there um are compared against that
database the tiny nation of Luxembourg
is tucked between France and Germany but
its small size masks an economic Giant
here interpo agents and local police
bear a heavy case
load the country's strategic position
and its role as a banking center make it
a frequent stopping point for criminals
from all parts of the
world the DEA contacts Pierre Conan who
works for interpole in Luxembourg and
tells him to be on the lookout for
Darnell Garcia
da considered him a a very dangerous
person tracking down a skilled and
trained police officer who knows how to
avoid to be caught is much more
difficult than a normal
criminal Conan goes to the bank that
issued the
check yet once again they are too late
Garcia has recently closed the account
for the bank manager the transaction is
memorable so first of all he picked up
the money in
cash he put it into a plastic
bag over $3
million and he asked as a bank manager
would you mind to come out with me and I
will show you my
vehicle and that's what the bank manager
did he was gassing it would be a nice
sports car so hospitable here to me but
there is no Ferrari just a
bike the manager recognizes a rental
sticker from a
hotel Conan might be able to use this
small clue to bring down this DEA agent
turned drug
dealer fugitive Darnell Garcia surfaces
in Luxembourg in June
1989 then promptly disappears carrying
$3 million in a plastic
bag interbull believes that if Garcia is
in Luxembourg it may be their best
chance to find him interpoles John
mhof Darnell Garcia might be a
sophisticated law enforcement officer
but he's a Stranger in a Strange Land no
matter where he goes he's an American
and he's going to stand out there more
than he would and Southern
California interpole can exploit that
Garcia was last seen riding a bike which
interpo agents track down to a nearby
Hotel staff members remember Garcia
easily he's a frequent
guest Conan traces phone records from
Garcia's room to a travel agency in
Luxembourg as a result of this
information we of course went to the
travel agency
a young woman a travel agent remembers
Garcia he had given her a lot of
business they were able to identify him
as one of their clients who a couple of
times had flown from Luxemburg to
Paris we weren't able to trace in any
Freer but uh we just had the the hope
that he would show up again Conan again
turns his attention to the money
we started thinking that the money would
still be in lxb oh if you uh withdraw uh
over $3 million cash in a plastic bag
riding away on your bicycle we were
thinking that he went to put the money
into another account with another
bank but a survey of area Banks comes up
empty this is uh Darnell Garcia has not
opened a new
account but where is he taking his
money back in Los Angeles officials have
a
theory well one thing when you're
tracking a fugitive um generally it
helps to look for some sort of affinity
or or hobby or uh sport that the
individual likes because that may give
you opportunities to track him
down Darnell Garcia had a particular
affinity for Grand Prix RAC
but finding one man among the crowds
attending the French Grand Prix will be
nearly
impossible held in July near
Marseilles the race attracts thousands
of fans it's the perfect place to blend
in and
disappear the DEA and interpole are
undeterred they scour Hotel records and
reservations across the
country all searching for Darnell G
in Paris on July 3rd 1989 with less than
a week before the Big Race French police
assisting the DEA and interpole get
lucky while inspecting guest registers
they discover Garcia's wife and son
checked in at a hotel in
Paris perhaps Garcia is in the country
for the race
they dispatch agents to watch his wife
in case Garcia
shows but while French police keep watch
for the elusive
criminals less than 200 miles away in
Luxembourg um I don't Garcia makes an
uncharacteristic
misstep thank you he goes to the travel
agency to cash in a plane
ticket he had at one point made a
reservation and paid for a round trip to
Paris but he never had used it so
basically the travel agency owed him
some 200 bucks he wants his refund it is
incredible the man hiding Millions would
put himself at risk for such a small
amount of
money the woman cannot let Garcia slip
away she waits for her opportunity then
steps away and calls
police she tells Conan that Garcia is
about to leave the agency and begs the
police to
hurry Conan urges her to stall delay do
anything she can to keep their suspect
in place was very urgent that we would
get to the scene as quickly as possible
my partner and myself we just took our
guns jumped into the
car for more than 7 months Darnell
Garcia eludes the law Pier Conan finally
has the chance to take this dangerous
criminal into custody but without a
backup if anything goes wrong an
innocent woman is in danger of becoming
a hostage or
Worse police have never been closer to
catching International fugitive Darnell
Garcia but with only two men to take
down the ex- narcotics agent Pierre
Conan is
worried this was a very in a way a very
delicate situation and we didn't know if
he was armed or whether he was not armed
so we approached him and simultaneously
we uh draw our guns
free the first thing you realized with
two
357 mum at his
head he was arrested because being so
greedy going back to this travel agency
for 200 bucks
after 7 years of illicit drug deals and
7 months on the run the bars finally
slam shot on Darnell
Garcia but now there is a new concern
for the police getting Garcia extradited
back to the
US the DEA contacts Mary Joe grotenrath
at the Department of
Justice experienced working with
Interpol she SP specializes in getting
criminals back from Europe and then I
took a good look at the Luxembourg
treaty because we hadn't used that one
for quite a while it was a very old
treaty as I
recall so old that it did not even have
a provisional arrest request in
it that means the government of
Luxembourg cannot detain Garcia for
extradition I didn't want to take that
for an answer right away so I I talked
to the uh Luxembourg
authorities and said uh what can we do
we have a really old treaty and we have
a really bad guy located there very
serious fugitive Luxembourg officials
find a local law allowing them to hold
Garcia for 30 days if grout and wrath
requests it and provides them with
sufficient evidence of Garcia's
crimes the 30 days is better than no
days and so we sent them the request now
to gain Garcia's extradition back to the
US officials must present their case to
a Luxembourg
court all 26 charges of drug trafficking
money laundering and tax
evasion but the investigators still have
a problem they haven't found the money
he was allegedly
laundering at the end of the 30 days he
would have been released they would have
had no choice no matter what he did
their law did not permit them to hold
him longer so the clock started started
ticking interpole and the DEA have to
come to terms with the fact that Garcia
might slip
away the hardest part of the job is
finding the person and not getting him
back or her and this happens sometimes
it's a temporary defeat and
sometimes you just don't get the person
back um and you live with that while us
officials work to secure extradition
Conan keeps his eye on Garcia in
jail he hopes he will make some sort of
slip up that will lead him to the money
book you know maybe three four Garcia's
wife is a frequent
visitor but she is not the only
one I might need soon after his arrest a
couple of days later he uh got visited
by his wife and the day later or perhaps
it was the other way around by his
girlfriend one who was visiting Garcia
in the morning the other was visiting
him in the
afternoon it was obvious that both were
very much in love with d
Garcia or at the very least they are
fond of his $3
million Conan tries to use this against
him Conan sets up surveillance on
Garcia's girlfriend and his wife hoping
one of the women will lead them to the
$3 million
but the surveillance goes nowhere
neither one enters a bank or does
anything
suspicious Pierre Conan suspects
Garcia's wife knows she is being
followed she was probably trained by
Garcia to notice the specific
indications of a surveillance and since
this we were able to follow her for for
half an hour and then we had to give
up determined to locate the money
and his team focus on the paper trail
Garcia left
behind we were analyzing uh all the
documents he had with him he had two
suitcases full of of
stuff going through the suitcases Conan
comes across a new
lead hidden in some of Garcia's notes is
a
number police trace the number to a bank
in
Luxembourg the bank has no active
account with darn Garcia's name
attached they searched the records and
find an account opened with nearly $3
million under one of Garcia's
aliases but once again the account is
empty however the bank manager remembers
Mrs
Garcia his wife had trown off a couple
of days after his arrest with a power of
attorney and she had withdrawn all the
money from the bank it seems the $3
million has vanished police spread the
word to banks in Luxembourg asking them
to look out for any accounts opened or
closed around the period of Garcia's
arrest several banks have accounts that
fit the
description Garcia's wife made the
deposits he had given her the money for
safekeeping she along with his
girlfriend opened several accounts under
different names
[Music]
Conan and interpole finally locate the
$3
million the DEA now has enough to get
Garcia out of the country and to put him
behind bars in the US for a very long
[Music]
time Garcia's wife Anita is arrested as
is his girlfriend and the bank accounts
seized
Luxembourg Police Hold Garcia for 6
months on charges of using a fake
passport after that time the DEA working
with the Department of Justice uses six
counts of drug possession and narcotics
trafficking to finally bring Garcia back
to the
US in Los Angeles Brian Hartford and Ed
Williams plead guilty to drug
trafficking
charges Harford is sentenced to 10 years
and Williams to 5 years in exchange for
their testimony against
Garcia Luxembourg police sentenced
Garcia's wife to 4 years and his
girlfriend to 3 years both women skip
bail and to this date have never served
the
time on November 15th
1991 Darnell Garcia stands trial in the
US
his friend undercover FBI agent Victor
Guerrero testifies against him well I've
testified to many many many trials this
is the first time I had to testify
against a friend uh but it was the right
thing to do
uh he had uh certainly tarnished our
friendship by the actions he had taken
and as a law enforcement officer that
it's my obligation to either
substantiate or negate the allegations
against individual be friend be AO makes
no
difference on April 16th 1991 Darnell
Garcia is found guilty of selling
cocaine and
heroin and laundering millions of
dollars of proceeds through European
Banks he is fined $1.6 million and
sentenced to 80 years in
prison for years Garcia and his gang
betrayed their badges by using them to
hide their drug
dealings so there's a certain sense
amongst narcotics investigators that U
were trying to empty the ocean with a
bucket some will uh succumb to the
frustration and uh uh become cynical
about it to the point where they become
involved with it and I think in the case
of uh Donell Garcia that's what occurred
but in the end the men were tripped up
by their greed
the DEA interpole and Luxembourg police
put them behind bars alongside the very
drug pushers they had busted years
[Music]
earlier August 12th
1997 Scottdale
Arizona 10:45 a.m. business as usual at
a local
bank and then
[Music]
the gunman threatens to shoot anyone who
touches the
alarm dead you hear me he orders the
tellers to dump their cash drawers and
hit the
[Music]
floor it appears he plans to execute
them
but instead he flees with $32,000 in
[Music]
cash the traumatized tellers wait for
the car to peel away then rush to lock
up the bank and hit the alarm did you H
the alarm yes
yes un the nearest patrol officers take
several minutes to arrive
[Music]
okay I'm on the
way the call also reaches Detective Tom
Van Meter of Scottsdale's violent crime
Squad I remember running out of the
station because it's every cop stream to
you know get to a scene and catch
somebody in
[Music]
progress but the gunman's already off
and moving
fast he pulls into a parking lot to
ditch the getaway
car he has it all worked
out to get the cops off his tail he
creates a
[Music]
distraction if he can't outrun the
police he can at least slow them
down buying a chance to disappear behind
a ball of flame and
confusion a emergency operators dispatch
firefighters and more police units to
The Inferno leaving fewer officers to
inspect the crime
scene it's a lot for the Suburban
Phoenix police force to handle at once
Scottdale is kind of a small community
in the south end of town don't have that
many Patrol units can respond to each
individual
call when the first officer arrives at
the bank the rattled employees give an
account of the robbery the thief war is
stocking so the victims can describe
only his clothes and vague physical
features not much to go on but police
spread the
word the description matches a man seen
at the carfire a white male athletic
build light brown hair wearing a white
shirt and
[Music]
jeans at the time Phoenix police have a
chopper in the air it speeds to scotdale
to Aid the search
efforts from their bird's eye view the
Pilots spot a dark colored sedan racing
away from the area of the
carfire helicopter pilot Officer Larry
halis follows keeping a safe distance to
avoid
notice the down there we were trying to
be as syruptitious as possible in
following this vehicle because we didn't
want him to know that we knew where he
was at and we were trying to stay behind
him but he can't go unnoticed for long
and he can't call Scottsdale Police
directly he has to to relay his location
through
dispatch every second he risks being
spotted the Scot scale Police Department
had an entirely different radio system
than Phoenix Police Department which
caused a little bit of a problem with
regards to getting timely information to
their units on the
[Music]
ground the delay proves too long to
remain undetected the suspect
erratically changes Direction trying to
ditch the surveillance it went East for
a while and then back West and I think
uh perhaps uh being aware of our
presence that the driver might have uh
tried to determine if in fact that we
were tracking
him still they stick with him radioing
positions until the car slips into a
shopping
[Music]
mall unfort Ely by that time the vehicle
had gone into uh a parking garage and
had gone out of our
site all the while detective Van Meter
coordinates the frenzy of police
activity on the ground we had to do a
multitude of things at once and it had
to go
quickly I had units responding to the
bank I had units going to the fire scene
to tell me about the car that's on fire
and then the FBI joins me at the mall
and then we start the joint
investigation in regards to locating
him in the mall garage officers find the
car the helicopter Pilots
trailed they're not sure if it has any
connection to the fire and robbery until
they check inside you can see in the
right front passenger seat that there
was a backpack which had a lot of
currency that was hanging out of the
backpack you could also see a panty hose
that was laying on top of the money it's
the right car but no sign of the robber
or his weapon he might have slipped into
the mall or had a third vehicle planted
in the
garage in other words he could be
anywhere it was pretty chaotic we had
Scott Police Department we had Phoenix
Police Department join us we had the FBI
show up and we had internal security at
the mall the mall covers a four block
area 200 stores thousands of
[Music]
Shoppers and police have only a vague
description to go
on that and the
car but the rber keeps changing his look
[Music]
detective V meter learns this guy did
his homework he finds a receipt for a
police scanner he was monitoring our
radio traffic so he heard us chasing him
which means he knew about the
chopper but maybe he didn't count on it
maybe it caused him to make a
mistake that could explain why he left
the loot
behind even better inside the car Van
Meter makes another startling
find a
wallet inside
ID for a man named Craig
[Music]
Pritchard it only raises more questions
does the wallet belong to the suspect or
did he leave it as a decoy to throw
investigators off his
sent police have no
idea but they're about to find out they
run Craig pritchard's name through the
criminal database I directed other
detectives to start doing a series of
criminal checks to find out am I looking
for a person who's a first-time bank
robber am I looking for somebody who's a
wanted dangerous criminal that is now
somewhere around the garage area
possibly into the mall itself whoever he
is he's armed security alerts all stores
to be on the
lookout employees at a men's clothing
shop call in the first
sighting a customer has just bought new
clothes there and left his old ones
behind the discarded items match the
suspect's original
description more time Ticks by as police
prepare an updated description that must
go out to multiple law enforcement
agencies and every store in the mall we
have a wanted fugitive described as a
white male at 180 lb 5'
10 detective V meter coordinates from
the parking garage it sounds crazy but
he feels confident the thief will return
to his car I person stayed with the car
in the past I've had people Circle the
area then asally come back to their
vehicle and get
away but the guy is a
chameleon Van Meter learns the suspect
changed clothes again this is no first
time
criminal he's thinking so he's not
panicked he's thinking what do I do now
how do I get out of this and he starts
changing the clothes well somebody's
going to see me do this I'll do it again
you know for a bank robber to change
clothes three times pretty good suspect
description at last the ID check on the
wallet comes
through Craig Michael Pritchard has
surfed time for bank
robbery their man has a history of
violent
heists they've seen the heist they don't
want to see the violence in a shopping
mall full of people cornering Pritchard
could spell disaster first case
scenarios that we would confront him and
he would try and harm as many of us that
he could being police officers or take a
hostage to try and get away and some
innocent person would get hurt or
killed but confronting Craig Pritchard
won't happen soon Van Meter and his
officers have to find him
first get your hand get out here on
August 12th 1997 Craig Pritchard walks
into an Arizona Bank whips out a pistol
and walks out with
$32,000 cash police track him to a
nearby mall but Pritchard
disappears Detective Tom Van Meter locks
down the site but fears for the
customers inside we knew he was armed we
knew he was dangerous we knew about his
criminal past as far as bank robberies
and his violence
potential police swarm the area but find
nothing after a frantic 6-hour search V
meter calls his investigators in somehow
Craig Pritchard slipped past him
the hunt shifts to a measured
investigation of Craig pritchard's
life they start with his last known
address an apartment in
Scottdale on the rental application
there was two people in the apartment
being Craig and his girlfriend contacted
her at work she came
home I spoke to her identified myself
told her why we were there told her we
were in a hurry we didn't have time to
play games and and it was we need to
find greig Michael Pritchard before he
hurts
anybody the girlfriend knew Craig had a
record but swears she had no idea he
planned to hit the bank in
Scottdale she says he called her earlier
that day he sounded upset and said he
could never see her again now she knows
why and then we get the basic
information from her who he is where he
is family friends relatives in the area
and then we send other people out to his
mom and dad's house his dad's business
his sister's house so we start watching
those places thinking how is he going to
get out of here how is he going to leave
town police turned to the public for
help we tried to get as much news
coverage as we could on it in regards to
putting his face on the
news that evening the story leads the
local
news believe the man is known as Craig
perard he is considered armed and
dangerous it pays off off employees at a
bar near the mall recognized the photo
of Pritchard they called the
police I went over and spoke to those
individuals learned that a subject did
come in right after the bank robbery
they say Pritchard had a few drinks made
a couple of phone calls and calmly
watched the drag net outside they said
he continuously looked out the window as
the patrol units had the mall surrounded
after a few hours hours he left carrying
a large bag police figure he called
someone for a ride and fled the area
without anyone taking
notice with Pritchard On The Run police
have to figure out where to start
looking they need to know more about
pritchard's
background they don't have to look far
fellow officers including the assistant
chief had actually gone to school with
Craig Pritcher so I was getting all the
stories all the background information
it was actually helping
me Richard was a star baseball player in
both high school and college he even had
a shot at the majors until a new man
named Barry Bonds joined the team
outshined and disillusioned he quit
college and eventually left his wife and
kids assistant us attorney Michael K
Craig Pritchard seemed to have a lot of
things going for him in the world uh for
some reason um he began to rob banks
Pritchard served 5 years at the Federal
Detention Center in Arizona for armed
bank robbery until his release in June
1996 once out it took him just over a
year to resume his bad habit maybe he
was planning his comeb back all along
normally there's an underlying problem
um either substance abuse or gambling in
this case we don't see a lot of evidence
of any of those things with Craig
Pritchard so it's really kind of a
mystery why he became a bank robber
other than it's an easy way to get a lot
of money investigators check hotels
rental cars anything to find a lead the
FBI works with the Scottdale police
because bank robbery is a federal crime
since the FBI was involved there was a
nationwide uh bulletin that went out
giving a brief description of the
robbery uh photographs of Craig Michael
Pritchard and a description of
him authorities arrested Pritchard for
his first robbery as he boarded a flight
for Australia they alert all border
crossings and international airports
we needed to pull all stops out to try
and find him quickly because we felt
that he's not going to go find a real
job he's going to go out and do exactly
what he did before and he'll just get
better at it especially with
help within a few weeks Pritchard
arrives in New
[Music]
Mexico in a bar he meets an ambitious
salesman the two strike up a
conversation and the man introduces him
to his sister Nova Guth
she and Pritchard hit it off Nova grew
up in a conservative religious home
fresh out of college she's looking for
adventure and with Craig Pritchard she
gets more than she bargained
for Halloween
1997 Durango
Colorado it's 4:30 p.m. and the bank
tellers start closing up for the day
before they lock up they switch off the
surveillance
video and Pritchard makes his
move your hands up don't that let's you
right now you hear me let's go he
bypasses the cash drawers where the
marked bills are
capped he orders the tellers to head to
the
Vault get that on your knees that on
your knees you get in there and fill his
bag with large
bills Pritchard keeps in constant
contact with his new
accomplice outside Nova keeps
watch again Pritchard threatens to kill
everyone in the bank if they resist and
he orders them to lie face down but this
time he binds them with plastic zip
[Music]
ties in an instant it's over
go go go go go step on let's go the
bandits make off with more than
$64,000 in a matter of
minutes twice the take of the Scottsdale
hit and with the addition of a driver a
smoother
Escape once the tellers finally freed
themselves and hit the alarm Durango
Police rush to the scene not knowing the
situation they take up positions outside
in case the gunman's holding hos
hostages Durango Police Detective Tom
Boyce initial concern is is their safety
are the robber still in the bank is
there still a threat to the employees or
any other citizens uh in that immediate
area dispatch calls the bank to send one
employee
out sir FBI put your hands on top of
your
head when the teller assures them the
gunman's gone and taken no
[Music]
hostages the investigation
begins police learned the gunman came in
just as the surveillance cameras went
off certainly no
coincidence he wore a
mask easy to get away with on Halloween
SC and he wasn't alone he had a getaway
driver and look out the teller did
overhear some radio traffic of always
come over that radio saying that there
was someone outside walking by he left
virtually no clues nothing to ID the
gunman the flex ties used to bind the
victim's wrist and ankles were left
behind some coins and maybe a few single
bills of currency were left behind door
was standing open on that Vault that's
essentially it very for the most part a
very clean scene detective Boyce knows
he's after Pros
it was very well planned it showed
surveillance was done prior to the
robbery by the suspects they knew the
layout of the bank they knew the Bank's
hours and I think it was pretty obvious
that they hit it right at closing
time police turn up a witness who
describes the suspect jumping into a car
driven by a woman with short dark
hair but he didn't get the license plate
nothing solid to follow up
on FBI Bank squads regularly share
information on Unsolved
cases Scottsdale's suspect Craig
Pritchard fits the general description
of the Durango
robber right down to his aggressive
style then 5 months later another
holiday another
Heist on March 17th of 1998 another
robbery occurred in Aztec New Mexico
which is about 38 to 40 Mi south of
Durango that robbery occurred on St
Patrick's Day it's like Durango all over
again a masked gunman empties The Vault
and binds the tellers with plastic zip
ties during the robbery he speaks with
his Lookout and getaway driver through a
radio the general description fits Craig
Pritchard that gives police something to
go on Pritchard likes to ditch his cars
to throw off eyewitnesses so
investigators follow a hunch we decided
to go ahead and check our toe records I
did find that one of our Patrol officers
had in fact towed a vehicle from a city
parking lot which is about a block
further south from where our bank was
located agents Ed the vehicle
identification number or vin to track
down the original
owner he explains he recently sold the
car to a woman named Nova Guth
and her
boyfriend police learn guth's family
lives nearby they tell investigators
that they haven't heard from her or her
boyfriend in
months now authorities have two
suspects when Nova Guthrie calls to
check in with her family she learns the
FBI had come calling asking difficult
questions what the FBI the FBI it's time
to move
fast the couple the Press will call the
modern day Bonnie and Clyde take off in
search of a new home base and a new
[Music]
Target the FBI and police Across the
Western us seek Craig Pritchard and Nova
guthy for a series of armed bank
robberies the Press dubs them the
modernday Bonnie and C romanticizing the
couple's crime
spree it is a sentiment detective V
meter does not
share when people come in and point a
gun at your head tell you to lay on the
ground they start swearing and yelling
and cussing at you um you don't know
with that Amenia moment two seconds
later you know the light's going to go
out it's going to be all over
with Craig Pritchard is no folk hero he
is a dangerous criminal
but the media's portrayal of pritchard's
charismatic Rogue tells only half the
story after a failed bid at professional
baseball Pritchard abandons his wife and
three kids and commits a series of armed
robberies he gets caught does time and
emerges owing almost
$100,000 in child
support his accomplice Nova Guthrie
lives a privileged Life as a college
student and plans for a career as a
pediatrician but after after graduation
she meets Pritchard and falls in love
seduced by The Outlaw life she abandons
any plans of a career and her
conservative religious
upbringing pritchard's no typical bank
robber correct Richard did his homework
this guy's methodical he knows what he's
doing and his type has a name he's a
takeover robber the most dangerous
kind most bank robbers quiet hand to
teller a note run off with a few
thousand and get caught quickly not
priter he boldly takes control of the
entire Bank threatening with his
gun with takeover robbers there is
always the threat the robbery will end
in
Bloodshed and Tom Van Meter knows it's
just a matter of time before somebody
gets killed he won't give
up I would run 50 state driver's license
checks on him every 6
months I would check under his
children's name I would check under
family members names it's kind of a
personal Vendetta that I will find him I
don't care what it takes I don't care
how long it
takes but the two stay under police
radar until they run out of cash and
decide to strike
again this time in the Pacific Northwest
the employees of a small Bank in Bend
Oregon have no idea the trouble just
blew into
town branch manager Bill
Olen thank you you're welcome it wasn't
any different than any other Friday
night uh activity at the branch until
closing time about 2 minutes to 6 that
evening I went to the front door to lock
the door as I did typically and his
typical a ended right
[Music]
there get now he was yelling very
hostile get out of here he would kill us
uh blow our heads off if in fact alarm
was set particularly the silent alarm
which instantly alerts the police he had
with him a police scanner and he was
monitoring it and he told us if alarm
was set that he would know it the
employees are trained to comply fully
trained to survive it is not worth it to
be a hero or in any way try to to try to
stop the robbery you know you you become
very compliant and you do what they tell
you to do when the zip ties come out
olssen relies on another sort of
training when I was a young child I'd
watched the show I believe it was Sky
King on Saturday morning and and in it
they it was one of the tricks they
taught you if you were to be tied up you
you placed your wrist in a certain angle
so when the straps or the Rope is tied
all you need to do is rotate your wrists
and your hands can come free hurry up
lady I all day the gunman orders one
teller to open the vault and fill his
bag with large
bills he demanded the money only From
the Vault he he told us I don't want any
money from the teller drawer knowing
that that's marked knowing that there's
silent alarms that can be tripped the
asant is aggressive with his gun he
would from time to time point to the
other two to keep them uh in line I
guess uh but he'd always bring it back
to my head we were kneeling in the vault
area not knowing what could happen uh if
if he would shoot all three of us he'd
shoot any of us the scanner crackles but
no calls of a bank
robbery the whole time because of my
proximity to him I could hear the uh the
background noise of the police and the
different calls that were going out
[Music]
get on the ground get on the ground face
down put your
hand lady you got that you got that one
last threat of death and then he unlocks
the door and
vanishes Olsen's Sky King escape plan
works and he quick frees himself get the
door I'll be right back he spots a light
colored car speeding away but can't get
a plate
number okay can you get your
[Music]
leg we were fortunate that we weren't
Hurt No we have no it could have gone
just as bad the other way ahead yes
something occurred over his monitoring
device that he felt threatened uh I I
truly believe he could could have just
as easily shot all three of
us police determin the robber nabbed
more than
$120,000 they find no usable evidence no
fingerprints no real
description Bend police detective
Sergeant Kurt kuster all the things the
wearing the gloves the the concealment
of his identity the the radio that he
was wearing it tells you that this is an
experienced bank robber this is not the
first time this person robbed a bank
only a pro hits this clean a home run so
you start uh you know turning over every
rock and stone you can uh hoping that
you'll get a break that'll identify your
suspect despite an intense investigation
they get nowhere reaching a frustrating
dead end your fear is that he continues
to rob banks and eventually an innocent
person gets hurt and you you don't want
that to happen that's your worst fear
the general description of the bend as
salent does fit Craig Pritchard whom van
meter's been chasing for 2 years that is
the only case file that I never took off
my desk it was always on the corner of
my desk I would always look at it I'd
work other cases but when I had a free
moment i' would always come back what
didn't I do right what could I do more
Van Meter can do nothing else to capture
Craig Pritchard and Nova Guthrie he'll
have to wait and hope for a
break but he never expects the break he
needs will walk through the
door Craig Pritchard and Nova Guthrie
have eluded police for nearly 2
years they are suspected of a string of
four bank robberies totaling over
$250,000 in cash then a strange turn of
[Music]
events on March 2 1999 a chaplain walks
into the FBI's Denver field office with
a surprise visitor
Nova Guthrie the Bonnie to Craig
pritchard's Clyde has had a change of
[Music]
heart her family has convinced her to
talk with their Pastor who persuades her
to surrender she agrees to help police
and the FBI though she claims she
doesn't know where to find Pritchard but
she does reveal in detail how they
pulled off the robberies in Colorado New
Mexico and
Oregon they'd start by renting an
apartment within sight of the target
Bank they'd buy used supplies like
radios a scanner and masks through one
ads in the
paper cash transactions with no
receipts Pritchard would spend weeks
planning each hit detective Kurt kuster
he used that time to
surveil the bank opening CL times
closing times the layout of the bank
where he wanted his getaway driver to
park he knows where the vault is where
the employees are likely to be when
employees come when they are locking up
what times they're going home they'd buy
cheap used cars stealing one might draw
the cops attention they couldn't risk
it during the robberies Nova kept watch
and drove getaway always handle the guns
they'd move fast systematically to stay
ahead of the police after each Heist
they'd look for marked bills die packs
or tracking
devices they'd dump the car and burn all
the
gear and then they'd get another car in
Split heading across state borders or to
the
airport they'd always travel separately
to be safer contacting each other
through payones and free email
accounts cash bought fake IDs and
passports so they bounced around the
globe to Canada Europe Central America
never staying in one place for
long Guth agrees to testify against
Pritcher so the FBI releases her to the
care of her family in Wyoming the move
surprises Arizona prosecutor Michael
Camp my thinking would be that the
authorities believe that since she
volunteered Lally came in to cooperate
and uh assist the authorities that she
would not flee if she was released but
no one understands how tight a hold
Craig Pritchard has on
her over here looks interesting
authorities dashed to the Bend Oregon
townhouse Guthrie and Pritchard used to
Stage the most recent
robbery according to Guthrie they moved
out prior to the heist but police want
to process the place before it's rented
it's not just good enough to have
somebody saying that this person a
particular person did it you know you
have to be able to confirm that
information in the fireplace they
discover burned plastic zip
ties and melted latex the material used
for
masks throughout the place they lift
dozens of fingerprints including the
ones they need we located Lon Prince
which the Oregon State police crime lab
positively identified as belonging to
Craig Pritchard which is huge the prince
confirm guth's confession but bring them
no closer to finding
Pritchard the FBI and police send
information on pritet to police
departments across the country and based
on guth's confession they may have to
expand the search
internationally we need to pull and use
all the resources we can this is a a
team effort Team game that's the way you
have to play to be successful
Richard could be anywhere in the world
by
now he's on this map somewhere and it's
my job to find
him but the investigators are in for a
surprise courtesy of
Nova
TR suddenly one day she didn't show up
for work and they found her truck up on
the highway and she was
gone in the interview with her her
originally she told us that she had been
in contact with Craig over the Internet
so we felt that she would go back to the
internet try and hook up with Craig
again and we feel that that's exactly
what she did The Fugitive couple
reunites and they're back on the
lamb interpole moves fast putting the
pressure of an international Manhunt on
the two but former head of interpo us
John imhof knows that kind of stress can
lead to panic just a matter of time
before he was going to commit murder
somebody was going to stand up to him he
was going to go into a bank where the
security guard would draw his gun and
then Craig Pritchard would have to kill
but first Pritchard will have to run far
he can't stick around the US with dozens
of law enforcement agencies searching
for him that's a that's a lot of people
to have on your
tail when he leaves the country he knows
that he's made the game much more
difficult for the them but interpole
levels the playing field sending
fugitive notices
[Music]
worldwide Nova Scotia Canada seems like
a safe place to hide but photos of Craig
Pritchard and Nova Guthrie circulate the
globe at a hockey game an off-duty
police officer spots the
fugitives he knows it's too dangerous to
approach them alone and goes for help
but Pritchard and Guthrie have been on
the run for years they can sense when to
disappear and they know how to do
it by the time backup arrives the couple
has
vanished we had a number of tips and
leads but we were always just a little
bit behind them sometimes they travel
together then split up for a while
investigators try to track the pairs
online activities but the fugitives are
too smart to leave much of a
trail changing identities changing
locations both within the United States
outside of the United States somebody
you know he knows change identity that
often they're hard to track the tuum
outwit the police at every turn staying
just beyond
reach but investigators are about to
turn up the heat making the world a very
small place for novag and Craig
Pritchard suspected in four bank
robberies Craig Pritchard has been on
the run for over 2 years Detective Tom
vanmeer plays a long shot and turns to a
popular Crimestoppers TV program he
hopes friends and family members might
Inspire
contact when we put the segment on we
put his ex-wife on so he would see her
we actually put his children on throwing
a baseball to try and entice him and we
had a chat line set up hoping that he
might actually call a chat line saying
something to us and then we could trace
that The Fugitive doesn't take the
psychological bait still police hope the
program and subsequent campaign will
produce a new lead on Pritchard and his
accomplice Nova Guth we put out over
50,000 Flyers through the United States
Postal Service and we had their pictures
in the post
office in August
2003 the tactic pays off a South African
National on holiday in the US
spots one of the Flyers recognizes the
fugitive's faces and contacts the
FBI he knows Guthrie as Andy the manager
of a popular nightclub in Cape Town
Pritchard visits the club often and goes
by the name
DNE the witness says the club's website
has photos of employees featuring its
manager pulling up that internet site we
pulled it
up immediately saw the picture of
Craig's
accomplice compared those there was no
doubt that it was
hurt then meter now understands why the
TV program didn't reach Pritchard
interpol's John mhof is not surprised
the couple settled in South Africa when
Craig Pritchard chose South Africa as
his destination for Safe Harbor he was
looking at the fact that South Africa
has a large expatriate population he's
familiar with the language
and whatever false identification he
might derive to help him blend in would
be um less readily recognized as uh
false
documentation Interpol us and the FBI
get to work they contact authorities in
Cape Town South Africa who are eager to
help
out cops are cops and when you've got a
bank robber who's hiding out in your
country that's wanted in another country
politics aside you going to do what's
right to bring that c of
Justice the South African interpole
office must move fast and they must be
discreet South African interpoles nton
Mendes we know that the world is is very
big and today the here in South Africa
tomorrow they they may be somewhere else
and in terms of changing identities or
changing obtaining false passports or
documents it's very easy so we don't
want to cause uh or to act in a such
such way that we may lose
them Cape Town Police accompanied by FBI
agents set up surveillance at the
nightclub hoping to spot the couple they
don't wait long before they find what
they came
for detective inspector dear ke bger
sees a woman who matches Guthrie's
description and spots a distinctive
tattoo of a son on her
back I had the FBI agent with me at the
time and they asked me to contact the
FBI office in the United States to
verify whether this person had a
tattoo she does and it verifies her
identity they have found Nova G three
Cape Town police now hope she will lead
them to
Pritchard and she does right to the Cape
Town apartment she shares with
him now they have to determine how to
capture the too and not get hurt in the
process
y many people like animals when cornered
do become more dangerous uh the more
dire their circumstances become the
level of uh danger associated with that
uh desperation has to
escalate investigators take their time
watching for several days learning the
couple's routine so they can take down
the pair when they're most vulnerable
Nova and Craig follow a pattern designed
to expose any police
surveillance for instance whenever
Guthrie heads home from work she always
calls
Craig she would notify him that she's
coming through and then he would go to
the balcony and have a look whether
she's been followed despite the couple's
anti-surveillance plan Cape Town police
watch them
undetected confident they've learned all
they can the police prepare to sweep in
[Music]
a tactical arrest team plans the takeown
they'll strike when they know the couple
is at home and relaxed watching
TV Pritchard will be desperate and
possibly armed they have to assume he's
ready to kill to keep his
freedom you're on edge you hopped up you
anything can
happen uh it could be a nasty takedown
it could be easy taked down
you make sure that when your arrest goes
down the element of surprise is on your
[Music]
side and it works Pritchard is caught
off
[Music]
guard I came in and briefed them that
they were wanted by the United States
armed
robberies and I called them by their
birth names Craig and
Nova and not by the alas they had been
using
they responded to those names so that
confirmed once again that we had the
right people after two weeks of tracking
Craig Pritchard Cape Town Police finally
arrest him and his accomplice novag Guth
without incident thanks to the
coordination of
Interpol head of extradition at
interpole South Africa is detective
Captain Milton Mendes we trying to make
the world now smaller place for the
fugitives on Iran to see that well you
can try to run but Som day or sometime
you're going to get
caught for 6 years Tom Van Meter has
waited for this day now he has to get
the fugitives back to the
us we made sure that all of the
paperwork was completed ready to go so
that we could get the extradition
process done
quickly quietly to get them out of South
Africa as quick as we could
[Music]
Pritchard remains in custody in South
Africa until US Marshals arve to bring
the fugitive home for Pritchard it was
all about the money but Guthrie had
something more personal at stake on the
20-hour flight back to the US Nova
Guthrie opens up to Deputy US Marshall
Brenda
mcgoffin I was just there for transport
I wasn't trying to get information out
of her but but she just said that she
realized that she had made a mistake and
that she had done something wrong but
that she would do it all over again to
be with
Pritchard Nova Guthrie pleads guilty to
multiple robberies and is sentenced to
10 years in
prison The Mastermind of the operation
Craig Pritchard also pleads guilty and
earns 22 and a half
years he's ordered to pay over $200,000
in restitution to the
banks we did find him we've got him
everybody's
okay it's just a personal thing that
once you get into investigations and you
start investigating violent crimes
against people um it's not how much I
want to catch him it's how much I wanted
the satisfaction I get from telling the
victims I finally C him for you and now
he's going to go away he's not going to
hurt anybody else those days are over
police suspect Craig Pritchard robbed as
many as a dozen Banks across the US
taking hundreds of thousands of dollars
at
gunpoint his violent crime spree spread
Terror Across the Western us but because
of Interpol and police around the world
Craig Pritchard will spend the next two
decades of his life Behind Bars the
story that will span 28 years begins in
the lazy Resort town of paa Thailand in
the mid 1970s
[Music]
one morning a fisherman in a Longboat
finds the body of a woman floating in
the
water he alerts the Royal Tai police who
rush to the scene
[Music]
the coroner examines the young victim
and questions the
fisherman with no identification and no
signs of Foul
Play the woman is most likely a
Westerner who's had a swimming accident
[Music]
the coroner fingerprints and examines
the
victim but still can't identify
[Music]
her a Toxicology test reveals alcohol
and hashish in her
[Music]
system the medical examiner has seen
several cases like this in her
career an unsuspecting tourist falling
prey to the Waters of Patia
what she doesn't yet
realize is that there's a killer on the
[Music]
loose the police canvas area hotels to
see if anyone has reported a foreigner
[Music]
missing but foreign tourists come and go
all the time without notice
no one reports her
missing it's as if she never even
existed and after 2 months another
Discovery grabs the attention of the
Royal Thai
[Music]
police a worker driving his truck near
the very same Beach notices something
unusual in the
brush he finds the body of a second
young Western woman
[Music]
murdered police comb the area but find
few
Clues she's a young woman perhaps a
student on an overseas
vacation but she has no
identification no purse no wallet no
passport police don't connect her to the
earlier
victim in the beginning there was no
alarm raised over this covering the two
deaths reporter Alan Dawson people
didn't really correlate for a while the
appearance of of one body and then
another
but one person paying attention is SLE
suami a lieutenant colonel in the Thai
police department and also the head of
interpole in
Thailand the similarities of the cases
don't catch his eye the differences
do they were both found near the ocean
but the conditions of the bodies were
different the police report stated that
the second woman was murdered
deliberately drowned
this discovery raises doubts about the
first young woman perhaps her death was
no accident either a Sinister pattern of
anonymous female victims could be
developing John mhof former director of
interpol's us
office the tie officials have a problem
on their hands they have dead bodies
they have no identification associated
with them they know they have an
investigation that they have to pursue
criminally but one of of the key steps
to getting that started is the
identification of the
victim the morg releases pictures of the
victims to the Bangkok Post tens of
thousands in Southeast Asia start their
day with this English language
newspaper police hop that one of those
readers could provide a
lead but days later the two women in the
morg remain
unidentified paa known as the Riviera of
Thailand caters to
westerners young men and women come here
looking for a good time in a safe but
exotic
land it's not a place you'd expect a
killing
spree the young people were attracted to
Thailand they thought that it had so
much to offer compared with their
culture and they would soak it all up a
popular travel route for young tourists
unofficially begins in paa it leads
through Thailand India and
Nepal Travelers come for a taste of
Eastern
philosophy and a ready supply of hashish
and
alcohol but the relaxed atmosphere
conveys a false sense of
security and this would make them
especially vulnerable to the Predators
who were on the trail
the day after the body of the second
victim was found in
paa villagers find two more
[Music]
bodies this time a man and a
woman like the others they're clearly
young
westerners and undoubtedly murdered
they'd been set on
fire the bodies were still burning when
they were discovered
this was a horrific
crime Flames had scorched the faces of
both
victims police look for anything some
sort of
identification some kind of
lead all they can
find a tag on the woman's clothing that
reads made in
Holland the Thai police now have four
dead
westerners no leads and no
motive they rely on Forensic Clues to
reconstruct the latest
murders the woman was beaten with a hard
object the man was
whipped strangled until he couldn't
breathe the coroner also finds soot in
both of the victim's air passages
the couple was burned
alive this is a terrible inhuman
act the person who did this has an evil
heart out there among the fun-loving
tourists stalks a Killer without a
conscience a predator with no motive and
no
limits three women and one man all
between 18 and 25 years old are
dead police hope that word flies along
the tourist
Trail and that someone somewhere might
have crossed paths with any of the
victims long enough to provide a
lead but the killer travels faster than
the
news striking almost 1,400 miles away at
the end of the trail in Katmandu Nepal
both Nepal and Thailand recently joined
Interpol but the rudimentary
communication between the countries
fails to alert nepales officials that a
killer is on the
loose then police discover two bodies
outside
catmandu a pair of nepales boys stumble
upon the grizzly scene
an unforgettable sight for both the
children and the
investigators the woman had a wound on
her chest the man had a wound on his
neck they were so damaged it was
difficult to see much
more Catman do detective Bish
investigates both
[Music]
M when we saw the dead bodies faces were
burned they were naked we had no idea
who could have done
this securing the crime scene the police
turned the boy's
back but too late to protect them from
the gruesome scene that lay before
[Music]
them the nepes police I that the
anonymous couple travel
together adventurous westerners soaking
up the culture of
[Music]
Nepal and in Katmandu that almost
certainly means a visit to the tourist
Mecca of Jan
chenol also known as freak
Street investigators begin their search
there in the hotels and hostels that
cater to Travelers
at one Lodge a clerk remembers that a
pair of the guests had not returned for
several
days their names Pierre balmont and
Vanessa
Wilson when police search the room they
find most of the traveler belongings but
not their passports
we also found a diary
for we found the name
alier from Bangkok written inside it
what's
going guests in the room next door come
by when they hear the police activity
can you identify these two people first
place concerned about the missing couple
they tell police everything they can
[Music]
one remembers seeing Vanessa Wilson with
a man who claimed to be a gem dealer
from
Bangkok the police ask the Traveler's
friends to come to the
morg they identify the bodies of Pierre
bont and Vanessa
Wilson the body count now grows to
six but the two police departments still
aren't in communication
[Music]
what will it take for Interpol to stop
this serial
killer in the Far East police find six
young westerners murdered under similar
circumstances 1,400 M
apart as separate investigations
continue in Thailand and Nepal police
don't realize they're chasing the same
man Charles Sage
Interpol is trailing Sage for crimes in
India John mhof former director of
interpol's us
office Charles can present a Persona
that is what the people want to see not
what he really is so if he wants to
assume a false identity he's practiced
it this for a long
time the woman killed in Nepal met with
a gem dealer named Alan gotier an alas
us by Charles
S throughout Catman do officers search
for more
leads at one hotel a clerk remembers a
guest matching the description but not
registered under the name alen
goer
Alan he claims to be a Dutch national by
the name of Carl
gasel the clerk recalls that gassel
drove a white car
it isn't much to go on but police must
run with
it they search throughout
catmandu setting up
checkpoints stopping dozens of
cars and interviewing the
[Music]
occupants an officer pulls over a car
that matches the
description the driver calmly produces
passports identifying himself as Carl
gasel and his wife Ida
BOS police call off the search and
escort the couple to headquarters for
questioning the man claims to be a
scholar his wife a Dutch television
starog he insists he has never seen the
murder victim before
I ask what this is all about when the
witness comes in to identify the man she
met with Vanessa
Wilson she draws a
blank she can't positively identify him
as the same man she saw with her
friend Katmandu detective
bisha in napales culture any Foreigner
or guest is treated very
politely we look at him
suspiciously false identification can be
very difficult for the
investigator documents can be reproduced
and they can be made to look authentic
the police let the couple go the man
they know is Carl gasel and his wife
returned to their
hotel the investigators all the time are
coming this close to capturing someone
that needs to be brought to Justice only
to see them slip away because of their
identification changed or because they
were just a minute too late um so that's
that's a huge
[Music]
frustration Days Later a catm do
policeman takes a statement from a
witness who saw a white car near where
the bodies were
found amazingly she remembers the
license plate number
matches the plate on Carl gle's
car and then hard
evidence police find two arrival cards
for the victim Pierre
bont the signatures don't
match a handwriting expert determines
that the second card shares
characteristics with Carl gessle's
signature and it was dated December
24th the same day Pierre bman Mon's
corpse rolled into the coroner's
office the police conclude that the man
they know as Gastel had left the country
and re-entered Nepal using the Dead
Man's
passport the cool calm Professor was a
cold calculating
liar police now have a case against the
man they think is
gastle they hurry to make the arrest
[Music]
but it's too late gasel and idash are
gone there were clothes all over the
place documents were all over the place
including
passports gasoline and
gasoline we also saw things to alter the
passport after we found bad evidence we
were certain that the killer had Slipped
Away police have no idea where to find
him and it will be months before the
information they've gathered reaches
Interpol reporter Alan
Dawson you could wait two days to get a
call through to Nepal and and
Communications were not like they are
today at
all by the time authorities could really
make their case uh it was quite some
time down the road and he was long
gone in Thailand authorities still have
no suspects and no identities for the
four dead Western
tourists Interpol Chief s Paul suami
searches for
leads it's very unusual that a large
number of foreigners were murdered
nothing like this had happened
before usually foreigners come to
Thailand to relax and have
fun they come here to do wrong or break
our
laws so we were investigating the
possibility that the killer was from
Thailand while Thai police attempt to
identify the
victims the Dutch Embassy in Bangkok
receives a vital
clue Herman nienberg is the most Junior
Diplomat at the Dutch
Embassy he receives a letter in the
Diplomatic pouch about a Dutch couple
traveling in
Thailand the family was very worried
about the fact that for a period of over
6 weeks they had not had a sign of life
from a couple who were Ardent
correspondents 28-year-old nienberg
can't imagine how important the couple's
names
are Carl gessle and Ida BOS
the relative has only one
[Music]
lead in The Missing couple's last letter
they wrote that they had made a
sophisticated new friend in
Bangkok the man was a French gem dealer
who was helping Ida and Carl by precious
stones Frenchman had been very
hospitable had uh taken them to dinner
and had invited them to his
apartment they were not completely sure
if this Frenchman was genuine in his
intentions they thought that there might
be an ulterior motive from the
Frenchmen but since that letter nothing
the family asked the Dutch Embassy to
help find
them they felt worried and I felt that
they might have reason to be
worried Herman nienberg contacted Thai
authorities and gives them the names Ida
BOS and Carl
gessle but the Thai police have no
information about the missing
couple nienberg has to find someone who
knows this mysterious gem
dealer he gets a lead from a friend at
another
Embassy I learned from the Australian
Consul that an Australian couple
youngsters traveling had been drugged
and robbed by a French gems
dealer nienberg locates them and
discovers the name of the gem dealer
alen gotier but little
else in a city of 4 and A2 million
people locating gotier would prove next
to
Impossible but nienberg catches a break
when he learns of a woman who knows the
suspect working after hours he arranges
an interview with the
woman she lives in the same apartment
complex as aan
goer her name is Nadine
jir she tells an extraordinary story
about a devious and ruthless
killer several months earlier nen met a
French Canadian woman named
marlair who moved into the building with
her husband alen
goer Marie told naen that goer was
extremely possessive and would probably
kill her if she ever tried to
leave when naen expressed concern Marie
told her that she was
joking nen soon learned
otherwise my
informance told me that goer was an
extremely dangerous
person he was also charming and lured
young foreigners into his
apartment nienberg learns about one
guest who got sick left with gotier and
never
returned people had a way of
disappearing from the Halen Co apartment
they suddenly went on trips from which
they never returned leaving their
jewelry and bags and passports
behind naen soon learned he had two
willing
accomplice AJ chowdery had earned a
chilling
reputation Char was considered a killer
who to great pride in showing people his
knife marlair cultivated more subtle
skills she had a great knowledge of
pharmaceutical things she could inject
people she was considered the poisoner
of the
three and then nienberg got the best
news
yet naen had actually met the missing
Dutch couple Carl gessle and Ida
BOS and significantly while they were
buying gems from Alan the couple fell
suddenly ill
not long after that gotier and AJ
chowdery whisked the sick Dutch couple
away then one of Go's guests showed
naine a picture from the Bangkok
Post respons they could see on the
photograph in the newspaper that these
people who had been murder in such a
cruel manner that they were wearing the
clothes of the
couple naen now believed the horrifying
photo of the burned couple found outside
paa showed Carl gessle and Ida
BOS she had to find out more about her
dangerous
neighbors with gotier and his two
accomplices on a trip to Nepal Nadine
entered their
apartment in a safe
journals passports
jewelry in a suitcase nearby syringes
drugs everything that the Charming host
Alan goer would need to kill his guests
and assume their
identity now afraid for her life naen
contacted a friend at the embassy who
contacted
nienberg she took something from Go's
apartment for proof
Ida bash's
diary she gives it to nienberg along
with press clippings about other murders
and missing persons
cases nienberg reads the
Articles and as he looks over the
headline about the murder outside of
Bangkok he has a
recollection the thing which had stuck
in my mind was that the female had worn
a t-shirt with a label in it made in
Holland although not a police officer
nienberg finds himself in a position
familiar to many
investigators circumstantial evidence
points him toward a
solution but he needs concrete
proof he gets that from the dental
records of Carl gasel and Ida
BOS I just entered the mark and suddenly
from one of the corners of the room came
this
voice which
said Mr
knippenberg I found it it's them and at
that moment I knew that our worst fears
were becoming reality and that it was
the young Dutch couple which had been
murdered well tha Police search for the
killer Charles Sage he assumes the
identity of Carl
gastle and the Alias alen goer to escape
murder charges in
Nepal but police in two countries have
not made the
[Music]
connection interpole will have to put
the pieces
together and pick up the Killer's Trail
in
Bangkok Dutch Diplomat Herman nienberg
suspects gem dealer Alan gotier of
murdering a young Dutch
couple but he hasn't realized that the
gem dealer is serial killer Charles
so I had already very very strong
suspicions that more young people of
roughly the same age and of a similar
background had come to an end in a
similar
manner nienberg compiles all the
evidence he has secured into an
exhaustive study of the Killer's crimes
in
Thailand connecting the deaths of the
two unidentified women with the Dutch
couple his research uncovers the
unsolved murders in
Katmandu I also saw press reports coming
out of Nepal which described exactly the
same operation
method vicious killings followed by
burnings with gasoline in
Nepal nienberg submits his report to the
police who take it very
seriously the Thai police and an
undercover Squad raid elen Go's
[Music]
apartment inside
two men and a
woman let me get it hold on the woman's
name Mar
CLA she has a valid
passport with her AJ
chowdery papers in
order I go Steve Watson I don't know
where he's at so BR produces an American
passport now he is calling himself Steve
Watson
the police bring them to the station for
[Music]
questioning they also confiscate the
apartment
[Music]
safe but amazingly sobr convinces police
that he really is an American named
Steve
Watson and author authorities cannot
refute his phony passport on the spot
John mhof former director of interpol's
us office explains
why every document can be replicated and
if he is sufficiently skilled or he
knows the right people who are
sufficiently skilled to help him prepare
an authentic looking US Passport there's
no reason why the Thai officials would
question
that the safe Nair found full of stolen
passports is now
empty except for some
receipts no evidence no case and for the
police no choice they hold the Trio's
passports but have to let the suspects
Go
free when the police stated to me there
had been no proof of their criminal
activities was of course quite
flabbergasted I could not stand idly by
and have a group of completely innocent
young people be
slaughtered without anybody lifting a
finger but nienberg had also delivered
his file to interpol's National Central
Bureau in Bangkok chief of Interpol s
suami now knows more about this elusive
Killer's true nature
I understood from the beginning he had
to commit more crimes he has a true
criminal
nature he doesn't care anything about
other people he only looks after
himself no one in Thailand knows the
Killer's real name but interpole follows
close on his
Trail his luck is about to run
out in Canada
agents track down the parents of
marlair we they learned that she had
given her family a phone number in Paris
of a Woman by the name of Madame
s at interpo headquarters in
[Music]
France agents run the name sobr through
their International database of known
felons finally they trace the Alias
alang goer to The Wanted killer Charles
so they put him on their most wanted
list and post a red notice to member
countries around the world you have an
ability to very effectively disseminate
to 181 countries instantaneously
information about a particular crime
pattern and when people are moving
across borders it's important that you
be able to disseminate that kind of
information readily
so bra is already wanted in
India where he has earned his nickname
The Serpent for his uncanny ability to
slip out of the grasp of the
[Music]
law and now the serpent slithers away
again following the murders of six young
westerners in Thailand and Nepal
Charles Sage the killer known as the
serpent is on the Run throughout
Asia interpole has issued a red notice
on The
Fugitive placing him on the
organization's most wanted
list and although already wanted in
India sobr enters the
country and in no time has apparently
struck
again in New Delhi a young Westerner is
found murdered in a tourist Hotel his
passport and money
gone the coroner determines death by
poisoning 3 Days
Later police respond to a mass poisoning
of over 50 tourists at a new Deli
[Music]
Hotel a group of French students claimed
their tour guide poisoned them
[Music]
police recognize S as the phony guide
and immediately take him into
custody reporter Alan Dawson is not
surprised by sra's bold act I think
Charles really thought that he could do
anything he wanted to do and he wanted
to show his power over these people by
poisoning them and Charles went down
that
day authorities are rest sage and
marlair charging them with poisoning the
students their usual accomplice AJ
cheler was not with them and has never
been seen
again an Indian Court finds the couple
guilty lir gets 8 years so BR
12 but it takes more than iron bars to
hold the serpent and authorities
underestimate his devious
nature so and lir are incarcerated in
tar
prison but the charismatic Sage manages
to gain special
privileges he exploits the media to toy
with authorities back in
Thailand reporter alen Dawson visits him
several
times I asked him about the
murders he says he is familiar with the
victims he knows what happened to that
person and he makes it very obvious that
he was in directly involved in what
happened to that
person and on one visit a disturbing
Revelation he proceeded to draw me a map
of a place in Patia with x marks the
spot where a body was buried and when I
came back to Thailand and I gave that
map to the police and they went to that
spot and dug where it said X and they
dug up a body
High authorities really did want Charles
to come back here face a court be found
guilty and be
shot extradition proceedings have
already
begun as Thai authorities triy to bring
s
back they have until 1995 to try the
serpent for multiple counts of murder
before the statute of limitations Runs
Out chief of Interpol in Thailand s
suai India I went to India to strengthen
our extradition
request the Indian police took me to see
Charles S in prison he knew why I was
there he knew that if I was successful
and he was sent back to Thailand he
would die he would be executed we had
plenty of evidence Charles told me that
he feared one thing legally and that was
to be sent to
Thailand the Indian government refuses
to extradite sobr until his sentence is
complete years pass and the serpent
plots his next
move on his 10th anniversary in prison a
former inmate returns to visit his good
friend he brings candy
Charles generously offers it to
everyone within the hour prisoners and
guards pass
out so brj slips out of
jail a deadly fugitive on the
[Music]
loose and no one knows where the serpent
will strike
[Music]
next a man of the world escaped killer
Charles Sage The
Serpent could be anywhere hiding nearby
or slipping out of the
country without a moment to lose
interpole reopens its file and notifies
its members that the serpent is
loose New Delhi police assign a
surveillance team to stake out the
Serpent's old Hangouts
3 weeks later New Delhi detective M
hooker zendi spots a man who looks
familiar then I focused on him I
realized that he looked like
Sage my heart started
pounding it seems too
easy how can a man famous for eluding
the law be so
[Music]
careless now it is time to arrest the
serpent yet
again the agents make their
move the serpent received an additional
10 years for the
Escape but it's exactly what he
wants Charles said later the reason he
staged his Escape was
specifically because the time was
running out on his real sentence in
India that he faced possibly being freed
from Indian Jail uh he Thailand had
filed EXT his extradition but that if he
escaped from jail in India that he would
not be extradited to Thailand and that's
exactly what
happens India will not extradite a
criminal still serving a
sentence while so brage does the
additional jail time in India the
statute of limitations runs out on his
crimes in
Thailand when his sentence is up he'll
be a free
man even free to kill again
[Music]
in 1997 Charles so is
released chief of interpole in Thailand
s Paul
suami I was very angry I wanted him to
be tried and punished for his crimes in
Thailand he killed a lot of people
here his old accomplish is gone Mar
Clair died of cancer in
1984 but Charles sbrj is never tried for
the murders of the two people who were
found burned to death outside of
Katmandu Nepal has no statute of
limitations on murder a warrant for s's
arrest remains in effect 28 years after
the
crime in that time Ganesh KC the young
boy who discovered the burned bodies has
joined the catmandu police
department he has never forgotten the
site it was the first time I saw a dead
body it was a foreigner naked
burned I was really very
afraid
terrified then in an odd twist of
fate 6 years later in October
2003 the serpent returns to
Nepal a journalist snaps a few photos
and sells them to the local
newspaper we couldn't believe that s
would come here so we called the
paper they said we're certain it's him
2 days later as s enters a casino in
catmandu Ganesh and his men arrest
him I was delighted because I thought
that this might give another opportunity
to find Justice for the two Dutch
victims nepalis investigator bisha Lista
hopes his patience will be
rewarded yeah man we people of
law we believe that Justice may be
delayed it should never be denied jce
Justice shouldn't
die so bra denies he had anything to do
with the
murders and Justice might still prove
elusive Ganesh KC and the police in
Nepal have a difficult task
reconstructing a case almost 30 years
old they turn to
Interpol it was important for me to get
as much evidence as
[Music]
possible the International Community and
Interpol offices in different countries
helped us to solve this
case the organization provides an extend
dossier on the
serpent the fruits of their
investigation John
mhof when you have a pending
investigation you're not going to
destroy any records associated with that
as long as these cases are outstanding
whatever information comes to Interpol
will be collected and stored the dosier
gives Ganesh the evidence he needs to
secure a murder conviction against
Charles
[Music]
Sage sage has to pay for his crimes he
has to be punished The Souls of his
victims will now rest in
peace after a 28-year Chase on August
12th 2004 a nepales court sentences
Charles so to life in
[Music]
prison December 1990 a crime of
international proportions begins with
one Suburban family
in Branford Canada 65 Mi Southwest of
Toronto Barbara Walker allows her
15-year-old daughter to spend the
holiday skiing with her ex-husband in
Switzerland where both father and
daughter vanish Without a
[Music]
Trace our last conversation was about a
health problem that I was having and uh
and I was worried that I was it was
going to be diagnosed as cancer that was
our last conversation before she
[Music]
disappeared the holidays pass and her
ex-husband and daughter do not
[Music]
return here this is a picture of them
this is the last picture I've took after
countless attempts to reach them Barbara
goes to the Branford Police to report
them missing just let me know
okay it felt very hopeless because in
another country far away how would I
ever even begin to
find and the distressing News keeps
[Music]
coming over
$700,000 has vanished from the accounts
of Walker Financial Services the company
owned by Barbara's ex-husband
Albert for more than 10 years Walker
Financial has invested millions of
dollars in savings and retirement
accounts for its
[Music]
clients the offices were besieged with
phone calls and then people who came
down uh I'm given to understand reporter
Bill Schiller from the Toronto Star
newspaper there was a sense of panic
because people had invested their life
savings and some of them quite frankly
were rather
elderly and um this represented
everything that they had been able to
save in life
Canadian investigators determined that
Albert Walker made credit card purchases
in Switzerland and never used his return
tickets from
Zurich they notify
Interpol John mhof former director of
interpol's us
office all an officer has to do is call
and establish for the interpole bureau
in Ottawa uh that is a law enforcement
officer and that he needs assistance in
the matter and interpo can act on
it interpole issues an international
missing person's report called a yellow
notice for Albert and Amanda
Walker they'll stay on the case until
father and daughter are
found many notices are decades old
that's not
uncommon but interpole will be there to
render its assistance that is keep that
notice pending
as long as the investigator needs
interpo to pursue her
[Music]
matter only interpole can connect what
happens 3500 M away off the southern
coast of Devon
England a tler fisherman hauls up his
catch from the bottom of the ocean
he is shocked to find entangled in his
Nets a human
[Music]
body Her Majesty's Coast Guard receives
the distress
[Music]
call they escort the boat back to brckom
Harbor
detective Constable Ian clenahan heads
to the
scene he expects the victim to be a
young man who had disappeared off the
coast a week earlier in a boating
accident his body at that stage hadn't
been recovered and it was certainly a
consideration that the body that had
been trolled up by the the fishing boat
um could have been um at that stage the
the body of this young l
but the facts don't quite add
up I went onto the boat and found a male
body it was fully
clothed the victim seems older and his
body looks to have been in the ocean for
some
time I found that uh there was no
identification on
him Pockets were pulled out of the
trousers
detective clenahan wonders if this could
be a robbery victim but the dead man
still wears what appears to be a Rolex
watch we didn't know whether it was a
genuine Rolex or whether it was of
course a a
fake either way the watch could provide
a
clue I examined the wristwatch um on the
boat and noted that the time had stopped
at
11:35 and the date window window on the
watch was showing the number
22 Clan also notices a blurred
star-shaped tattoo on the victim's
hand there's definitely when the medical
examiner arrives detective clenahan
points out a deep gash on the back of
the victim's
head good morning doctor de police bring
the body to the Pathology
Lab the watch on the roof the first
order of business raising
fingerprints not so easy on a body that
spent a long time in the
water the skin of the hands become
wrinkled and it's extremely difficult to
get fingerprints off a hand like that
but forensic pathologist Dr guyan
Fernando manages to lift a usable
print The Frigid Waters of the English
Channel help preserve the fragile
body he discovers three injuries a
bruise on the hip and a second bruise on
the middle of the thigh that he
concludes occurred after
death the timing of the third injury a
deep gash to the back of the head
presents more of a
mystery it could have been inflicted
before or after death
but the lungs clearly indicate that this
man died from
drowning at that stage I had only the
few injuries to go on and they didn't
make any sense it's common to find
injuries in people who had drown and at
that time I couldn't really say that
this was a
homicide the forensic text plac the
victim's few personal effects in a
bag the doctor grapples with another
mystery the victim's time of
death after several days at Sea it's
impossible to
estimate all I could say that he's been
in the water for a week or
two not much to go
on three injuries of unknown cause no
identification and no way of knowing how
the man drowned
the pathologist freezes the body in case
it requires further
[Music]
examination Devon authorities run the
fingerprints through their database of
known
criminals they find no
[Applause]
match days go
by another body surfaces in the waters
near brixen
[Music]
Harbor the Coast Guard determines that
this was the young man from the boating
accident it has no connection with the
previous John
do the first body lying in the morg
remains a mystery that Demands a
solution what we have to do is try our
utmost to identify who the Dead person
was um to find out how exactly that
person um came to
die clenahan learns that the victim's
Rolex watch might hold the
answer Rolex keeps records for each of
its time
pieces if the owner ever had it serviced
the company would have his name on
file investigators send the watch to
Rolex headquarters in Kent
[Music]
England but going through the victim's
clothing detective clenahan discovers
another important
[Music]
clue and in amongst those clothing we
found that a lot of the labels um
originated from uh Canadian
manufacturers by now more than 5 years
have passed since Barbara Walker's
ex-husband and her daughter left Canada
bound for their Switzerland ski holiday
and
disappeared it was hard to handle if you
thought about it too much you could lose
you could lose your
mind Barbara's hope never
waivers she tries not to imagine the
worst believing that her daughter and
ex-husband will somehow be
found I can't imagine what it would be
like to be in her shoes in the
situation tragic a mother you know
uh I imagine that it would be very
difficult two cases on two
continents A desperate family
tragedy and a body pulled from the
sea seemingly
unrelated but investigating will soon
find them linked to a large and cunning
criminal
[Music]
plot two random tragedies or so it
seems in Canada a father takes his
daughter on holiday to
Europe and they never
return in England a fisherman pulls a
dead man from the
sea eventually authorities will connect
them and reveal the Mastermind behind it
all but for now investigators work them
as separate cases counting on timing
luck and thorough detective
[Music]
work in Devon England detective Ian
clenahan tries to solve the case of the
dead man pulled from the
sea the victims watch has a serial
number that could identify its
owner so we sent the Rolex off to the
Rolex company head office in England
where it was
examined and we were eventually informed
that that particular Rolex watch had
been serviced three times um all in the
haraga area of England in Yorkshire and
the name of the person that put the
watch in for service on all three
occasions was Mr Neil Barrett
Neil
Barrett investigator's first lead on the
identity of the man in the
[Music]
morg his last known address was in
Chelmsford Northwest of London and a
5-hour drive from
Devon detective clenahan asks a
colleague there to help
out so my role was to go to chelon and
establish if anyone there knew
uh the
chat detective Sergeant Peter Redmond
finds Barrett's rental house empty and
calls upon Barrett's
landlord sir detective Peter Redmond
just wanted to and he told me that uh
Neil had given up the house and moved to
France to set himself up in business
the landlord gives the detective a copy
of Neil Barrett's
lease on it Barrett listed a man named
Steve Russell as a
reference detective Redmond calls Steve
Russell authorities only linked to the
deceased their only
hope the purpose of my meeting with with
Steve Russell was to see if there was
anything else
about Neil that he could tell us that
would assist the identification I
mention to you on the because as I
understood it the body wasn't in a fit
state to be viewed by a
friend
my we sat and talked for a while nice
chap well spoken well dressed casually
but very well-dressed expensive clothes
um he'd got an air of confidence about
him there was an accent but I couldn't
detect it was North American whether it
was American or Canadian I couldn't I
couldn't
tell I wanted to know when he'd last
seen him and if he knew at that time
what his plans were because we couldn't
explain how he would be traveling to
France and winding up in the sea of
Deon Steve Russell can't explain his
friend's deadly twist of fate he was
originally going to Paris but I but he
offers some useful information
he recalls that Neil had served in the
Army labor would provide Neil's medical
and dental records which were forwarded
to Devon and coral and they were able to
match the dental
records Barrett has been positively
identified police find no further
evidence of Foul
Play detective Redmond believes the case
is wrapping
up they they identified the body there
was no sign of any third party
involvement in his death was being
treated as a as an accident of
drowning but what investigators don't
realize is that this case is just
getting
started detective clenahan notifies
Barrett's brother of Neil's
death it's Neil Barrett brother tells
clenahan that the tattoo is a Canadian
maple
leaf he asks clenahan to put him in
touch with Steve Russell hoping that
Russell can help him find his brother's
belongings clenahan calls on detective
Peter Redmond again to ask him to visit
Russell in the small farming village
where he
lives in rural England houses often have
no street
addresses instead they're given
names at first detective Redmond can't
locate
it I found the two houses neither of
which has got names on them um so I took
pot luck and I called it as it turned
out the
neighbors I said I was who I was and
then I was looking for Steve Russell and
he said oh no Neil Barrett lives there
and I'm thinking straight away
something's not right here that's the
name of the man who's dead Endeavor
about how long have they lived next door
to
[Music]
you redond learns what the neighbors
know about this other Neil
Barrett he discovers an uncanny
similarity between Neil Barrett and
Steve
Russell and when they described the
person they knew as Neil his manner the
ACC and it became apparent to me that we
were talking about the same person but
with two different names Redmond
realizes that Steve Russell is
pretending to be Neil
Barrett what they' said transformed what
had been a simple investigation to
identify a found body to potentially a
murder
investigation the man I was seeking was
living as this man's identity there had
to be something sinister in my mind and
had Neil met his end as a consequence of
this on his way back to the station
Redmond calls detective Ian clenahan in
Devon with the news detective clanahan
informed me of his findings at wooden
Walter which really threw a totally
different light on the matter but
investigators haven't begun to Fathom
the depths of Deceit involved in this
case or to suspect the international
criminal at the bottom of
it in Canada people have begun to
realize the Albert Walker case is much
more complicated than it originally
seemed right after Walker disappeared
with his daughter money disappeared from
his
company and now it appears that Walker
had plundered his own
Corporation I I found Bank information
indicating that large amounts of money
were being transferred through his
personal bank
account I knew it wasn't his own money
because we didn't didn't have that kind
of money so it had to be either money
that he was taking from the company or
taking it from
clients hello he had left his wife to
deal with the U CL sents who are
obviously extremely
upset it was a shock to people that
someone like this who seemed to be
righteous and good and charming and
generous uh could actually disappear and
leave people high and dry without their
life
savings Canadian police charge Walker
with 19 counts of theft fraud and moneya
laundering
they request that Interpol issue a red
notice for Albert Walker he will rise to
number four on interpol's most wanted
list the red notice is is like an
electronic version of The Wanted notice
that we used to see in the post office
interpole will send that out to 181
countries so that if this person if this
subject comes to their attention uh they
can take steps to see that he's
apprehended and returned to face Justice
in
Canada but Walker will be very hard to
locate when he left Canada he shed his
[Music]
identity I think he was difficult to
track because you're dealing with a very
cunning Criminal
Mind Mr Walker was not a deeply
intelligent man he was not an
intellectual but when it came to Crime
he was dangerously clever maybe too
clever for his own good because now
Albert Walker has the full force of
interpole gunning for him that leaves
him with no place to
hide off the coast of Devon England
an anonymous dead body is pulled from
the
sea eventually dental records identify
him as Neil
Barrett but this case is not so
simple someone has taken Barrett's life
and stolen his
identity detective Peter Redman has even
met the impostor not a
problem he introduced himself as Steve
Russell concerned that maybe a
friend police soon learn that Steve
Russell lives with his young wife and
two small
children in Canada the name Steve
Russell means nothing
yet Barbara Walker is more concerned
about the capture of her ex husband
Albert Walker number four on interpol's
most wanted list
but during the Canadian police
investigation into Albert Walker they
meet the real Steve Russell one of
Walker's former
clients you know what that
is oh yeah couple years ago he told the
police
that he had gone to Mr Walker for a loan
talking about that would be Mr Walker
said that he would be able to facilitate
that and in doing so he said he would
need his birth
certificate with that one slip of paper
an experienced criminal can steal an
identity no I don't I mean our deal were
he needed another identity apprciate and
Mr Walker did just
that he from like you to contact me okay
there were two key things that uh he did
extremely well he kept moving and he
kept moving under different
personalities and he got the necessary
documentation the official papers that
he needed to in order to be
convincing using Steve Russell's
identity Albert Walker starts a new life
in
England 3 years later fearful that
Canadian investigators will catch up
with him he takes on yet another
identity Neil
Barrett we started over the next few
weeks to investigate the house and we
checked on all the utilities the gas the
electric the
water and we found that all of these
items were registered in the name of
Neil
Barrett both of them police find the
children's birth certificates are also
registered under the name Barrett the
only piece we can find but the real Neil
Barrett is is lying in the morg in
Deon he has no wife and lived alone if
these
[Music]
aren but he did have an ex-girlfriend
named Melinda who became an unwitting
Pawn in a murderous master
plan detective clenahan tracks her down
hello hi
when did you first meet Steve Russell
Melinda worked for the man police know
as Steve
Russell she bought Antiques and property
traveling around the continent for him
anes but that isn't all she
did she was also asked by Mr Russell to
take vast quantities of money over into
Europe and deposit them in various Banks
um in Switzerland and other similar
countries she never questioned where the
money came from Russell wins her trust
completely I introduced Melinda
introduces her boyfriend Neil Barrett to
her boss from can you
[Music]
drink she informed Mr Russell at the
time that her boyfriend Mr Neil Barrett
had one great ambition in life which was
to immigrate to Canada
Russell makes Melinda and Neil business
partners setting the
trap to complete the paperwork he asks
for their identification papers
including birth
certificates it was wonderful to work
with them together they have no reason
to be suspicious of Russell after all
he's exceedingly
generous one Christmas they were around
at Mr Russell's home address when Mr
Russell gave Mr Barrett and Melinda two
oneway tickets to
Canada what they don't know is that
Russell needs Barrett out of the country
for a reason he wants the man's
identity the Trap is sprung Steve
Russell becomes Neil
Barrett but things don't quite work out
as planned left together really thinking
that it was Neil and Melinda break up
Melinda moves back home
itn't and soon enough a letter arrives
in Steve Russell's
mailbox Neil Barrett has decided to come
home as
well Steve Russell finds himself in an
impossible
situation the problem s came when Neil
Barrett decided to return to England and
then there were two Neil barretts living
in close
proximity how are you I'm good clenahan
suspects that gave the impostor a motive
to kill
Barrett we decided at that time that we
would arrest both Mr Russell and his
wife Dian Russell on suspicion of the
murder of Neil
[Music]
Barrett according to the neighbors
Russell and his family are out of
town but detective Peter Redmond decides
to drive by to see for
himself he is surprised to see a car in
the
driveway but the detective is alone
without
backup and I found said the car's back
I'm not going to leave in case they take
flight it was then suggested well we
don't really know who this person is
he's wanted for
murder I someone suggested there might
be Firearms
[Music]
involved in Great Britain Police almost
never carry a
pistol and armed raids require special
[Applause]
[Music]
Arrangement Redmond is told to tight
until headquarters can mount an
operation while the detective waits for
the Firearms team to arrive a taxi
approaches the
house and the man he knows as Steve
Russell gets
in with or without backup Redmond cannot
let the suspect slip from his grasp so I
decided to follow
it and to get it stopped
Redmond is alone and
unarmed he can only pursue his Mark and
hope that backup will arrive before it's
too
[Applause]
late I got on a telephone and explained
to them what was happening that I was
following this taxi and I believe it got
our suspect in it so they frantically
tried to get the armed response vehicle
which in fact was some distance behind
me to catch us up and eventually I would
imagine 2 to 3 miles from the house they
finally caught
up and stopped
him police approached the arrest
cautiously they know Steve Russell is a
desperate man about to be cornered
in England a fishing boat snares a dead
body police discover that a man named
Steve Russell has stolen the Dead Man's
[Music]
identity they arrest him on suspicion of
murder
detective Peter Redmond takes him
in Russell plays it
cool so I walked up to him and he he
recognized me straight away Sergeant
Peter Redmond the Yorkshire police all
about we placing you under arrest with
the murder of Neil
Barrett he was completely
compliant he put his hands behind his
back in Readiness for him to handcuff
him
and then they took him away in their
patrol
car Mr Russell is a very cool calm and
calculated killer he's a very very
ruthless man and would do anything to to
meet his
ends at Russell's house redond and his
associates find the rest of the familys
of the murder of his wife Diane and two
children they take the young mother in
for
questioning she seemed a little taken
back but there was no hysterics or or
panic she all about the
[Music]
children now while Diane was getting
herself ready and the children the
female officer who was with her noticed
the small Ru sack that she was preparing
for the
toddler and said wait a minute what have
you got in
there heavy
it and when she opened the bag she
discovered several bars of gold and
several thousand in cash just what a a
three-year-old needs for a for a night
away the man at the center of the
mystery won't cooperate
just got a couple of questions uh it's
very difficult to give someone an
opinion of a person who answers no
comment to every question that answered
I have no comment on
that no comment but he appeared to me to
be a very calm very calculated person
very sure of himself how long police
question Diane Russell separately
really she answered all our questions
and she informed us that Steven Russell
was a very successful businessman and
that he had fled America in order that
his wife who he had now split up from
couldn't get half of his earnings from
the business and that was why they were
over here too to come over here and we
just love it
[Music]
here the police search Russell's house
hoping to find evidence to turn their
suspicions to proof
[Music]
at this point we still didn't have any
hard fact at all and in fact really we
were struggling to say that Mr Barrett
had actually been
murdered investigators find more cash
and gold
bars they also uncover various documents
including a rental agreement for a self-
storage
facility so we checked a l this and we
found most a search of the storage unit
yields a global positioning satellite
device or GPS used to navigate boats
[Music]
GPS the suspect has a boat registered
under Barrett's
name police locate it at the pier in
Devon they impound and search
[Music]
it on board they find a bag with credit
card receipts
including one from a nautical supply
store the credit card is also in the
name of Neil
Barrett police question the owner of the
nautical supply
store he tells them that the receipt is
for an
anchor he recalls the customer insisted
on buying the anchor even when told it
was too small for his boat
the store owner describes the
purchaser he fits the description of the
suspect known as Steve
Russell detective clenahan knows he must
find the missing
anchor he reinterviews the tler
fisherman who discovered the
body he informed us that in fact an
anchor had been trolled up in the same
Nets as Mr
Barrett the fisherman had forgotten all
about it he was after all focused on the
discovery of the
body clenahan knows the anchor could
provide crucial evidence of
murder pathologist guyan Fernando has
frozen the victim's
remains when the police bring the anchor
to the morg he can re-examine the body
in light of this new
evidence morning Dr Fernando determines
that the bruises on the thigh at the hip
seem consistent with the Anchor's shape
he concludes that the killer used the
anchor to weigh the body
down and immediately the police and
myself thought this must have been
hooked onto the belt yes in here Dr
Fernando believes the anchor pulled away
from the body when it got caught up in
in the toler's net might I see the belt
please so we took the belt out and had a
look and where we thought the an must
have been hooked the belt showed
definite evidence of
twisting they bring the belt and the
anchor to the
lab the anchor is coated with
zinc forensic investigators discover
traces of zinc on the Belt Pro dividing
the evidence they need to classify this
death as a
[Music]
murder they theorize that the killer
knocked Neil Barrett unconscious on the
boat waited him down with the anchor and
threw him
[Music]
overboard the police knowah murder
occurred now they must link it to the
suspected murderer
using Neil Barrett's card Steve Russell
purchased the
anchor but investigators need to place
him at the scene of the
crime the GPS device recovered from his
storage locker could be the Smoking Gun
they're looking
for they send it to the manufacturer to
determine where the GPS system has
traveled
recently very interestingly this put
that GP PS system out at sea at 9:00
p.m. on the 21st of July 6 mil off
tinmouth which was roughly where the
body was trolled up from this is
consistent with the date on the watch
found on the body the
22nd a Rolex will self-wind for up to 44
hours before it
stops time has run out for Steve Russell
on the hook for murder
but he is not the man authorities think
he is and his crimes go far deeper than
they ever
[Music]
imagined British police arrest North
American Steve Russell believing he
murdered Neil Barrett to steal his
identity but through interpol's
fingerprint database they are about to
discover they've solved an international
Case that has stymied investigators for
years whenever a foreign suspect is
arrested authorities send the
fingerprints to the Interpol database to
see if the suspect has committed crimes
abroad in fact interpole does have a
match but the fingerprints do not belong
to a man named Steven Russell
[Music]
he is not the man authorities think he
is and his crimes go far deeper than
they ever
imagined within a few hours a reply came
back that in fact Mr Steven Russell
wasn't Steven Russell but was in fact
Albert Johnson Walker uh a man that
featured very prominently on interpol's
most wanted
list Albert Walker the same man who left
Canada 6 years earlier to escape fraud
charges to your right the same man who
disappeared with his teenage
daughter we had caught the fourth Most
Wanted man in the
world we were all obviously very
thrilled in Branford Canada Barbara
Walker has not seen her daughter in six
years
ever since her husband Albert
disappeared with the young
girl finally she receives the call she
has longed for this is detective Myers
from the Ontario Provincial Police I'm
calling to inform my knees went weak I
thought this is this is unbelievable
they were saying that my daughter was
found that she was
okay and it was it was just after all
those years of hoping and it came out of
the blue
British authorities uncover that the
woman posing as Russell's wife is really
Barbara Walker's kidnapped daughter
number
six an older man with a younger wife is
not
unusual but an older man with a younger
woman who when you look closely has got
physical resemblances to him then you
start to think I wonder what was going
on here this is a particularly difficult
situation because you're talking about a
child parent relationship and
the concept of Free Will as we know it
breaks down somewhat in that
equation certainly you're a victim in
that
instance his daughter came over them at
15 years of
age Mr Walker was a very manipulative
man he manipulated many lives that he
came across daily and ruined people's
lives it didn't matter whether it was a
friend or family he didn't
care though many have speculated about
the identity of the children's father
the paternity has never been
revealed I British Social Service
counselors arrange and monitor the first
meeting between Barbara and her
daughter I was shaking when I went into
the room but it went well it was awkward
of course when you haven't spoken with
someone in six
years sort of had to reintroduce
ourselves
God it was when that spell was broken
the contact with her father was broken
she was then able to come forward and
tell what had really
happened and it became apparent that she
was not a suspect she was a
victim s in time Amanda Walker agrees to
testify against her
father Albert Walker will finally have
to answer for the death of Neil
Barrett it seems like the perfect murder
and for all intents and purposes he
should have got away with it the Rolex
watch found on Barrett's body the clue
that gave police the Dead Man's identity
is where the case came together for
police and unraveled for the con
man had he even taken the watch off and
thrown it perhaps 60 or 70 yards just
simply disengaged it from the body he'd
be a free man
today and were it not for interpole the
identity of the murderer would have
forever remained a
mystery the fingerprints were the key
issue I think had the fingerprints not
identified him as Albert Walker I don't
think think we would ever have found out
who he was in the end thank God Interpol
were the people who put together the
information sent it to the United
Kingdom and the investigators finally
knew who they were dealing
[Music]
with Albert Walker is convicted of
murder and sentenced to life in
prison although finally brought to
Justice Walker's ego will not allow him
to be humbled
he was led away in the prison van when
one of the prison officers mentioned my
name to
him he replied yeah I know the man tall
scouser not too
bright but I was brighter than Mr Walker
on this
occasion Albert Walker is serving a life
sentence in
England he still faces 37 charges of
fraud in Canada
the Lio Paris Night
Train it barrels through the lir valley
of France at 100
[Music]
mph and usually blows past the small
town of chabanet about 180 Mi south of
Paris few tourists visit this tranqu
Village but one night murder comes to
call in October
1999 a man walking by the railroad
tracks makes a shocking
Discovery The partially clothed body of
a young
woman French John Dar from nearby bourge
respond the confront a disturbing
[Music]
sight quite we knew it was a girl but
identifying her was practically
impossible especially because she had no
identity
cards Colonel Bruno hear leads the
investigation the jarm are the military
police who handle law enforcement in
rural areas of France
he and his fellow investigators have
little to go on beside the wrecked
body somewhere hidden near these
railroad tracks like Clues to This
Woman's
identity and possibly the key to her
[Music]
killer Amar soon finds the clue he needs
the woman's
watch the hands have
[Music]
stopped the hands on the watch were
stopped at 4:10 but we couldn't tell
whether it was 4:10 p.m. 410
a.m. but when hear removes the watch it
starts to
work this meant that the fall must have
stopped
it the expensive watch tells
investigators robbery was probably not a
motive not much to go on but all they
have right
[Music]
now the local press jumps on the
story you have to realize that chabanet
is quite small very isolated so this
incident immediately the local
[Music]
press when the local newspaper files
this
story veronique bhan a French press
agency reporter runs with
it it was like
thunder in a region where nothing much
happens you don't see things like this
on the front page of the
newspaper the the story receives
national
attention striking a wave of Terror
among the 50 million French citizens and
tourists who depend on the train for
safe passage each
year the killer has struck just as
France plays host to more visitors than
anywhere else in the
[Music]
world unlike the United
States France embrac the train it's an
image of
childhood there's a romance about the
train that makes it part of the French
[Music]
culture with tourism at a record high
this Anonymous victim could have come
from
anywhere the medical examiner finds no
evidence of sexual
assault he determines that she fell to
her death from the speeding train killed
by the violent
impact a random victim or Marked for
Death hear can't say until he learns
more about
her though her watch has no monogram it
has a distinctive design himar takes a
shot in the dark that pays
off we researched the
watch and we discovered that it was
manufactured and sold only in Great
Britain Amar believes the victim may be
English to find out more will require
help from the world's police
force
interpole John mhof former head of
interpol's national Central Bureau in
Washington DC Interpol is a dedicated
Network that allows Law Enforcement
Officers to communicate worldwide
instantaneously almost 500 mil from
chabanet in a small village in northern
England fear is missing she she didn't
make a mother and father report their
daughter
[Music]
missing 20-year-old Megan Thompson had
gone to France to study
[Music]
law but homesickness Drew her back to
England I
will she left for home the same day the
body was found in
[Music]
chabet she should have arrived at
Birmingham New Street Station as she
should have been met by her
boyfriend detective Diane M investigates
the case
[Music]
when Megan fails to show up her
boyfriend calls her
family and they contact
police it was unclear initially whether
she'd gone missing in France or in
England to help find Megan British
police contact
interpole which issues a yellow
notice the yellow notice is the flag
that this is a missing person here's
somebody that were desperately trying to
find Colonel Amar receives the notice 5
days after the discovery of the body by
the tracks in
chabet we were notified by the policeman
of the regional crime Squad of L that
interpole London had submitted to them a
report about a missing person a girl who
had left L and who had not arrived in
eng he notifies
Interpol the victim matched Megan
Thompson's
[Music]
description Days Later Megan's parents
arrive in
[Music]
France Colonel hear shows them the
jewelry recovered from the
[Music]
body the couple recognized their
daughter's
possessions enabling authorities to
officially identify the victim as Megan
Thompson her body is so disfigured that
police never show it to her
parents Megan was just 5 months shy of
her 21st
birthday the positive identification
rivets The public's
attention when she was identified and we
learned was English the French and
English press reacted
immediately all the new papers picked up
the story and the Press took the case
into their own
hands the pressure from the newspapers
was
so especially from the English
[Music]
press the police retrace Megan's Final
hours at the University in Leo France
Colonel Amar questions the victim's
roommates to find out when she left her
apartment
investigators learned Megan planned to
take the night train from L to
Paris where she would travel on to
England amar's next stop LMO
station the ticket agent remembers
seeing Megan who paid cash for her
ticket Amar learns the train left LMO at
308 and passed by the chabanet station
at 4:10 a.m. without
[Music]
stopping 410 a.m. the time Frozen on
Megan Thompson's watch when her body was
discovered investigators now know the
exact train Megan rad the night she
died we seized the whole train all the
cars and took it back to L Mo station to
search for DNA tra
or any clues in the
car but police face a nagging
inconsistency the French national rail
system the
sncf Tells investigators it is
impossible for anyone to fall or be
thrown from the train all doors and
windows automatically lock when the
train accelerates to cruising speed even
so Amar feels certain that Megan
Thompson had been on this train and that
somehow someone had forced her off at
high speed investigators find their
proof one car with the automatic locking
feature
disabled crime technicians scour the car
but cannot find any significant
Clues it had already been used again the
cars had been cleaned so any evidence
was wiped away
[Music]
but investigators will find their most
valuable Clues outside the train along
the tracks 10 kmet north of where Megan
Thompson's body was
found a hunter discovers a
purse inside a
passport Megan Thompson's passport
[Music]
that police find her luggage further
down the
track the discovery supports haar's
darkest
suspicions it proves that Megan Thompson
had not Fallen had not thrown herself
from the
train we knew it was a murder
her belongings followed her off the
train not only had Megan Thompson been
murdered her killer Roes free along the
railways of
[Music]
Europe a young student in France tries
to get back to her family in
England and instead meets her death
along the train
tracks the killer still out
there somewhere
anywhere jeand launch an intensive
Manhunt for a faceless
suspect the French rail system
cooperates providing the names of
passengers who purchased their tickets
by credit
card but many passengers including Megan
Thompson paid cash
police also know that another group
doesn't pay at
all the so-called train rids who sneak
aboard without
tickets in this investigation we became
familiar with the underworld of night
trains and we realize a very shady crowd
travels on these night
trains there are dropouts H who are
looking to steal
many countries passengers caught without
tickets must either get off the train or
buy a ticket on the
spot in France passengers caught without
tickets are cited and later issued a
fine train inspectors do not force them
off the train if they can show
identification to solve the Megan
Thompson murder French police who who
generally don't ask for assistance from
the
Press make a public appeal for Witnesses
who might have seen the young
student investigators also begin riding
the train at the same time of night
Megan Thompson would have been
aboard
I the interview passengers who regularly
Took the Night Train and might have seen
something
investigators question hundreds of
witnesses after almost two months riding
the rails pays
off one passenger recalls Megan speaking
with a young
[Music]
man reconstructs a timeline of their
trip she arrives at the L station and
she withdraws 2,000 Franks from the
[Music]
cash she goes to the ticket office where
she purchases a ticket to
Paris the ticket remembers this young
lady very well
[Music]
then at around 2:00 in the morning she
talks to another witness who tells
police that he remembers seeing Megan
[Music]
a man wearing a cap stops to talk with
her he tells her that he is from marsill
gent and that he is traveling without a
ticket
[Music]
they get on the 17th car and sit side by
side the train pulls out at 308
[Music]
a.m. sometime later they leave the car
and move to the next
one after Megan Thompson switches cars
no one sees her again
[Music]
based on the description of the man
given by The Witness police create a
computer generated
picture thousands of people come and go
on the train
[Music]
unnoticed one of them is the Killer
ready to strike
again and he could strike
anywhere Dijon France about 160 mi from
Paris on a chilly December night in 1999
the Cal vilia Train rattles through the
city on its regularly scheduled
route on board the train inspector not
is a little boy sleeping alone in a
compartment he looks for the child's
parents sees no
[Music]
one before exiting the car the inspector
makes his routine check of the restroom
patrolling
starways play
[Music]
he finds the body of a woman crumpled on
the floor stab wounds perforate her body
she barely clings to
life in just two months the French rail
system has endured two murderous
[Music]
assaults a murderer stalks the night
trains in
France his first victim a British
student her body found thrown by the
side of the
tracks the second victim a young woman
stabbed and left for dead in a
bathroom police have a description of a
suspect but no
[Music]
names Dijon inspector Pierre Mar pazio
leads the investigation
[Music]
it's unusual because it occurred at
night it took place in a train a place
where people should feel
safe Dijon police cordon off the train
to keep Witnesses and a possible killer
on
board train authorities call the
paramedics but they can't save the
victim
[Music]
We
examined an initial evaluation of the
cause of
[Music]
death the body was next to the restroom
sink what position were the feet in how
was the victim's body
positioned the arms folded where the
arms stretched out all those indications
were noted
[Music]
and this person had a
purse we opened it very carefully and
discovered her
ID syv Bago from northern
[Music]
France and police soon discover a child
alone who was traveling with Sylvia
[Music]
Bago this was very hard because he was
just a child we were not supposed to let
him know that something terrible had
happen that his mother had died so we
needed to get some information from the
child to be able to contact the victim's
husband
I have two boys that were about the same
age at the time of the event so I tried
to talk to
him I was expecting him to ask
me where's my mom I had trouble facing
that
question that child touched me
[Music]
personally believing the killer could
still on board they H to flush him
out although many of the passengers
slept some report seeing a passenger in
a baseball cap acting
suspiciously he was very agitated
nervous moved around he caused problems
strangely despite their thorough search
police can't find a passenger matching
the description of the
suspect but in a nearby compartment they
discover hard evidence he had been
there we found a baseball cap lying a
short blood cap that we took away to
analyze
[Music]
then police find evidence that the
suspect fled the
train we found a blood
stain a handprint on one of the doors in
the
car police learn that the train makes a
routine maintenance check into
the train stopped just 5 minutes before
they discovered the
[Music]
body one person left the train after the
maintenance stop when he wasn't supposed
to we established that he was a store
he knew for sure that this train would
make a maintenance stop at the DJ
station at that
time the train inspector remembers the
man the official had discovered the
stowaway and written him a
citation when someone is traveling
without a ticket the train inspector
asks for an ID to verify the person's
identity in this particular case he
presented a document identifying himself
as
ahed
rala we had finally found a very
promising
suspect Dijon police learn that Sid
Ahmed rosala is a 20-year-old Algerian
immigrant who has done time for raping a
14-year-old boy and committing multiple
counts of violent robbery in his crimes
he often used a knife
he was released in June 1999 4 months
before the first train
[Music]
murder inspector pazio issues a
nationwide police bulletin alerting
French law enforcement agencies to find
and apprehend
risala the bulletin reaches Colonel
Bruno hear still in investigating the
two-month-old Train Murder of British
University student Megan
Thompson bourge investigators seize upon
the similarities between the Dijon and
the chabanet
murders though the violent manner of
death differed the parallels pointed to
the same malicious killer both women
rode the night
trains Sid ahed rosal's mug shot
resembled the computer generated
illustration and one other striking
similarity
[Music]
we suspected a man who several minutes
earlier had been fined because he was
traveling without a ticket so we
immediately made the
connection the poor je called the police
[Music]
in when they found out about the picture
they contacted me to say okay we are
interested because we already have
something against this person from
another
homicide let's talk and try
[Music]
the murders stir the Press into
frenzy French police have to contend
with both the murderer and constant
media
attention the tradition of train travel
in Europe and the Region's dependence on
the railway creates an unprecedented
level of public
interest the hardest thing for us in
this investigation was the
pressure the pressure of the press the
pressure of our superiors
that kind of pressure is
[Music]
unbearable the investigators discover
that since leaving prison risala
practically lived on the
trains always on the
Move inspectors had find him over 40
times for riding without a
ticket do the
this is
unique stalker
case person who lives by Night takes
advantage of the
situation because during the night there
are fewer Witnesses it's easier to hide
to escape to use the darkness to
disguise
oneself I'm sure the same crime could
not have been committed at 4
p.m. it's
impossible a killer stalks the railways
of France relying on Darkness as his
ally striking the Vanishing into the
night police believe they know his name
and they are certain he will kill
[Music]
again French authorities in bourge and
Dijon have joined forces to stop a
killer on the French rail
system the suspect 20-year-old excon Sid
ammed risala
[Music]
an expert stow away he'll be nearly
impossible to track
down but Dijon Police Inspector Pierre
Mar pazio has a
plan to get to rosala he'll identify
everyone who he had visited while in
jail we had his parents address
Mar his girlfriend's addressing again
which turned out to be something
critical a man on the run will seek
places where he has
allies police begin surveillance on both
his family's home in Marseilles and his
girlfriend's apartment in
amen when the Press learn police have a
suspect they demand to know the name of
the man they've dubed the railway
Ripper we
magistrate gave a press conference in
saying he didn't want to identify the
suspect by name because they were
concerned he would
Escape but someone leaked
[Music]
it one journalist defying authorities
calls on rosal's family tipping off
rosala that he's the prime suspect in
the hunt for the railway
[Music]
Ripper man no
no the Magistrate's worst fears are
[Music]
realized when Marcel police arrive
rosala has already
[Music]
fled knowing he's wanted a violent
unstable criminal like rosala can act in
two
ways he could vanish or he could kill
again
for us this caused a lot of
problem the suspect was
agitated p and he
ran rosala retreats to the world he
knows
best the night
trains we never stopped worrying that to
get hurt another victim
as the information about rosala becomes
public hundreds of phone calls pour
in the public was passionate about this
investigation because it involved the
train because involved a
young because a child had lost his
mother that people
upset police investigate real and
imagine rosala sightings in Paris amen
and
Dijon people didn't just see him in the
trains they'd see him at gas stations
they would see him in town things like
that to the public it seems the railway
Ripper is everywhere but to the police
he is nowhere to be
found tracking rosala movements north of
Paris to amen inspector pazio meets with
some of rosal's friends
to have these conversations with young
women we had to win their
trust we had to convince them that he
was a very dangerous
person that there could be more
victims pazio persuades them to reveal
crucial
information he learns that rosala rents
a room in an apartment building in amen
[Music]
they are too late they find an empty
apartment or so it
[Music]
appears they search the entire building
ending up in the
basement when we searched it on the we
would look looking for living
[Music]
person then we discovered something in
the basement under a pile of
coal the body of a
young investigators have found another
victim
but they are no closer to capturing
[Music]
risala in France authorities stage a
nationwide manhunt for 20-year-old Sid
Ahmed
risala suspected of murdering two young
women on France's national rail
system in the basement of a building in
amen where risala hides out police
uncover the body of a third
victim 20-year-old Renee V
missing for 2
months the report was filed over 2 weeks
after rosal's first victim Mak Thompson
was found
dead vas has been
strangled suspecting that rosala may
have fled the country French authorities
contact
Interpol the international crime
fighting organization issues a red
notice for Sid ammed rosala
red notice is a wanted notice a poster
if you will that uh is promulgated
internationally as opposed to just
within the bounds of a single
country now an already Sensational story
reaches fever pitch
was every SP everyone knew the story the
story of the British woman the victim in
and the one
inen all the details were known that
created seing Panic by the night
trains the entire nation of France
wonders when and where the railway
Ripper will strike
next police struggle to keep the lines
of communication open between
departments without feeding the rumor
mill on the
streets success demands Flawless
cooperation local Regional and National
Police team up to catch the railway
River each has its own methodology and
its own set of cases to
solve but rosala takes top
priority the magistrate grants the
police permission to trace and record
phone conversations of people they
believe he may
contact inspector pazio manages to turn
one of the suspect's old friends into an
ally hello
we had earned her
trust very bravely this person chose to
inform
me it started with a puzzling phone call
in a language she didn't understand from
a number she didn't
recognize but it was the break
investigators were looking
[Music]
for she did not understand why they were
talking her in
Portuguese and she decided to give me
that number saying
weird strange I don't know this
number they speak a foreign language can
you check
it if risala placed the suspicious call
then it means he's fled the country and
is now in
[Music]
Portugal French authorities contact
interpol's National Central Bureau
headquarted in Lisbon
[Music]
Portugal we received the information
here at interpole we knew right away the
case was very
serious Dr Luis n is head of interpol's
national Central Bureau and the
coordinator of Investigations for the
Portuguese Ministry of Justice now he
must pick up the trail of the killer in
Lisbon we knew what he had done and that
he was a very dangerous man and we knew
he could
Escape French police traced the call
that rosal's friend had received it
originated from a phone booth in the
town of bisha deera 12 miles from
Lisbon law enforcement agencies in
Portugal find the
booth and verify the information on the
caller
ID now they can zero in on their
suspect we communicated with the French
via
andr to tell them that the place really
existed
and that their information was
[Music]
good french investigators fly to
Portugal to join their
colleagues John mhof and others depend
on this crucial level of
cooperation it's important for interpole
to be a partner in these investigations
and to uh Bridge communication gaps
[Music]
the person who brought the matter to
interpole should take credit for the
achievement because they had the good
sense to go that
[Music]
way we immediately went to B
de we brought in many criminal
investigators and spread out to try to
find
rosala within hours of staking out the
Phone Booth Lisbon detectives spot man
fitting rosal's description heading into
a post office they tell
[Music]
him this case of international
proportions hinges on what happens next
Lisbon police calculate the right moment
to take him down any slip and rosala
could
[Music]
disappear and when they strike they
strike
[Music]
fast Sid Amed
was French detectives confirm that the
man in cust is the railway Ripper Sid
ammed
rala rala was very
surprised he never suspected he would be
arrested
here while France prepares extradition
proceedings rosala stays imprisoned in
Portugal with his capture the French
authorities must now build their case
against
him they hire RI julen a movie special
effects designer to recreate Megan
Thompson's brutal death with mannequins
they reconstruct her terrifying last
moments being thrown from a speeding
train at
chabanet we positioned the mannequin on
the window
and the mannequin fell practically at
the same place where the body had been
found all the elements of the crime
matched our
reconstruction we knew the way he had
done it that he had thrown her by
topping her over the
window 4 months after ral's arrest a
French magazine publishes an interview
with rosala in a Portuguese
prison in the article rosala confesses
to the murders of all three
women he claims to have experienced
flashes of light that triggered him to
kill why did he
kill this is not just my opinion but
also what the psychologists think he was
in his own world in a bubble and then
everything external stopped to matter
the only thing that mattered was being
rejected he felt very bad being rejected
by a man or a woman and in that moment
he would turn into another person a very
dangerous
[Applause]
[Music]
one then one month after his confession
risala kills one last time
[Music]
inside a Portuguese prison just a few
weeks before going back to France to
stand trial he sets his mattress on fire
within minutes he dies of smoke
inhalation if rosala had not died he
would have been sent to France maybe 10
or 15 days
later that was what scared him the most
having to go back to jail France
[Music]
again but now as suddenly as it began it
was over for the Killer and for the
families of the
victims at the home of rosal's first
victim the news of his death comes as a
Shar detective Constable Dian M assisted
Megan Thompson's Family through their
ordeal on the one hand a satisfactory
trial and result of trial brings some
finality for the
family but on the other
hand the fact that they didn't have to
suffer a trial they didn't have to go
through the trauma of that
trial was again a
relief inspector pazio and his
colleagues from Dijon gain valuable
knowledge by working with the police in
different interpole member
countries this small case touched
Portugal touched Great Britain and in
some way that brought us
[Music]
closer it was a terrible case above all
these people did not deserve what
happened to
them you feel quite helpess when fa with
these acts but we cannot prevent
everything
the overwhelming publicity surrounding
the case focuses The public's attention
on train
safety the French national railroad
improves Security on the night route
reestablishing confidence in the
venerable
Railways Megan Thompson's Family makes
certain that their daughter's tragic
death will contribute to the awareness
they donate money given in their
daughter's name to the suie Lampo trust
a foundation that helps to educate young
men and women about protecting
themselves as they travel the continent
of
[Music]
Europe in shadowy ports along the east
coast of the United
States a perverse form of the American
dream plays out
Chinese immigrants smuggled into the
country sell their lives to Chinese
gangsters welcome to America the value
of these clandestine operations $3
billion a year
worldwide the Smugglers use many routs
but their final destination is New York
City and its thriving Chinese
Community this criminal Enterprise finds
fertile soil in mainland
[Music]
China the tianan Square massacre in 1989
began a huge Crackdown on personal
freedom and sparked a flood of migration
from mainland China into British
controlled Hong
Kong every day Hong Kong authorities
brought hundreds of illegals into camps
before deporting them back to the
mainland
a second wave of mass migration begins
in the late 1990s as the official
Handover of Hong Kong to China
approaches thousands of Chinese citizens
turn to the Smugglers called the
snakeheads named for a deadly predatory
fish for a chance at a new life in the
west most have no idea they are buying
into an entirely new set of dangers
the migrants pin all their hopes on a
one-way ticket to American
Prosperity human smuggling uh has been
very lucrative um there can be no doubt
about
that over the last decade agent Todd
bankra of Hong Kong Interpol has
witnessed the explosion of the human
smuggling trade and the desperation of
its
victims our intelligence indicates that
uh the snakeheads or the the uh
Syndicate masterminds have been charging
up to uh us uh
$45,000 uh per head and when you take
into consideration that uh in mainland
China uh most people earn less than $1
per day then it's a phenominal
figure recruiters find no shortage of
villagers willing to pay a steep price
for a shallow
promise but pulling it off requires a
complex criminal Network
they have to have a source country the
ability to identify folks that they're
going to
transport John mhof former head of
interpol's us
office you have to have an smuggling
route where you have the access across
the borders then you have to have a
destination point where those people can
be secreted and the money can be
collected for the
delivery the recruiters tell people that
if they come to America they can easily
become wealthy
before they ever you know step on the
soil of America they fantasize a
lot Steven Wong reports for the Chinese
language newspaper
Sinta they fantasized about Easy Living
very easy to make money in a few year
they can be able to buy a one family
house air conditioning every rooms two
car garage you're very happy
but as soon as their feet touch American
soil they're over their heads in
debt they'll spend up to seven
impoverished years working to pay the
snake heads
[Music]
off if an immigrant can't earn her
passage the snakeheads go after her
family back in China
[Music]
it takes just a phone
call they we say they do not have the
monies ready and that's the uh torturing
Parts you know Comm in painful enough to
squeam so the other side can hear
it once is sometimes not
enough the gangsters will repeat the
tactic until they've squeezed every
dollar they can get
the family knowing that they're getting
tortur or maybe getting going to get
killed they would go out and borrow
money if they do not have anything they
would call all the cousins distant
cousins every one of them come up with
few th000 to uh B this individual
out these Chinese gangs use violence as
a weapon they kill you if you don't play
ball this is generally an ethnic on
ethnic crime so once they transcend
their own borders in there in another
country they Lo they lose the ability to
communicate with anyone they don't have
law enforcement contacts uh and they
become uh isolated and dependent on
their
captors the immigrants can't go to the
police because they're here
[Music]
illegally and besides they have an
inherent distrust of all
authority unfortunately we were brought
up not to trust the police we were
brought up the police are corrupted we
were brought up that they are
evil so it's very difficult for the
police to tell you know to recruit or to
talk to somebody who happens to be a
victim of a crime or witness a crime we
learned how to mind our own business to
keep our mouth
shut the gangs know it and exploit it
viciously if a smuggled immigrant tries
to slip the gang's grasp her punishment
will be Swift and
unrelenting females will be sexually
arrest or assaulted or sometimes again
rape in front of everybody
of the many Chinese gangs in New York
City the fuk Ching gang claims the
biggest stake in Alien
smuggling the snakeheads conduct their
business
[Music]
carefully they use their connections to
organized crime in China and the United
States to smuggle in hundreds hundreds
of thousands of illegals every
year one of the most powerful snakeheads
a man named Wang
UI he masterminds lucrative smuggling
deals trading human cargo with other
snakeheads Wong claims to be a
construction worker and restaurant
employee he relies on the fuk Ching gang
and its 27-year-old leader a
a convicted felon who served time for
extortion in 1988 a was deported but he
soon came back and resumed his criminal
business a depends on his Lieutenant
shinen
Lin to do his Dirty
[Music]
Work 30-year-old Lynn uses violence and
torture to carry out his boss's orders
and behind it all stands the formidable
Shang Chui
ping they call her big sister ping and
she bankrolls the whole
thing she's worth an estimated $30
[Music]
million sister ping manages to wield
enormous power power without ever
dirtying her
hands for more than a decade she has run
a souvenir shop and a restaurant in New
York's
Chinatown but her main source of income
comes in under the
counter she operates an illegal money
transfer business that immigrants use to
send money back to
China the service grows so popular that
the nearby and legitimate Bank of China
has to offer new customers free
televisions to compete with her
operation this 43-year-old illegal
immigrant was smuggled into America in
1981 soon after she and her husband
began bringing in huge illegal shiploads
of Chinese
citizens some think she's a saint
helping families come together in the
prosperous United
States others in including the police
think she's a virtual slave
trader the ins nailed her once and
convicted her of
smuggling she's already served 6 months
in
prison from what I heard from other
people from different sources you know I
believe she is a smug with the strong
connection to the fuk chain G the
underworld sister ping has the money the
fuk Ching Gang has the means
[Music]
and together they plan a major
score now they plan to move almost 300
Chinese
immigrants the Smugglers expect to pull
in over $9
million sister ping agrees to share a
healthy cut of the profits with gang
leader
a but his lieutenant Shing Jan Lin will
receive only his usual rate as an
enforcer they outfit a rundown freighter
called the Golden Venture for this new
smuggling
operation the ship leaves Bangkok on
February 14th
1993 and stops off in Pia Thailand to
pick up 90
passengers two weeks later it arrives in
Kenya to pick up 190 more
passengers then the frighter heads for
[Music]
Boston months before the ship reaches
the American east coast Lynn Corners his
boss for more
money he tells a that if he doesn't get
a bigger share he will leave the gang
and take members with
him but AK refused
uses setting the stage for a
showdown so zind and Lynn wanted to take
over the gang from
AR former assistant prosecutor Bill
Murray they had the Golden Venture
coming in 300 illegal immigrants on that
ship $35,000 a piece due to math because
who ever controlled those 300 bodies and
the $35,000 that each one represented
was the one who was going to control the
[Music]
gang a knows that his rebellious
Lieutenant Lynn now poses a
threat one that he will have to deal
with and
soon gang Lieutenant Lynn contacts his
own enforcer kinen
Lee AO the
ship it's time for Lynn to take over A's
business Lynn orders the enforcer Lee to
divert the ship from Massachusetts to
New York where his men can unload
it Lee and Lynn agree to wait until the
Golden Venture draws closer to shore to
make their
move the captain and crew has expect
nothing they stay on course to unload
the ship off the Massachusetts
Coast below deck the months of living in
squalor have taken their toll on the
immigrants many have dissenter and are
constantly
seasick I came across with somebody that
you know do not have enough water to
drink and still bottle of water and
somebody have to break his
arm I know some females that have to you
know trade sacks for food it's not
ready a learns that Lynn plans to seize
control of the Golden
Venture enraged he strikes fast and
calls in a Hitman to assassinate
Lynn problem within fuk ching and all
gang war is about to
erupt
win whoever wins the fight for control
of the gang will inherit the lives of
almost 300 people steaming across the
[Music]
Atlantic an Asian crime syndicate
capitalizes on the dreams of hopeful
Chinese immigrants
and the Wy big sister ping pulls all the
strings 2 months before the Golden
Venture leaves the Far East and picks up
almost 300
passengers they're heading towards
America the conditions on the freighter
are
squalid but for most of the passengers
the arduous journey is a small price to
pay for the promis have a better
tomorrow the most basic motivator for
illegal immigrants to leave their
country is
survival they're trying to escape
extreme poverty or governmental
oppression uh so they're willing to take
the risks ironically they often end up
in worse situations such as slavery uh
when they're finished the immigration
process
in New York's Chinatown the battle for
control of this smuggling operation
spills onto the
streets the leader of the fuk Ching gang
a has ordered a hit on his Lieutenant
Shin Chan Lin for trying to steal
[Music]
control A's Hitman takes out Lynn's two
bodyguards but he runs out of bullets
and Lynn
escapes a knows that his men got away
and that means all out War within the
fuk Ching
gang fearing Lynn's Revenge a meets with
his brothers at his New Jersey home he
gives them instructions for unloading
the Golden
Venture and leaves the
country detective Thomas goldrick
investigat the gang
murders B feared some sort of
[Music]
retaliation We Believe V K left for
China uh after the January murders
simply due to the fact that Zin Dan Lyn
had
escaped the escalating gang violence in
Chinatown attracts the attention of the
media reporter Steven w
when the San Francisco Chronicle
interview me I described alien smuggling
during that time was the best business
for any Under
World on April 28th 1993 the San
Francisco Chronicle breaks the story of
the human smuggling trade and gives the
secretive sister ping prominent
ink this once lowprofile crime becomes
Front Page News
[Music]
with the Golden Venture just weeks from
reaching the United States sister ping
can't afford to let Authority see any
more of her shiploads of illegal
immigrants the captain of the Golden
Venture an Indonesian named Amir
[Applause]
tobing receives orders to wait off the
coast he agrees even though food and
water aboard ship are critically
low in his move to take over from the
snakeheads Lynn calls kinen Lee his
enforcer aboard the Golden
Venture he tells him to order the
captain to take the ship to New
York but Captain tobing
[Music]
refuses and his crew forces Lee off the
bridge
take care of him take care of
him but kin sinley isn't taking no for
an
answer he commandeers 12 Chinese
[Music]
passengers then arms them with guns
knives and even
sticks he forces them to storm the
bridge of the Golden Venture
in a matter of seconds kin sinley and
his men seize the
[Music]
ship they handcuff captain tobing and
hold him in his
quarters kinin Lee the enforcer takes
control and orders the first officer to
steam ahead to the United
States He informs Lynn that the Golden
Venture will be off the coast of New
York City within a week
but Lynn has some unfinished business to
settle
first he has to kill the men who tried
to assassinate him a and his
[Music]
brothers then he can cease control of
the
gang the boat and its $9 million human
cargo he believes A's Clan is hiding at
his house in New Jersey
a and his brothers stand between Lynn
and a $9 million
[Music]
Payday the freighter Golden Venture
approaches the coast of New York
City the value of its human cargo over
$9 million
but a war is Raging within the fuk Ching
gang over control of the ship and its
cargo Lynn and his followers storm the
Suburban New Jersey home of gang leader
[Music]
a they Gunn down all of the gang members
inside including a
Brothers but AK himself is gone he's
fled to
[Music]
China police arrive in minutes
it was a bloody brutal crime scene the
um we observed a dead Asian male by the
uh by the front uh
door he had received numerous gunshot
wounds along with stab
wounds we had two people in the basement
that were duct taped and shot uh and
also another Asian male uh was found on
the street about a block away uh from
the crime scene uh also shot numerous
times
there were well over 400 pieces of
evence handguns a machine gun hunting
knives serrated saws
handcuffs but additional evidence
suggests the killers didn't have time to
cover their
tracks there were gallons of gasoline
that were brought in because they had
planned to subsequently burn the house
down to destroy any evidence they might
have left
behind in the affluent normally quiet
suburb of tck New Jersey the murders
shock the
neighbors Witnesses quickly give police
a description of the
van police radio the van's license
number and description to all
officers they put up Road blocks along
the
Palisades and check every vehicle
looking for the
[Music]
van caught in the drag net Shing Jan Lin
and his
gang officers approach the van
warily right away they see blood on the
men
[Music]
inside they order everyone out for a
search you out the car close the
door on the ground on the
ground they question every man but
nobody's
talking police arrest the gang members
on the spot suspicion
[Music]
homicide the New Jersey crime lab
analyzes the blood swabbed from the
suspects the DNA is a match with the
victim's blood sample
ballistics also ties the weapons to the
gang
members with this evidence authorities
charge them with multiple counts of
homicide investigators still don't know
the
motive and the suspects still won't
talk but the physical evidence gives
police what they
need meanwhile the Golden Venture nears
the coast of New York
City Lee the enforcer tries in vain to
reach Lynn on the
radio the impact of the murders in tenek
as it relates to the Golden Venture were
profound zindan ly and all of his people
were arrested at the George Washington
Bridge within 15 minutes leaving no
hierarchy left in the fuk Ching gang in
the eastern United States there was no
one to direct the offloading of the ship
to to give instructions to the people
that were responsible on the
ship with a and
China Lynn in
jail and sister ping staying out of the
public
eye the crew and passengers on the ship
idle off the coast for 13
days food and water are running out
then in the early morning hours of June
6th the on duty alarm sounds at the
coast guard station in Brooklyn New
York it was kind of a breezy night it
was clear visibility so we' be able to
see very easy it looked like a routine
sort of boater and distress kind of
call Coast Guard officer William Mundy
is one of the first to
arrive I had no idea what we were about
to face until we got close enough to see
the people jumping on off the boat and
into the water then we knew we had a bad
situation 200 yd off the New York Shore
well the Golden Venture runs ground on a
sandbar dozens of people scramble over
the decks and throw themselves into
freezing 5-ft swells we could see all
the people on the deck people in the
water we knew that this had to be some
kind of illegal alien operation going on
right away because these people were
just running to the side of the boat and
jumping jumping into the water without
looking at it without anything they were
just getting off the boat nothing was
slowing them
down the ship's engine still on Full
Throttle feudly churns the ocean as its
enormous screws bite the
water most people went to the front of
the boat cuz it was closer to the
beach the ones that went off the back
they went through the screws
[Music]
Coast Guard and police helicopters hover
over the boat ordering the passengers to
remain on
board stay on board do not jump off
repeat stay on
board but Panic engulfs the ship as
terrified passengers leap into the
violent Seas
below while authorities in a New Jersey
suburb grapple with a blood Chinese Gang
Related
homicide the freighter Golden Venture
runs a ground in New York
Harbor the ship carries its cargo of
nearly 300 men and women who entrusted
their lives to human Smugglers known as
snakeheads we have Coast Guard and New
York police helicopter Pilots call for
assistance but they watch helplessly as
frantic passengers leap from the
stranded ship
emergency Personnel care for those
strong enough to make it to
shore it looked like chaos we see people
you know lying down could not tell
whether you know this person still
breathing or not and then later on I
find out know this guy is
dead despite rescuer efforts the current
slams bodies against the
Jetties seven people die
I could see this massive group of people
um that was growing as more and more law
enforcement responded and more and more
aliens were pulled off the vessel or out
of the water special agent Karen Pace
investigates the disaster for the
Immigration and Naturalization
Service many of the aliens as they uh
before they jumped they bagged up what
few items they had and pled bags and
they jumped overboard with those bags
but being the water was so rough they
couldn't maintain holding that and
swimming uh so these bags of uh items
would wash up on the
shore when the ins questions the
passengers they answer only one thing
political
Asylum they don't mention the ship's
crew or the criminal events on
board someone had clearly coached these
passengers into Collective amnesia
when I ask them who's The Smuggler or
who's the recruiter if you do not know
who's The Smuggler you know they were
hesitate they will pause then they will
try to tell you something else and they
will try to tell you that you know I
love this country I love
America the ins takes 276 people into
custody buses bring them to nearby Fort
Tien Military Reservation for processing
and
questioning watch the bus make sure
nobody gets home to get the full story
investigators separate the crew from the
passengers the crew was Indonesian and
Burmese uh so they looked a little
different and were dressed a little
differently and were more easily to
identify once they isolate the crew
members investigators try to determine
who was responsible for this Death Ship
did you know other
people we asked them questions like who
gave you permission to go on Deck were
you allowed on Deck who told you when
you could eat uh if there was a fight on
board who enforced discipline were there
fights on board one crew
member stood out a little differently
because he was not Indonesian or Burmese
uh and he claimed to be a passenger only
um but we suspected this was not true
and that person subsequently was
identified as uh kinen lee who was the
chief Smuggler on board the the
ship there were people who were not
there on the beach June 6th who actually
were the Smugglers and organizers who
are the masterminds behind this this
smuggling Venture and those are the
people we really wanted to identify and
arrest and bring to
[Music]
Justice two of the snakeheads behind the
shipment
big sister ping and her partner in crime
wangu Chui see the disaster on
television wangu Chui disappears in New
York's
Chinatown big sister ping escapes to
China hiding out in her native home in
fujan
Province she continues her smuggling
operations without missing a Beat
the ins secures a warrant to search the
ship pac's team Combs the Golden
Venture
clear the living conditions on the boat
were terrible when you look at the boat
and you see what the way these people
lived for several months on this ship
how does one human being do that to
another the choking stench of urine and
vomit fills the
hold there is only one
toilet very little food or
water they were truly victimized by
their uh by their own people and that's
what I uh really am amazed at the the
level of
exploitation agents scour the Golden
Venture and they find a
lead it looks like a list of names and
phone
numbers this list that was uncovered
which was in poor condition um was
written in the Chinese language
including phone books and and scraps of
papers with telephone
numbers investigators Rush the documents
to the forensics
lab before the ins can translate these
scraps of paper
they need to dry and preserve the
evidence wait what did he do with the
passengers Pace continues interrogating
Captain tobing and the
crew and the story of Lee's Mutiny
unfolds the ship's first officer told
the INS What happened as they approached
the shore
Le's men warned the passengers that the
ship was being deliberately run
ground anyone who could swim was told to
try to make it to
shore the others were ordered to stay on
board until the snake heads came to pick
them
up political
[Music]
but as the Golden Venture rattled and
shook the miserable passengers dashed
towards the door of the hold to what
they believed was
Freedom once the ship tore Into The
Sandbar Panic took
[Music]
over even as pace and her team untangled
the story of The Golden Venture the
investigation continues at the beach
[Music]
within days authorities pull three more
corpses from the water bringing the
total to 10
dead still more remain missing and
investigators start piecing together the
story we had a homicide investigation
and an alien smuggling investigation so
we want to identify the snake kads and
uh and arrest
them as the forensic scientist s begin
to translate the documents from the
ship they give Pace a solid
lead the names of 19
snakeheads including Wango
Chui we sawar his name and a list of
people under him then we compareed that
to the ship to shore records and that
showed a telephone number that was
subscribed to by his
wife pace and her agents hit the streets
in Chinatown to chase the
lead finally authorities know the names
of the
snakeheads
a wangu
Chuy and sister
[Music]
ping they expand the Manhunt
internationally calling upon Interpol to
find the criminals and bring them to
justice 10 people die when the Golden
Venture a Freer loaded with human cargo
runs a ground in New York
Harbor ins agent Karen Pace has learned
the names of the so-called snakeheads
behind the deadly
Voyage a the leader of the fuking Gang
has left the country
Interpol has alerted its offices around
the world to track him
[Music]
down in New York City the circle
tightens around the criminals behind the
Golden
Venture the ins traces Snakehead Wang UI
to his girlfriend's apartment in
Chinatown in April 1994 Karen pace and a
team stti out the apartment
we were sitting there for several hours
when we observed them going to the
building ins agents rush in behind
[Music]
them open
up open up
now they tear up the place looking for
one
and question his
[Music]
girlfriend wangu Chuy the powerful
snakehe head cowers in a
[Music]
Closet during his interrogation wangui
gives up another name for the ins to add
to their list of suspects Shang Chui
ping the woman known as sister
ping authorities know the name she's
already served 6 months for smuggling
aliens ins agents now intensify their
search for the snakehead
Mastermind sensing The Fallout from the
Golden Venture disaster sister ping has
already left the
[Music]
country interpole issues a red notice
for sister ping alerting authorities
worldwide about a warrant for her arrest
for human
smuggling from her previous conviction
authorities have her fingerprints and
mugshot on file
[Music]
but now she's out of their reach almost
7,000 M away in her native home in
shenmai
[Music]
China she hides in her luxurious
three-story pagota financed by smuggling
profits sister ping protects herself by
bribing local officials she's
conspicuous but untouchable
Hong Kong interpo also receives a red
notice for
a now Interpol catches a
break an informant tips them off that a
is living comfortably in the Western
District of the
city a is arrested without a fight and
they extradite him to the United
[Music]
States his conspirators are already
serving
time
wangui receives 10 years after pleading
guilty to smuggling and manslaughter
charges Shing Jan Lin four life terms
plus 40 years for murder and
kidnapping and a is sentenced to 20
years for
rering but sister ping the big fish is
still at
large in all 22 people serve time for
crimes related to The Golden Venture
disaster 10 passengers die and six
remain
missing life for the nearly 300 victims
of the snakeheads remains
difficult for those surviving the
horrific Journey from China to New York
New York City less than half remain in
the United
States many endure several years of
detention and more than 30 live in limbo
not knowing if they will be sent back to
China and there are very good reasons
why the immigration laws exist but at
the same time we are human beings and
there's a certain amount of compassion
that extends to people who are in a
situation where they're merely trying to
survive it's a difficult equation
personally but uh it is one that has to
be met and has to be met with
compassion the tragic death of 10
illegal immigrants aboard the Frader the
Golden Venture tears the lid off the
lucrative underground industry of
trafficking in human
beings Golden Venture is like an alarm
that you know waking up everybody but
it's been shut off almost immediately
people don't want to know there an alarm
people still want to go back to sleep
International police know that sister
ping is still
busy she travels freely using three
passports and continues her smuggling
operations but interpole does not give
up 7 years later in April
2000 agents discover the name of sister
Ping's son on a passenger list for a
flight from Hong Kong to the United
States I think International cooperation
in this case was very important the
United States law enforcement officials
together with Hong Kong officials
managed to uh pinpoint her and pinpoint
her
location we obtained a domestic arrest
warrant to arrest Chang and uh and that
put the whole thing in
action 11 agents Converge on the scene
intent on nailing The elusive smuggling
Kingpin they know this might be their
only chance to catch ping while she's
vulnerable local police search the crowd
at the Hong Kong airport hoping to spot
her sister ping carries three fake
passports from Biz Hong Kong and the
United
States she claims it's a case of
mistaken identity
[Music]
but her fingerprints tell a different
story finally sister ping Snakehead is
hooked but proving her guilt in court is
another
[Music]
matter although Hong Kong returned to
Chinese rule in
1997 the extradition treaty between Hong
Kong and the United States remains in
effect
[Music]
my unit within the interpool division
was specifically responsible for the
extradition of Chang Choy ping to the
United States she was quite a tough
cookie uh but in the end uh justice
prevailed and she went
[Music]
back in July of 2003 10 years after the
Golden Venture ran a
ground sister ping returns to New York
City to stand trial for her crimes
she faces charges for alien smuggling
hostage taking and money
laundering ironically even after the
Golden Venture disaster some in the
Chinese immigrant Community still refer
to her fondly as big sister ping
in Brazil a wealthy businessman gets
kidnapped the tense negotiations air on
live
TV 3600 M away in Nicaragua another kind
of disaster seemingly unrelated yet
inextricably
late Decades of violence and Revolution
once tore these streets
apart and the residents of Managua araga
thought those days had
passed May 23rd
1993 While most people in the Santa Rosa
neighborhood outside of the capital
sleep a nightmarish blast exposes the
Hideous secret right under their
feet and unearths a crucial piece of
evidence missing for almost 4 years
[Music]
the explosion was very
loud
frightening there's a lot of dust
Windows
broken it totally destroyed 16
houses the blast awakens Managua police
officer Marlon manano who lives
nearby he's the first on the scene
and gets right to
[Music]
work three explosions demolish an auto
repair shop and the neighborhood around
it emergency Personnel respond
quickly dozens of injured residents
wander in a
days authorities rush to set up field
triage units to treat the wounded
as Rescuers search for people trapped in
the extensive
wreckage the destruction reminds many of
the earthquakes that have rocked the
region in the
past but this is no natural
disaster Montano's first job find out
what caused such a large
explosion investigators suspect a
propane gas tank blew up
[Music]
but some distinctive metal fragments
strewn throughout the area suggest
something more
Sinister authorities find remnants of a
grenade launcher crushed into a front
yard Montano and the investigators
approached the obvious flash point of
the explosion the auto repair shop where
they discover something much more
Grizzly human
remains by coincidence criminal
investigator Carlos bandna also runs
Nicaragua's interpo division at the time
a job that will soon prove
crucial the blast caused total
Destruction I saw body parts from
victims more than a 100 yard from the
site in the chaos police make another
startling Discovery a weapons bunker
hidden under the auto repair shop
[Music]
[Applause]
as investigators sift through the debris
they uncover a steel reinforced concrete
stronghold complete with metal
doors tunnels Branch out leading to
several more underground Chambers
housing a massive arsenal of deadly
weapons I'm talking about
AK-47s and missiles
[Music]
Bazookas in the bunker police find
nearly two dozen surface to a
missiles many with their serial numbers
obliterated and a store of C4 plastic
explosives produced only for the
military but B and the investigators
know these explosives have another
use on the black market they're a
favorite item for terrorists and that
escalates the importance of this case
right to the
[Music]
top the discovery of the illegal weapons
Arsenal and its terrorist links alarm
law abiding
nicaraguans after Decades of upheaval
under the Samoan dictatorship followed
by a Revolution by the left wings and
denas Nicaragua still struggles for
stability The Rebirth of democracy began
in
1990 when nicaragu elected moderate
vieta Chamorro to the
presidency yet trouble still plagues the
country Guerilla bands remain armed and
organized chamaro knows she needs help
to dismantle
them after a 14-year absence Nicaragua
rejoins
Interpol the organization offers its
investigative brains and muscle to the
struggling
Nation they didn't have the experience
to handle all of
this the country had just gotten out of
a military
regime Brazilian federal police chief
romea Tuma is the vice president of
interpole in Latin
America the bunker proves terrorists are
working to destabilize Latin America
again president Chamorro was trying to
reinstall
democracy it was alarming that they
found these kinds of weapons in their
country
then as they continue sifting through
the weapons bunker they make an even
more chilling
Discovery proof of a global terrorist
conspiracy the stash includes hundreds
of fraudulent identification papers from
over 20
countries police find driver's licenses
birth certificates and passports with
the photos of known gorilla leaders
enabling them to operate anywhere in the
world
among the papers are documents for two
Canadian
Nationals David Spencer and Christine
Lamont both convicted controversially in
a high-profile kidnapping several years
before they had three four different
passports of Peace some with photographs
with eyeglasses some
without they would use these to move
secretly from country to Country under
different
[Music]
names to the investigators the documents
show that terrorist groups throughout
the world had banded together to form a
well organized Terror Cooperative a
precursor of organizations like today's
Al-Qaeda the new discovery changes the
investigation former US Interpol
director John
mhof once you have a cache of
information such as this um then the
impetus isn't so much just to solve the
crime of who blew up this building but
to also understand um how far reaching
uh this criminal Enterprise this
terrorist Enterprise is the terror
groups likely entered the country years
earlier while the Revolutionary
sandinistas
ruled Nicaragua under the sandinistas
became an
asylum any foreign group involved in
violent anti-government political
activity was offered protection there
and found Refuge
when the sandinistas fell many of these
violent refugees stayed
behind now Interpol realizes they've
combined their resources becoming
well-armed and
organized managa police take no chances
they plac the fake IDs passports files
and other documents under heavy
guard president Chamorro orders
Nicaraguan Interpol Chief Carlos Bend to
lead the investigation and to contact
the country cited in the
documents something big is brewing
terrorism possibly on a global level and
Interpol means to stop
it I used interpol's resources to call
different countries to see if they would
collaborate with the Nicaraguan
police interpol's Romeo Tuma is one of
the first to respond he travels from
Brazil to Managua to help organize the
man hunt for the group behind the stolen
passports and Forged
IDs he faces a daunting task the massive
amount of evidence over 6,000 documents
fills 40 file
boxes meanwhile Managua police work the
local angle they track down an address
for the proprietor of the auto repair
shop Miguel
Moreno apparently a typical small
business owner who is harboring known
terrorists investigators need to find
out
why police raid the suspect's
[Music]
home but Moreno's
gone the respectable auto repair shop
was a Flawless cover for the terrorist
groups to stash weapons and
documents but how much did the employees
know about it
we found out that a night Watchman at
the shop had been injured in the
explosion and we went to the hospital to
question
him police learned that shop owner
Miguel Moreno's real name is isubo
aralo a member of the terrorist
organization called Spanish Basque ETA
I he's wanted in Spain in connection
with several terrorist
Acts including
[Music]
murder Managua police notify
Interpol obviously there's a time out on
here that has to be done quickly so what
are we talking about we're talking about
an ability to communicate with the other
country immediately and that spells
interpole striking before the trail goes
cold interpo issues a red notice for the
arrest of asubio
aralo the terrorist now appears on
interpol's most wanted list alerting
member countries to apprehend
him but he's probably already assumed
another
[Music]
identity among the illicit documents
recovered from the bunker investigators
find dossier on business political and
corporate leaders from Latin America
Mexico and
Brazil leading to a chilling
realization the dossier confirmed they
were financing their organizations
through kidnapping businessmen in Latin
speaking
countries each dossier contains a
complete profile on each potential
kidnapping victim daily travels and
personal habits security concerns Maps
suggested Ransom amounts the best kind
of information that a law enforcement
agency can get is information that's
anticipatory of a
crime interpole now has a leg up on the
kidnappers they act fast to protect the
targets interpole notifies the countries
where the targeted subjects
live in many cases they foil the
kidnappers but in one case they are too
late one of the dosier names a Brazilian
Tycoon kidnapped almost 4 years earlier
December 11th
1989 Supermarket magnate ailio Denise
one of the wealthiest men in
Brazil leaves his Mansion for work in
South
Pao the Denise company built by his
father has an annual profit of $65
million
us Denise separated from his wife lives
with his
sister he has a close family and his
kidnappers have studied it very
thoroughly preparing to make their move
[Music]
[Applause]
in less than a minute the gunman capture
a Bilo
Denise and disappear thinking they left
behind no
Witnesses but their Flawless plan has a
[Music]
crack in 199 93 an explosion in
Nicaragua reveals a cash of weapons and
plans for a string of kidnappings by an
alliance of terrorist
groups the kidnapping plot sheds new
light on the 1989 Abduction of
52-year-old Brazilian businessman ailio
Denise ailio Denise uh is one of the
richest men in Brazil he is the um
president of one of the largest
Supermarket chains in the country he was
on his way to work he was driving in the
in his car Isabelle Vincent was the
Latin American bureau chief for the
Toronto globe and male newspaper and
lived in Brazil at that
time the kidnappers cut him off uh with
a
van a fake ambulance that that they had
created and they drove him
off a witness to the abduction recog
Denise and rushes to the Millionaire's
Mansion to notify his sister who lives
with
him hello
okay organized and efficient the the
kidnappers quickly cover their
tracks and vanish with
[Music]
Denise by the time the witness tells
Denise's sister what he saw no in it's
too late
and terrified she calls the
police Nelson gimen the chief of sa
Paulo's anti-kidnapping division takes
the
call I always say that kidnapping is
made of two
halves like a
game the first half belongs to the
kidnappers our main goal is to preserve
that victim's life
in the second
half it's up to us to recover the
[Music]
victim John mhof former head of
interpole in the United
States there's always this cat and mouse
game that goes on between the the
criminals and and the police officer and
it really is part of why police come to
this work they want they want to play
that chess game but the game is a
dangerous one an epidemic of abductions
in Latin America in the late ' 80s have
left many victims dead over 500
abductions in one year
alone investigators vow to bring this
one to a safe and peaceful
ending it won't be easy these kidnappers
are skilled experienced and
vient if they don't get paid their
victims will die along with anyone who
get in the
way see 30 excruciating minutes after
they snatch ailio Denise the kidnappers
make their first Contact a woman warns
the Denise family not to contact police
if they want him back safely oh Wonder
stop she says she will call back with
further instructions and will kill
Denise if their demands are not
met no one knows whether the kidnappers
have already harmed Denise
his family desperate to learn if he is
all right will do anything to free
him within hours police find the vehicle
used in the kidnapping just a few miles
from the Denise
home the kidnapper's attempt to disguise
it as an ambulance only worked during
the
heist when we found the ambulance we
started to to examine it
thoroughly we practically took it
apart inside the ventilation system we
found a business card from a mechanic's
garage near the center of the
[Music]
city the police try to calm the Denise
family and convince them to trust the
experienced investigators rather than
act on their own
we instantly set in motion our plans
tapping phones and putting agents out on
the
street
frto
attend after several tense hours waiting
the Denise family gets another
[Music]
call hello this time the kidnappers
named their price for the safe return of
ailio Denise $30
million following advice from the police
the family agrees but tells them it will
take time to get the
money the kidnappers say they will call
back later to arrange a
[Music]
drop investigators leave to coordinate
the operation from police
[Music]
headquarters meanwhile at their Hideout
the kidnappers blast music into Den's
cell to drawn out conversation and
disorient their
captive it's psychological Terror
[Music]
the police know that every tick of the
Clock Works against
them the kidnappings they don't solve
quickly often end in
death Brazilian police rushed to the
auto repair shop printed on the card
found in the fake
ambulance we questioned the owner and
started to unveil the mystery of the
[Music]
kidnapping the owner informs them that a
middle-aged man and a younger man
wearing glasses recently brought the
vehicle in for
repairs he did not get any names but he
gives the police the contact number for
the two
men investigators trace the phone number
to an apartment in sa Pao
officers enter the
apartment but find it
empty technicians install microphones
and transmitters hoping to learn where
Denise is being
held then we started to do surveillance
on the building where the phone was
we even got an apartment close
by they see several men coming and
going our investigators listened to the
people inside the
apartment we were certain that these
were the people who left the ambulance
behind when one suspect gets left alone
at the apartment officers sweep in to
get him
[Music]
in the raid police arrest ulyses ACO
unnown
terrorist but he's in no mood to
[Music]
cooperate while the Denise family hopes
and
prays Brazilian police know that time is
running out
[Music]
police and Interpol pursue the
kidnappers of wealthy Brazilian
businessman ailio
Denise their investigation leads
authorities to an apartment in sa
Paulo and to a known terrorist named
ulyses
aavo investigators haul asedo in for
interrogation
he claims to know nothing about the
Denise
abduction but authorities don't buy
it Nelson
gimen he has a long criminal
history he belonged to a revolutionary
movement in Chile the
Mir and he committed some robberies
there he had a knowledge of paramilitary
strategy
[Music]
in the apartment where Brazilian police
arrested
Oedo they discover a lead that brings
them another step closer to finding AO
Denise we found a light bill for an
apartment on Charles Darwin
Street it was another place they rented
for their kidnapping activities
police stake out the apartment laying
low so the kidnappers won't spot
them since we still didn't know where
the victim was we didn't want to raise
the kidnapper
suspicions we didn't want to make too
much noise because it could jeopardize
the victim's
life instead of raiding the place they
decide to take the suspects down one by
one one as they
[Music]
appear very quietly police apprehend
four more suspects from the ru Charles
Darwin
address but still no sign of a Bilo
Denise
[Music]
5 days after the Abduction the
kidnappers try to increase the pressure
on the Denise family hoping to extract
money from the wealthy
Brazilians the kidnappers forced ailio
to write a note begging them to pay the
ransom money
now or his captors will kill
[Music]
him the Denise family Waits desperate
for news
and grows more frustrated as the days
slip
away at any time the kidnappers could
panic and kill
ailio the police try to assure them
they're getting
close but the uncertainty gnaws at the
family and the
authorities interrogations
continue slowly carefully police tangula
complex conspiracy organized like a
private
Army Isabelle Vincent of the Toronto
globe and
maale it was clear to the police from
very early on that these people had some
kind of paramilitary training all of
them and it was clear that you know all
of the people knew how to use AK-47s
they could go to sleep at the drop of a
hat when their commanders told them to
go to sleep they all had their various
functions they were highly organized and
highly
sophisticated all the suspects belong to
various revolutionary groups banding
together for one reason to finance
terrorism through
kidnapping extracting details takes
time and time is their
enemy only a few people knew where
Denise was actually being held
the others only knew pieces of
information some people would know
activities up to a
point we had to interrogate with
caution one by one to know the link
where one piece ended and another would
[Music]
begin 5 days into the abduction a
suspect finally crashed
he tells police where ailio Denise is
being
held taking one of the kidnapping
suspects with them authorities head to
the
house the plan is to wait for more
support then move in
fast but two pumped up officers jump the
gun and start the takeown on their
own the heavily armed kidnappers see
only the two officers there's an open
fire the police have lost the element of
[Applause]
surprise w
[Music]
they regroup and Order even more backup
soon 200 tactical officers from the
elite anti-kidnapping division surround
the
house what should have been a surprise
attack has become a tense
[Music]
standoff the terrorists bring ailio
Denis to a
window he's still alive but they
threaten to kill him if they don't get
what they
want the police to avoid blood
shed they encourage the kidnappers to
pass notes back and
forth but the negotiations don't go
well they demanded $30
million an armored
car and an airplane to take them out of
the
[Music]
country these were their comms and they
didn't want to discuss
them obviously I absolutely didn't agree
with any of those
[Music]
terms the Denise family begins to lose
hope they don't think the police can
bring ailio home
alive the stalemate continues Into the
Night
the Tactical units take risks to stay
visible and show movement
outside the kidnappers want to stop
negotiating but the police refuse to let
them
rest the plan is to wear them
down this was a very complicated
situation requiring lots of people from
the police
forces the shock police
people from the military police who
specialize in more violent
conflicts at any time things could have
gotten out of
[Music]
control they cut all power plunging the
kidnappers Into Darkness
it's a risk no one can predict how the
kidnappers will
react they might cave in and surrender
or they could panic and kill their
hostage an organized network of
terrorist groups from different
countries has kidnapped wealthy
Brazilian businessman ailio
Denise the Brazilian police C capture
several
members and surround the kidnappers in a
house in sa
Paulo the first night of the standof
passes with no
surrender in the morning the kidnappers
ask police to inform the media and the
cameras show up soon
after Isabelle Vincent of the Toronto
Globe and
Mail the standoff was pretty tght it
lasted for hours with the kidnappers who
were in the house threatening to
threatening to kill deis and and
threatening to kill themselves on the
same day history is in the making in
Brazil the country holds its first
Democratic elections for president in
over 30
years but the Denise kidnapping
overshadows the
election Sal Pao anti-kidnapping
division Chief Nelson giman
we restarted the negotiations and they
requested to speak with some
ambassadors the police offered them the
Cardinal of s Paulo to
intermediate hoping to resolve the
standoff peacefully the Cardinal of sa
Paulo a respected human rights Advocate
carries messages between the kidnappers
and police
ailo's family watches the drama unfold
on live
television i m they're willing to do
whatever the kidnappers ask
Police Hold
firm not wanting to give in to
terrorists as the tension Rises no one
outside knows the fate of
Denise his captors frustrated and
cornered might end it their way
[Music]
hours
pass and still no
word it doesn't look
[Music]
good then on Sunday morning 6 days since
the kidnapping and 36 hours into the
standoff the exhausted kidnappers
finally give it up
they announce they're coming
out two Canadians leave the house
first David Spencer
26 and Christine Lamont
30 so when the kidnappers actually came
out of the house they were captured on
live television and this was going on at
the same time that people were voting in
the elections so at the end of the day
you have these 10 kidnappers coming out
um and also the election results but the
kidnapping was so Sensational that it
dwarfed anything that was going on in
the
elections the eight remaining kidnappers
are all Latin
[Music]
Americans but still no sign of
Denise alive or dead
[Music]
Brazilian police move into the house to
search for Denise
while the family and the country holds
its
breath the investigators of Interpol tie
together two seemingly unrelated cases
an explosion in managa Nicaragua in 1993
that exposes a weapons B were used by
terrorists and the 1989 kidnapping of
millionaire abilio Denise by a group of
those terrorists in sa Paulo
Brazil after a tense standoff on live TV
the kidnappers finally give themselves
up but the fate of the victim is
agonizingly
[Music]
uncertain police move through the house
carefully
in the basement they find a crude
holding
cell it's dark no
[Music]
movement inside they find ailio Denise
alive
[Music]
while Millions watch on television ailio
Denise walks free after 6 days in
solitary
confinement sa Paulo anti-kidnapping
division Chief Nelson
gimmer the victim was
confused
weak he had no sense of day or
night police scour the house for
evidence the plywood cell 1 1/2 by 3 m
contains a lap a small mattress and a
portable
toilet the kidnappers controlled light
sound and their victim's
movement clearly they are
professionals but who was their
Mastermind and what were they out to
accomplish interrogations begin for the
newly captured
kidnappers investigators discover that
David Spencer a Canadian who claims he
is a human rights worker rented the
house under an alias you don't know that
in the Box he and Christine lont make a
bizarre assertion they had no idea that
Denise was being held in their
home but police find evidence
implicating Lamont and Spencer numerous
aliases forged documents and phony
passports items more befitting
International criminals than human
rights workers
even so Canadian Human Rights Advocates
lobbied on their behalf and LaMont and
Spencer swore they were not
[Music]
involved the Canadians totally
participated in this plot from beginning
to
end they rented a
car they rented real
estate and both of them were there
guarding the victim
they played a striking role in the
[Music]
plot in 1990 ignoring International
uproar a Brazilian judge sentences the
pair to 28 years in
prison still they maintain their
[Music]
innocence but 3 years later and 3600 M
away when the three EXP explosions rip
through an auto repair shop in Nicaragua
interpole discovers even more evidence
connecting Lamont and Spencer to the
terrorists journalist Isabelle
Vincent what linked the bunker to the
de's kidnapping were a number of
personal items from uh Christine Lamont
and David Spencer they were the
link the documents from Christine and
David were false driver's licenses all
sorts of things to cover their tracks uh
false pass
passports Brazilian investigator Nelson
gimen believes that the Nicaraguan
weapons bunker connection provides
irrefutable proof of Spencer's and
Lamont's
[Music]
guilt to the people who said that the
kidnappers were human rights
Advocates I would say that the reality
is that these are cruel
people who deprive other people of
freedom
interpoles Romeo
Tuma they were caught red-handed with
the victim in the first
place in the second place all the
documents most of the fake
documents American passports belonging
to the
Canadians fake
signatures were linked to that criminal
organization now Interpol set it sights
on breaking up that terrorist syndicate
with information gathered from the
weapons bunker in Nicaragua Interpol
tracks down its
members the biggest Revelation um that
came out of the bunker explosion was the
fact that these groups these terrorist
groups from different countries um were
in fact working together and pooling
their resources both financial and
Military and everything
else interpole might have never
uncovered the terror coalition if not
for the careless mixing of C4 and
detonators that ignited the catastrophic
explosion police take six people into
custody including the night Watchman of
the auto repair shop in
Nicaragua in 1995 they're tried and
convicted on charges ranging from
property damage to document
forgery two others including the auto
repair shop owner isubo aralo who fled
to Cuba are tried in
obena they too are convicted and remain
listed as threats to National
Security after serving 10 years in
Brazil Lamont and Spencer win themselves
a transferred to a Canadian jail and
remarkably are released 10 weeks
later on rare occasions international
law enforcement officers discover a way
into the shadowy world of terrorist
organizations the Nicaraguan explosion
offered detailed Intelligence on how
efficiently these groups
operate the Intel ultimately saves lives
and helps fight Terror we learned that
there were a lot of people who were
professionals Engineers architects who
had come together in this in this group
um in order to build bunkers study
logistically how kidnappings could be
carried out
um like there there were a lot of
strategy sessions going on and and
certainly the documents found in
Nicaragua um illuminated a lot of
that with that crime ring
dissolved interpole stands better
prepared to fight any others that come
along Brazilian federal police chief
Romeo Tuma now a senator makes fighting
terrorism a priority
this group provided the motivation for
police to improve their methods to
reduce the number of
kidnappings and after September
11 terrorism became something that no
International Community
accepts so interpole will be a permanent
security
Force recent history has shown that no
Nation on Earth is safe from terrorism
and the fight against it continues
worldwide
[Music]
France October
1984 after
midnight the small Museum in the village
of simiron nois closed hours
ago but that doesn't stop some
determined art collectors
the thieves have done their
homework the museum has no security
system no bars on the
Windows nothing to stop
them and then know something crucial
that most of the town's residents take
for
granted this unassuming little mum holds
five
masterpieces by 19th century artist Jean
Baptist Camille
Koo they have never been on the
market making their value impossible to
measure
a good job warrants a nice tip one of
the robers takes it in the form of
antique coins snatched as an
afterthought
[Music]
with no Witnesses no Bloodshed and
almost no effort they accomplished their
mission snatching a treasure in art in a
matter of
minutes the next morning hours after the
fact a museum worker makes the
horrifying discovery
[Music]
he notifies the French garm the military
police that serve rural areas Sergeant
Jean Dei takes the Frantic
call the phone call was
short we didn't get a lot of details we
just got there as soon as possible
[Music]
the forensic team scour every centimeter
of the
museum they look for a dropped tool a
scrap of paper anything to help them but
the Simplicity of the crime makes it
that much harder to find
Clues the only Trace we found were shoe
prints in the
courtyard swap
the pr suggested at least two people
made off with the
painting the jarms call on inspector
Tuan poal from the Judiciary police in
Dijon the Commander in charge of art
crimes is
perplexed most of the stolen art cases I
worked on before
have not taken place in
museums because they're usually
[Music]
guarded but this obscure museum open
only a few months each year had no
guards no alarm
system no one ever expected a crime like
this they look like local criminals
couldn't have done it
[Music]
we thought that a private collector
discovered the paintings and may have
hired some criminals to steal
[Music]
them investigators conclude the heist
took less than 30
[Music]
minutes the museum curator distributes
pictures of the five stolen Coro
paintings
[Music]
inspector then another clue turns
up a fingerprint on a
[Music]
window police try to trace it but it
points
nowhere the problem was that the print
wasn't in our
files it might belong to one of the
criminals or maybe to a museum guest
we just couldn't
tell police faced the same dead end with
the shoe print which lacked
detail we were really I'd say absolutely
in a fog about who committed this
crime unfortunately there's a a very
vast market for stolen artwork out
there John imhof former head of
interpole in the United
States our theft is a huge huge problem
in and of itself but it can also be
intended to other crimes such as moneya
laundering if you think about it
something of Great Value can be hidden
in something very
[Music]
small the theft leaves Museum officials
baffled and
embarrassed the stolen coros grab the
attention of art experts from major
museums though many of the residents of
simura NOA did not even know about the
masterpieces prior to the
robbery the thieves had obviously paid
close attention to their arrival here in
the mid 1980s art theft had risen to an
all-time high thanks to a booming
International black
[Music]
market after drug trafficking after gun
trafficking comes art
trafficking M bzi former head of Francis
art theft
Squad there were a lot of works of art
being stolen in France and inole
recommended that we create a specialized
division of the police force with a
specific mission of finding works of art
these works of art are a part of the
inheritance of the human race the thefts
in samure were like electroshocks for
all the museums to equip themselves
better for
protection for most police agencies
around the world art theft takes a back
seat to more violent crimes but Interpol
knows that thieves often sell stolen art
to fund dangerous criminal and terrorist
activities for interpole an art theft of
this importance demands fast
action we needed help from the
International
Community we sent pictures of the
paintings to all the countries that are
members of
Interpol art changes hands every day
interpole needs to be sure it goes into
the right
hands for title to transfer for a piece
of art work you have to know that you
have clear title in the first place and
there's no place else to establish that
at the international level other than
the Interpol stolen artworks
database if a piece of artwork has been
properly registered in the interpole
database there will be a sure hit that
yes this is a stolen piece of artwork
[Music]
despite interpol's worldwide search for
the five coros the paintings are not
recovered the culprits have apparently
gone deep under ground and their Artful
crime in seon NOA is about to be
eclipsed by one far more
[Music]
audacious the painting impression so
leavon Impression
Sunrise this iconic Masterpiece by
Claude Monae caused a sensation when it
debuted in
1874 this is the painting that gave
impressionism its name it is literally
Priceless for years Monae had kept the
painting at his home in Jer
France now it hangs along with other
National Treasures in the elegant marot
tan Museum located in paris's 16th
District every day hundreds of French
and foreign tourists come to Marvel at
the historic
painting but on a bright Sunday morning
in October
1985 thieves follow them
in and Impression Sunrise makes
headlines once again
the thieves make a quick detour from the
[Music]
crowd we
before anyone notices before the unarmed
guard can make a move the thieves strike
forcing everyone to the
[Music]
ground then they slice Impression
Sunrise from its
[Music]
frame October 27th 1985 a daring
daylight heist in Francis Marmot Museum
[Music]
in just 5 minutes the thieves make
history and a clean getaway
[Music]
they make off with nine masterpieces
into the bustling streets of
Paris art thieves but no art lovers the
gang escapes with up to $20 million
worth of paintings they hastily slash
Masterworks such as renoir's bather
sitting on a rock from their
frames but none can rival the loss of
Claude Mona's Impression
Sunrise the theft rocks France a
National Treasure stolen before their
[Music]
eyes at the French newspaper lemond
investigative reporter Emanuel daru
the theft of Impression Sunrise by Monae
is
[Music]
inconceivable the loss of one of the
most famous paintings of the 19th
century and even of all
time so it really shocked the world
because nobody thought that picture
would be
stolen what kind of criminals would do
this who would dare commit an armed Roby
in a
museum M bzi former head of Fran's art
theft
Squad it was like violating something
sacred nobody expected a robbery of this
kind in
[Music]
France investigators scour motan hoping
to find some trace of evidence but the
the thieves didn't even leave a
fingerprint authorities find
nothing the investigators had no real
evidence except for witness
testimony but no one got a good look at
the masked
men Witnesses describe the thieves as
European and the News only gets worse
never anticipating such a bold crime the
museum turned off its security system
during the
day no alarms no hard evidence and
seemingly no
hope and for the knifed masterpieces no
insurance the Mormon paintings are
absolutely
Priceless you can't put a price on
something that is considered a national
or worldwide artistic
treasure the director of the museum
makes a desperate appeal to the public
for
[Music]
help art experts know that impression
sunrise could be damaged by the humidity
when no respectable leads surface cops
tap the art community's Shady
underworld we contacts in the art world
where there are Specialists who hear a
lot of things who see a lot of things
but who don't necessarily tell the
police we used many of these contacts to
get secret
information police question art dealers
known for fencing stolen
paintings but none provides any
significant leads the investigation
stalls the senseless crime baffles
everyone
really most of the works of art that are
stolen are common objects of medium
quality that are easy to
resell and you can't resell Impression
[Music]
Sunrise authorities hope that such a
high-profile Caper can't stay under
cover for long what they're about to
discover is that the key to impress
Sunrise actually lies in the Land of the
Rising Sun in Japan 13 months after the
Maran Heist and half a world away a
Brazen daylight Heist goes down November
25th
1986 morning near the fashionable Ginza
shopping district of
Tokyo business as usual outside the
Mitsubishi Bank building as an armored
van arrives to deposit money
then out of nowhere asants attack the
unarmed
guards they steal over 300 million yen
or about2 million
[Music]
us and with no one to stop them the
robbers speed away into the busy Tokyo
[Music]
traffic a huge Hall of cash a clean
getaway it seems like the perfect crime
but interball is about to get involved
and prove
otherwise three bold and seemingly
unrelated crimes Rock two different
countries
first the midnight theft of five
paintings by Jean Baptist Koo from a
museum in the village of samura NOA in
France then during Gallery hours at the
marot tan Museum in
Paris thieves steal Nine Paintings
including a Priceless
Monae and now in Tokyo in broad daylight
robbers steal $2 million in Yen from an
armored
van this was a bold robbery being
executed right in front of a
bank tomofumi Yamamoto covered the story
for Japan's Asahi
weekly it was the biggest sum of money
stolen in Japanese
history everyone was
[Music]
shocked Tokyo one of the most congested
and one of the safest cities in the
world but even here safety isn't
100% the $2 million Heist sends Japanese
police into action
[Music]
inspector yorio Gata is the lead
detective of the first criminal
investigation section of the Japanese
police
the Tokyo Metro Police Department hit
the scene in minutes to pursue the
criminals within hours they' located the
getaway
vehicle in an underground parking garage
they find the abandoned
van and inside the van they find plenty
of
evidence including a pillowcase a
sheet
masks a large coat of a foreign
brand and a blanket with an address
label sewn in
the blanket came from a store that rents
bedding to people with unfurnished
Apartments among the 49 people who have
recently rented blankets they find a
promising
lead there were two French men who
rented blankets the leing company
normally would have check their
passports but this time they
didn't
H investigators also learned that a
foreigner recently exchanged a large sum
of money Franks for
Yen ,000 FR 1 million yet yes I need to
open a French restaurant I need to run
apartment passport yes the teller made a
copy of his
passport copy but police Det determine
it's a
[Music]
fake their search for Clues
continues and just 2 days later they get
another
break near the Tokyo Kawa Inari
Shrine in another parking
garage police discover part of the hall
the thieves Left
Behind 15 million y
about
$114,000 all in 1,000 yen
bills inspector uhi sukamoto head of the
fingerprints
group the amount of money they stole was
about 330 million yen that's a lot of
yen to carry
around I suspected that smaller bills
such as 1,000 yen bills were getting too
heavy Dr
[Music]
around sukamoto Department Begins the
laborious task of checking each bill for
fingerprints the department had recently
developed new methods to speed up the
process of fingerprint
detection they apply a liquid called
ninhydrin to the
bills which they place in inside a
book that they then wrap in
plastic a microwave creates the humidity
that develops the
prints if we don't do this it usually
takes two to three days for the
fingerprints to become visible with this
it only takes us one or two minutes to
get the
fingerprints even so it takes the team
10 days to pick their way through the
15,000 individual bills but it's time
well
spent we found seven fingerprints on the
new bills and 150 on the used
bills inspector sukamoto depends on the
recently installed fingerprint
database but a comparison against 7
million prints fails to find a single
[Music]
match the other evidence suggests that
the felons are
foreign he needs a larger database and
he knows where to find
one police contact
[Music]
interpole interpol's International print
database headqu Ed in Leon France
gathers the Fingerprints of felons in
all its member
countries the organization comes through
Interpol identifies the
suspects Philipe
jaman Richard
looy YF
kimun and tifra
Nordin the four friends from the obier
area in Paris
all have prior criminal records for auto
theft and drug
trafficking acting on interpol's info
Japanese police learned that the men
have rented an apartment in
Tokyo but now they're
missing inspector yorio Gata discovers
they left Japan on the same day as the
Mitsubishi
Heist according to the immigration
record they went to
Singapore since we knew that the
criminals were foreigners we started an
international
[Music]
manh the Japanese police pursuit of the
Brazen Mitsubishi bank robbers will take
them down an unexpected
path at stake is far more than the
recovery of 330 million stolen yen
[Music]
on the other side of the world French
authorities keep working to crack two
cases of art
theft months of searching have turned up
no leads on the missing Coro paintings
or on the painting stolen in the Marmot
tan
Heist as the months drag on with no
apparent
progress M balestrazzi and her
colleagues at Fran's art theft Squad
[Music]
fear that the paintings will be
destroyed through rough
handling then 7 months after the
Mitsubishi cash
Heist balastra gets a glimmer of hope
information that the Coro paintings are
being held for
ransom in
Japan the Japanese connection came up
for the first time when a middleman
contacted the French
Embassy he proposed to negotiate the
return of the
paintings in exchange for a payment from
the French
government the news that the paintings
showed up in Japan doesn't surprise Bell
arrazi in the 1980s Japanese high
rollers drove up the prices in the world
Art Market
newly minted millionaires craved lavish
pieces that flaunted their
wealth and some didn't ask too many
questions about where they came
from but art theft wasn't the only
property
crime in October 1987 Tokyo Police ramp
up a Manhunt for shinichi fujika wanted
for a $200,000 fur
Heist police want Fuji Kuma for
information they know he served time in
the same French prison as Philip jaman
the suspected ring lader of the
Mitsubishi Heist and they wonder if the
two men became partners in
crime police discover that Fuji Kuma
works at a local restaurant and they
issue a warrant for his arrest
[Music]
caught off guard and with no place to
run he's taken into
custody police have no idea they now
hold a crucial link to an international
crime spree that's baffled authorities
for 3
[Music]
years
Tokyo thieves pull off the biggest
robbery in the country
history but around the Clockwork by the
Japanese police identify the men
responsible Philip
jaman Richard
looy YF
kimun and tifra
[Music]
Nordin just hours after the $2 million
Caper the suspects split up and flee the
country
country now they could be
anywhere authorities don't know it yet
but the mitubishi job is just the latest
part of a bigger scheme that began in
France 3 years
[Music]
earlier September
1987 Japanese police arrest shinichi
fuuma wanted for stealing first worth
over
$200,000 Fuji Kuma has a long criminal
record and ties to the Japanese
Mafia or
Yakuza he confesses to
police giving up information on the
Mitsubishi
[Music]
Heist his taale begins at lante prison
in France where he was serving 5 years
for smuggling
heroin his gift for languages allowed
him to commit crimes all over the
[Music]
world Fuji Kuma met Philip jaman at
lante interpole determines that jaman
ran a stolen car network with a group of
smalltime hoods who grew up together in
the obv area of
[Music]
Paris apparently according to Fuji Kuma
jaman had graduated to grander crimes
again jaman called on his old prison
buddy to help sell off five Coro
paintings he stole from the museum at
simiron
nois check it out it's all
[Music]
good fujika notices paint flaking off
the master
pieces what were these two jaman and his
men had rolled them up incorrectly
during the
[Music]
theft but he agrees to fence them for
whatever he can
get fujika tells police that the plans
to move the art didn't go smoothly he
could only manage to sell three of the
five paintings he goes back to jaman and
says he can't find buyers for the stolen
art is however would not accept
failure he insisted fujika had to make
good on the deal even if it meant paying
for the paintings
himself just give me a couple days I see
what I can do all right
so fuuma tells police that's when he
decided to rob the first
store to get the money for jaman he sold
the stolen
furs and gave most of the money to
jaman the transaction bore some
unintended
[Music]
consequences when Shaman saw how easily
fujika pulled off the robbery he decided
to pull off a robbery in Japan
himself he gathered laroy kimun and
nordine and hit the Mitsubishi
Bank grabbing 330 million yen or $2
million us
Fuji Kuma swore to police that he acted
only as an adviser to the bank heist not
a
participant but police have no reason to
believe
him instead they get a warrant and
search his house looking for a link to
the Mitsubishi Heist or the Coro
Caper instead they find something even
better
a catalog from the marmatan museum in
Paris where the second art Heist took
place in the catalog were paintings
circled in
red a check with Interpol confirmed
suspicions these were the same paintings
stolen from the
marmatan the evidence t Fuji Kuma Jan
and the Gang to France's second major
unsolved art
theft Interpol issues red notices
putting the Suspects on their most
wanted
list their names and photos are sent to
police in every country that belongs to
the
organization they also notify M bastra
and Fran's art theft
Squad the good news keeps
coming authorities locate all five cor
paintings according to Japan's good
faith law if a person holds on to stolen
property for more than 2 years without
its owner claiming it the owner then
becomes the new rightful
[Music]
owner po and balestrazzi head to Japan
to try to bring the paintings
home but they need help from interpole
to navigate this delicate
situation Hello both countries belong to
interpole but they have conflicting
laws thefts of artwork Crossing
International borders present a unique
problem John mhof former director of
interpol's us
office what may be a crime in the victim
country may not be a crime in the
destination country Interpol can only
enforce Crimes by Constitution that are
a crime in both of the member
[Music]
countries French authorities ask
Interpol to pave the way for the French
to come to Tokyo to
negotiate in turn the French agree to
respect the Japanese laws as they travel
east to attempt to recover the
[Music]
paintings the suspects have ties to the
Japanese Mafia or Yakuza so a mob hit
isn't out of the
question the Japanese police fear for
the safety of their French
Associates we never felt that we were in
danger but our Japanese colleagues
thought that we
were so they did everything they could
to protect us and they were always with
us brilliantly balancing legality with
diplomacy belli spends the next 3 weeks
tirelessly negotiating the return of the
paintings madzi negotiated like an
expert convincing our Japanese
colleagues that we needed the paintings
back in France
[Music]
bastra successfully recovers four of the
five
paintings but an art gallery owner
simply refuses to return the last one
citing the Japanese good faith law which
made it his legal property
[Music]
now but bellzi won't give
up she appeals to his personal honor
assuring him that his surrender of the
painting will receive heroic
recognition at a press conference the
gallery owner handed over the
painting and a ceremonial property
title allowing him to save
face the Coro paintings returned home to
the museum in seur NOA
[Music]
the culprits have escaped Justice and a
greater crime remains
unsolved Impression Sunrise and the
other eight paintings from Maran are
still missing French authorities
believed that Philip Shaman and his
accompli have everything to do with the
theft at marmatan this gang of hardened
criminals make a career out of
Disappearing and when they do turn up
it's usually too late
one of the suspects Richard looy is shot
dead outside his Paris apartment
apparently a professional
hit in this case many people ended up
dead many of the people we questioned
were killed they died in violent ways
assassinated it's up to Interpol to
track down the criminals to save the
paintings and maybe a few
lives interpole tracks a ruthless gang
of Thieves implicated in at least three
major robberies they've made off with
millions of Yen from an armored van in
Tokyo five paintings from one Museum in
France and Nine Paintings from the
marmatan museum including Monae's
Masterpiece Impression Sunrise
one suspect Richard Leroy has been
murdered but three remain at
large Paris France
1988 3 years after the marmatan Caper
French authorities make a breakthrough
in the
investigation one of the suspects Tira
nordine applies for a new French
passport but in a routine check with the
police authorities find his name in
interpol's red
notices when he tries to pick up the new
passport French police arrest
him later an informant tells police that
the ring leader Philip jaman is hiding
out in
Mexico Interpol takes it from
there working closely with Mexican
police when a member country of
interpole learns that a fugitive is
residing in that country they have two
challenges John mhof former head of
Interpol in the United
States one is this indeed the person
who's wanted by the other country and
two are the crimes for which this person
is wanted uh something for which we can
extradite Interpol supports that
transaction by making sure that
information is delivered in a timely
[Music]
fashion agents take the suspect into
custody France and Mexico share no
formal extradition agreement but
Interpol helps return jaman to
France M Bel rzi of France's art theft
squad has waited a long time for this
moment she hopes Shaman will be the key
to finding Impression Sunrise and the
other eight paintings from the marmatan
museum missing now for almost 3
years but jaman won't
talk Basi turns to Interpol
again they help her obtain phone records
from from
Tokyo she discovers the phone number of
a man who had once tried to broker a
deal for Impression
Sunrise this man placed a number of
calls to someone in the town of
ptoo in Corsa an island off the coast of
France the man is Pierre Kiti a
part-time
bartender balastras receives a tip he
might have his hands on the marmatan
paintings she travels to Corsica to
chase the
lead she once again uses her powers of
persuasion and
[Music]
tenacity and kti leads her to the
paintings stolen from the marmatan
including
Impression
Sunrise after 5 years of tireless effort
she
prevails the paintings leave Corsica and
finally return to
Paris but the investigation frustrates
authorities who can't find enough
evidence to charge the suspects with
stealing the paintings
[Music]
we never had real evidence simply a
series of elements of evidence some
witness testimony that put together made
us believe they were the
perpetrators Philip jaman and tifra
Nordin stand trial for the Mitsubishi
robbery but their fingerprints on the
stolen money are the only evidence of
their connection to the
crime so the men get convicted merely
for receiving stolen
goods their sentence is time
served to this day YF kimon has not been
found but for M bellzi what really
matters is the return of the missing
masterpieces
[Music]
she would soon join the organization
that helped her find the
paintings in 2002 she joins interpol's
executive
committee art theft remains a worldwide
problem fueling terrorism and organized
crime right now interpol's database
lists 11,000 stolen paintings
worldwide many will never be recovered
but interpole will never stop
looking Cancun Mexico tourists from all
over the world travel to the resort City
to take in its exotic
nightlife but in April of
1993 that nighlife turns
deadly rapael ailar wardo is one of
Mexico's most dangerous drug lords a man
with many
enemies while he finishes his dinner
with his wife one of his enemies
prepares to settle an old
[Music]
score outside Georgian canul and her
husband Barry rosenbom are enjoying a
second honeymoon in
Cancun Georgian is 2 months pregnant and
the American couple wanted to take the
trip before the Bab baby was
[Music]
born wardo pushes his wife to safety and
grabs Georgian as a shield
[Music]
the drug lord is
dead but he is not the only
victim Barry and goran's dream vacation
ends in a nightmare
[Music]
by the time paramedics arrive it is too
late the scene yields scant
evidence the witnesses draw a blank
there is little to help police find The
Man Behind the brutal murder of a drug
lord and an American
vacationer police fear this is only the
beginning when you have a gangling style
slaying probably not going to be the
only hit John mhof the former head of
the United States interpole office you
need to figure out why it occurred you
need to figure out the motivation first
of all to solve the crime and second of
all so that you can understand the
Dynamics of who might be
next the Mexican police begin their
search to find Raphael wo's
killer wardo is the Kingpin of one of
the country's largest and most dangerous
drug smuggling organizations the harez
cartel it is one of three cartels that
control drug traffic through
Mexico the Tiana cartel controls the
western part of the country the gulf
cartel operates in the East and the
Warez cartel holds the
center wo's death makes his entire
cartel vulnerable and ignites A
desperate power struggle among his
lieutenants
US Customs agent John Hensley now you
have a headless organization and you
have a vacuum and they have been in that
business long enough to know what
happens when you have a vacuum they're
going to be at War they're going to be
threatened they're going to be
killed that very night the bloody battle
for control rages as the streets of
Mexico's border towns erupt in
violence 8 Warz cartel drug lieutenants
loyal to a heart
are hunted down and
killed this bloody power grab is for
incredibly high
stakes the Warz cartel makes billions in
profits by delivering Colombian cocaine
into the
US Warez is on the northern border of
Mexico it's separated from El Paso Texas
by the Rio Grand River
it's one of the largest border crossings
into the
US Customs officers and police on both
sides of the Border struggle to stem the
tithe of illegal drugs in Warz the
police use high-tech surveillance
systems to try and gain the
advantage at the Crossing into El Paso
US Customs agents are engaged in a
constant
search their target the billions of
dollars in Colombian cocaine the Warez
cartel moves across the border each
year Interpol assists on both sides of
the Border but the head of Mexican
Interpol Pon Edmonson recognizes it is a
losing
battle no law enforcement in the world
has succeeded in the combat the only we
are in
war against the drug dealers we're
trying to control the flow of drugs the
seash shures we're doing are less than
20% of the drugs that go
through now a killing has given the
cartel a new
leader Mexican police and US Customs
must find out who is in
control informants on the street tell
them that the man who ordered the hit on
wardo is one of his drug lieutenants
Amato Kio
Fuentes the Warz cartel like many
businesses has two divisions Rafael
wardo a sort of head of sales made the
business deals and the Kio Fuentes
oversaw the operations but the two men
don't get
along Kio Fuentes doesn't enjoy sharing
power armad Kio Fuentes was a
undereducated uh very aggressive guy US
Customs agent John Hensley has fought
the War on Drugs for 30
years the key to success for a man like
armato Kio Fuentes was
ruthlessness Kio Fuentes joined the
cartel as a teenager and over the years
police have become familiar with the
aftermath of his quick and bloody rise
to
power but despite Kio fent's reputation
authorities can never pin any of the
murders on
him looking for something to link him to
the wardo headit police put his Mansions
under 24 hour power
[Music]
surveillance with wardo out of the way
Coro Fuentes continues to make his money
by familiar
means driving Colombian cocaine into the
us from the notorious medine
Cartel Cartel operatives smuggle most of
the drugs in the hollow dashboards and
hidden compartments of specially
modified cars
[Music]
the Colombians pay Korea FES
handsomely but to increase their own
profits they propose a change in their
payment
plan the Colombians made a decision it
would be
cheaper if they just paid the whatz
cartel in dope and so they started
paying them in hundreds and hundreds of
kilos of cocaine in terms of actual cash
they saw it as a good deal but the
Colombians miscount calculated badly
what they did was create and make armado
CIO Fuentes a cocaine drug lord now Coro
fentis is moving his own cocaine and
competing directly with the Colombian
medine cartel for the same Market the
Colombians try to stop him but Kio
Fuentes takes a bold stand they were
going to cut off their cocaine supplies
unless they stopped competing and the
answer back was then you're moving no
drugs through through Mexico we will
shut you down shut the door because we
control this we also control the street
organizations in the United States and
they're not going to buy from you
anymore they're going to buy from
us in preparation for this move Kio
Fuentes reaches out to competing
cartels he no longer needs the medine
cartel they know it and give in koreo
fent's
demands they become his partners
with this Victory Korea Fuentes takes
over cocaine trafficking into most of
the United States the Warz cartel we're
actually doing business from start to
finish from the fields in Colombia the
labs down there all the way to the
streets of Los Angeles California and
New York
City but the huge money grab by the
cartel creates chaos in the Mexican
border towns
and in some cases corrupt authorities
stand by and watch it
happen in fact the corruption fuels Kio
fent's
organization the police in Mexico have
historically receive very low pay and uh
don't come from a professional
background and have accepted the fact
that they can accept
bribes and so as you accept bribes for a
traffic ticket why not not take bribes
on a drug
transaction Kio Fuentes and his gang
make anyone who can help them a simple
and terrifying offer bullets or pesos
either they take his money or
die Kel fent's bribes reach the highest
levels of
government some officials receiving as
much as 1.5 million do a
month despite the threat some officers
Won't Back Down in November of 1994
police Commander Jose ruio rubalcaba
leaves his wife Maria and heads to
work ruio rubalcaba is a reformer who is
cleaning up the police department by
firing dozens of corrupt
officers he refuses to bow to the drug
Lord's
threats but today he is picked up by
members of the
[Music]
cartel Days Later Jose is found murdered
in the trunk of a
car a knife punctured his
lungs in the law enforcement Community
when someone goes down no matter what
their nationality affects all of us
despite the danger and almost routine
corruption many police refus to bow to
Coro fent's threats there's a lot of
risk there's a lot of threats
but I mean it's a job and you have to do
it everybody is afraid in
life if you step back you're a
coward I go up
front one step
more that's
it in August of 1993 US Customs and the
Mexican police are alerted of a large
scale drug
bust Mexican naval officers routinely
searching cargo vessels uncover 9 tons
of cocaine worth over $20
million it is Bound for the United
States according to Interpol agent Pon
Edmonson this kind of bust makes the
cartels
vulnerable if they lose a load of
cocaine sometimes they won't have the
money to pay the
provider they can get the Colombians
knocking at their door Say Hey I want my
money so those things are good for law
enforcement word of the bust soon
travels to koreo fent's Colombian
Partners they are Furious to lose so
much product and blame Kel
Fuentes they assume he has lost control
of his
organization Colombian Justice takes its
usual form they decide to take him
out on November 24th
1993 at a restaurant in Mexico City the
Colombians make their
[Music]
move a move that will have an unint Ed
and terrifying
effect in Mexico on November 24th 1993
Mexican police struggle to make sense of
a horrifying crime
scene Colombian Hitmen have attempted to
kill drug kingpin Amad Kio Fuentes and
his
wife the Assassins miss their Mark and
pay for it with their
lives Kio Fuentes and his wife Escape
journalist Jorge Mendes covers the drug
cartels
extensively it was a miracle K escap his
bodyguards risk his own life and rushed
and his wife out of the restaurant
pushed him into an armored truck and
save their lives The Bodyguard who saves
Korea Fuentes is reportedly aides Ramon
Mahana a policeman turned gang member
short in stature he is nicknamed El
Metro or the meter
he had some power and influence because
he stayed in the shadows he was never
considered one of the important players
in the
cartel that is all about to
change Kio Fuentes rewards El Metro for
his outsized bravery by making him his
right-hand
man he also gives him control of the
profitable Cancun
territory all the drug traffic in the
popular Resort town is now under the
control of El
Metro El Metro known as Kio fent's
enforcer has a reputation of conducting
business with extreme
violence investigators intensify their
efforts to find
him US Customs gets a tip that Al Metro
may be using retail trucks to smuggle
drugs out of the country and bring money
in but finding them is a daunting task
each year 16 million Vehicles cross into
the US from Warz
alone but the diligence of US Customs
and Mexican police starts to pay
off US Customs agent John Hensley one
case in particular El Paso inspector
seized over $10 million hidden in a
frozen food truck that hurt him a
lot with each success Customs gathered
intelligence and increases the
pressure we put a hard press on the
Mexican drug
cartels we did share uh intelligence and
information with Juan Migel Pon and the
people from
interpole they were beginning to focus
as to where they could attack the war is
cartel most
effectively the intelligence begins to
hurt the
cartel interpole and Mexican narcotics
agents confiscate huge amounts of drugs
weapons and
cash the Mexicans began doing sweeps and
seizing property that's when uh the Warz
cartel really started to uh
Shake as the intense pressure on the
border cuts into the cartel's profits
Kio Fuentes and El Metro shift their
tactics he starts shipping by air
once again good intelligence pays
off US Customs learns of the drug Lord's
new strategy and follows his every
move his drug shipments are easy prey
for us custom spotter
planes when the planes land in the
US Customs agents are often there to
greet
them yet the more than5 billion in
seizures authorities make each year
barely makes a DE in the
trade US cities are still flooded with
drugs from the Warz
cartel armado cordio fontus became one
of the biggest drug organizations uh
that we've ever known
about undaunted by the small plane busts
Kio Fuentes uses another
[Music]
way they were buying large planes which
were not like scrap material there were
very old plane from cargo airlines or
regular Fleet Airlines nobody had uh
statistics and so it was very easy for
them to buy they put $50,000 and just
they needed one more
flight and they crashed it at any Beach
or desert but there was 10 tons of
cocaine or 12 tons of cocaine
the drug lord catches US Customs off
guard was not something we were
initially looking for they flew the same
routes
altitudes and uh essentially tried to
look like a commercial
aircraft the large aircraft create
enormous profits for the
cartel Amato Kio Fuentes has become an
extremely wealthy and powerful
man want has had the benefits that is
skew from that kind of power women
Mansions uh jet planes nice clothes all
the trappings of a drug
lord he owned 54 Mansions all over the
country of
Mexico but his enormous wealth brings
enormous
problems Kio Fuentes is having trouble
hiding the mountains of cash he is
earning as
profit this might be the weakness in the
organization investigators have been
searching for
koreo Fuentes needs help laundering his
money US Customs and interpole devise a
way to help the drug lord with his
problem interpole in Mexico began
working with us to identify the assets
to seize them to identify people to
arrest and
prosecute they set up their own money
laundering front and launch a sting
called operation caun
their only interest is in one
client the what is cartel it's always
looking for a new source to launder
their money and so we began moving
millions and millions of their dollars
through the banking
system operation Casablanca is a success
the DEA files indictments and begins
investigations of Korea fent's Financial
activities in the United
States Interpol agent Pony Edmonson sees
the investigation start to hurt the
cartel if you cut the money laundering
they're ruined because they don't have
the engine the motor that makes the
organization investigators begin to
tighten the news they have enough to
arrest the targets of the cartel
indictments The Mexican government with
Juan Miguel Pon as the point person
began arresting those people that there
were warrants outstanding on in
Mexico investigators are finally closing
in on koreo
Fuentes the heat was too high on Fuentes
for him to survive in his present
role but the heat has an unintended
effect there were just too many
newspaper headlines too many US
indictments he was definitely going to
get out of the way before he got caught
when investigators finally believe they
are getting close to koreo
Fuentes he
disappears a man with his money can hide
anywhere in the
world only one agency has the means to
find
him
interpole when police begin pressuring
Mexican drug lord Amad Kio Fuentes he
disappears us custom
Mexican police and Interpol work all
their contacts to find him but
surveillance by Mexican police is not
working drugs rumors indicate the drug
lord may even have undergone plastic
surgery problem is Mexican interpol's
Pon Edmonson knows the reason Kio
Fuentes is on the Run he was scared as
hell that we would detain him Kel felt
he's always in hiding he never sleeps
two nights in the same
place when he has such a large
organization tipping him off when he has
corrupt cups giving him
information when he can buy false Forge
documents passports of different
nationality he was so afraid so afraid
that he took a lot of
precautions nothing investigators are
doing works
police at his home have not seen the
drug lord since he drove
off now that he is gone Mexican police
make a bold
move they seize kop Point's property in
Mexico some 54 manions in
all they hope one of these homes will
hold a clue to his current
Hideout police come up empty but head of
Mexico's interpole office Pon Edmonson
notices is a curious similarity they
were in different places with different
decorations but they had pool tables why
they had pool
tables because am Caro Fuentes had to be
hidden most of his time and he liked to
play
pool pool is not popular in
Mexico the drug Lord's passion for the
game might just lead Pon to his hideout
and also investigators noticed several
of koreo fent's most trusted cartel
members have also vanished however we
have reason to believe Pon Edmonson
fears he's fled the
country quite easy for a person like him
he could offer half a million dollars
for some
passports so I mean corruption is
anywhere when it's at those prices
Kio Fuentes might be able to buy
anonymity but he can't buy
luck in England 5,000 m from Pon
edmonson's office a strange break occurs
in the
case a woman at afternoon tea at the
Ritz hotel in London has $80,000 in
traveler checks
stolen come come here outraged she goes
to the
police Scotland Yard offers to
investigate the thief doesn't get
far a few days later when he has an
accomplice try to cash the checks they
find
him but it seems suspicious this woman
would be carrying
$80,000 to check out her story the
British detective turns to Interpol for
help he contacts Pon Edmonson at the
Mexican interpole office
when I heard the name of the lady I knew
was the mother of the principal
Lieutenant of Amad
Kio her son Eduardo Gonzalez karte has
worked with Kio Fuentes for
years Pon Edmonson wants to take a
closer look at the stolen Travelers
checks Scotland Yard faxes over the
information interpo agent Pon Edmonson
wastes no time in running down the check
numbers those numbers of checks were
bought wholesale 2 and A2 million dollar
and they were in the hands of the waters
cartel investigators learn they were
purchased from a currency exchange
office in Mexico
City interpole finally has a tool they
can use to track the cartel
members I was seeing the breadcrumbs of
where they were going because every
check that was traded I was
informed so they went London Paris
Barcelona
Moscow Jerusalem and most were spent in
Chile and Argentina so I went to Chile
in
Argentina in Argentina Edmonson notices
that a one runell has been using the
checks to buy real
estate ronell would provide the drug
lord with the perfect
cover Pon Edmonson travels to Argentina
to talk with the real estate company
where the Man known as runell cashed
several of the
checks the company provides no
information it seems even in South
America koreo Fuentes is buying people's
allegiance to capture koreo Fuentes
investigators are going to need a
break Ponce Edmonson plays a hunt
I said this is going to be quite
difficult if we don't have something
what was that something pool
tables I knew that Amad couldn't live
without a pool
table when agents in Mexico seiz Kio
fent's Mansions they notice they all
have pool
tables Pon Edmonson believes he may be
able to to use koreo fen's unusual hobby
to trip him up he visits an importer who
handles pool tables and plays aruse I
said I love to play pool and I would
like to know if those people that bought
those pool tables if uh it's a bar or
something where I could go play pool no
no no no no they were for four private
homes and precisely was one of your
compatriots a Mexican that bought oh
then would be Lov to play why don't you
give me the
address edmonson's plan works he gets
the
addresses convinced Kio Fuentes must be
behind the purchases Edmonson closes
in the residences are locked up
tight Kel quentes has
vanished Pon Edmonson broadens the
search two other South American
countries John mhof
yeah the war is cartel is huge I mean
they've got more money uh they've got
more people they've got more connections
than any local law enforcement agency
either in any one country's law
enforcement agencies but when you bring
Interpol into the equation uh now you
have this Force multiplier you can match
fire with
fire the interpole offices in Mexico
City buenos Ares and Santiago Chile
compare their information
the office in Argentina gets a tip Kio
Fuentes is at a hotel in Buenos
Ares Pon Edmonson finally has him in his
sights but the drug lord has gotten away
many times
before Mexican Interpol agents track
Warez drug lord Amad Kio f to a hotel in
Argentina but when they raid the
hotel K Fuentes is long
gone somebody tipped him and he
left we always one step
behind but that was good because that's
what got him so nervous and make him
commit
mistakes while staying at the hotel Kio
Fuentes had made a series of calls to
the same town in
Argentina now Interpol agents believe
they have finally found his
Hideout but before interpol's Pon
Edmonson gets to him again he goes on
the
Run pressure from the authorities forces
Coro FES once more to flee the
country Interpol agents learn he escapes
from buenos arees and goes to
Cuba from there he sneaks back into
[Music]
Mexico July
1997 Amato Kio quentes plans to
disappear
permanently in a hospital in Mexico he
undergoes plastic surgery on his
face but something goes horribly wrong
during the
procedure under the effects of
anesthesia Kio Fuentes stops
breathing and the medical team cannot
revive
him Korea Fuentes dies on the operating
table when Pon Edmonson learns of the
accident he rushes to the hospital to
try and identify the infamous criminal's
body Mexican officials and US narcotics
authorities want to confirm that the
operating table victim is in fact Kio
Fuentes the media thought that he was so
resourceful and he had so much money
that he could have put another corpse so
people will think he was dead and then
he would get out of the pressure so it
was very important to produce enough
evidence to show that he was who he was
and that was
DNA they take tissue and blood samples
for testing
this microscopic evidence holds the key
to the man's
identity a DNA lab in the US confirms
the dead man in the hospital is aad Kio
Fuentes the murderer and drug kingpin
who took over the cartel by killing his
predecessor an innocent tourist and
countless others is
dead at autopsy authorities discover the
Kingpin a cocaine user himself had the
drug in his system when he
died he also had traces of a cative
dormicum which Coro Fuentes often used
to help him sleep after a cocaine
binge when the anesthetic combined with
the dormicum it created a fatal
cocktail the ruthless drug lord had been
struck down by
drugs interpole has finally found amatoo
FAS but his death only signals the
beginning of a new bloody drug war
it will turn the entire country into a
battlefield it's like a wolf pack when
you when you knock the lead wolf down
they don't stop running they somebody
else emerges and the Wolf Pack just
keeps on
going generally that is the most
ruthless of the lieutenants waiting in
the
wings Mexican newspapers print photos of
Coro fent's corpse in the operating room
and news of his demise rocks the Mexican
underworld
outside Mexico City a woman makes a
gruesome
Discovery along a rural road she finds a
barrel inside is a mutilated
corpse police identify the unfortunate
man as the doctor who performed the
plastic surgery on Kio Fuentes it's the
ultimate signal of disrespect to an
individual so they sent a signal to
others that this is the way we're going
to leave you if you uh if you cross us
police have evidence to suspect that The
Man Behind the retribution killings is
alides El Metro
Mahana El Metro saw an opportunity to uh
take over and when he operated as
ruthlessly as as he did the rest backed
down and he was able to uh take over the
organization through force and
intimidation he was trying to rebuild
the organization in his own mold which
is a lot cruder a more
violent he operated differently through
threat and intimidation so as he had his
own sources of information and
identified local Mexican law enforcement
investigations at the regional and state
and local level his tactic was to find
out what he could and then kill
him a lot of local police officers died
at the hands of El
Metro El Metro has to be brought
down in 1998 Jose Luis vasconcelos from
the Mexican Attorney General's office
joins the
fight all the forces of the state were
mobilized and exerted strong pressure
over the
organization Mexican police are now
joined by the Mexican Army and US
military
forces they begin targeting El Metro
aggressively
to do this job you must have strong
convictions and overcome all your
fears these drug lords must be St we
must Prevail and we can if we don't give
in
fear El Metro has shown himself to be a
difficult
Target he makes certain he is always
well
protected El Metro operated in two two
modes one was to intimidate ter and kill
and the other was he still had to have
sources of intelligence and some cover
especially uh governmental cover if he
could find it reportedly his bribes go
as high as governor of the Mexican state
of quintanaroo Mario
viena what Mar and no did was offer
protection drug traff their airplanes
and bring in their boats he made certain
they could move freely throughout the
territory of
and even their money in the hotels of
without fear of
beinged police intensify surveillance of
his operation but they believe El Metro
is quick to strike
[Music]
back on June 2nd 1998 Juan Martinez the
leader of the investigation into Al
Metro's activities is met by two police
officers
within minutes he realizes he is in
terrible
danger the men posing as officers take
him to a secret location where he is
reportedly tortured for hours
[Music]
at the same time eletro allegedly sends
his men to the investigation Leader's
office to reportedly steal evidence
linking him to Governor
viua the next morning they leave the
investigator in an empty field to
die he is discovered in
time and he's taken to a local hospital
this assault on a police officer
infuriates Mexican
police they start an intense Crackdown
on all aspects of el Metro's
operation the new pressure creates
problems for El Metro from within the
cartel El Metro was being very rough he
was bringing Scandal and a lot of low
enfor men to that area precisely what
the cartel didn't
want Mexican authorities offer a reward
of more than
$400,000 for information that will lead
to his
arrest when his friends and enemies turn
against him for all of the bad publicity
he is generating he decides to make a
break and abandon
Cancun before he leaves he undergos
plastic surgery just as Kio Fuentes did
but unlike his former boss he stays away
from the drugs before he goes under the
knife the operation is a
success but interpole and Pon Edmonson
are not about to let the cartel's
suspected leader get away clean their
only problem is that now they don't know
what he looks
like as investigators close in on the
Warez cartel they they make a series of
high-profile arrests but the suspected
head of the cartel drug Smuggler El
Metro Mahana Still Remains at
large after undergoing plastic surgery
to rebuild his face he
vanishes in his wake he leaves a
political
Scandal US Customs and the Mexican
police begin an intense Crackdown on
corruption within the Mexican
Government drug traffickers must have
complicity with police and government
officials the cartel could only operate
with the corruption and protection
facilitated by the
authorities before the drug trafficking
could stop the corruption had to be
stopped in Mexico City Jose vasconcelos
oversees a task force working to clean
up the
corruption it is a daunting task the
Warez cartel has friends in very high
places the corruption is rampant
throughout the military the police and
it even reaches to some State's
Governor's
manions using wirs investigators prove
Mario Vena governor of the state of
quintanar Ru is on the payroll of the
Warez
cartel the corruption reached Mexico's
drugs are General gites reoo he was
accused of betraying highlevel
informants who paid with their
lives reportedly a deputy general for
Narcotics was paid by the cartel 1 .5
million a
month but the suspected leader of the
cartel El Metro still eludes police
agents believed El Metro was operating
out of Cancun and perhaps with his new
look that he has
returned agents descend on the resort
City but they aren't certain what El
Metro looks like
now he could be anywhere
police work every lead they have trying
to gain any information on the
whereabouts of the suspected drug
lord but getting good information is
difficult each time they think they get
close El Metro has moved
on either their information is no good
or he is tipped
off well police on the street are trying
to track him
down agents start to study phone records
of some of his known
associates they notice an interesting
pattern they are all making a series of
phone calls to a number in a small town
in the remote region of
Tabasco the town is called via
erosa it is the town where El Metro was
born Mexican police put together a team
to go to Tabasco and Shadow El Metro's
every move Pon Edmonson learns that
because of el Metro's violent reputation
the cartel lieutenants have forced him
out that group of lieutenants says look
you made a lot of Scandal you created a
lot of problems for
us we owe you because you saved the life
of our leader in the past so we won't
kill you just think you're dead you have
enough
money but you have no power no
anything you can do any more oper raon
just enjoy your money and go 10,000
miles away from here in Tabasco near the
town of VR amosa the agents pick up El
Metro's Trail they wait for the perfect
time to Spring a trap they get a break
from some unlikely sources we don't
really know but we have the suspicion
that maybe he tried to do something
because there were a lot of anonymous
calls saying where he was going to be in
Tabasco maybe it was a rival
cartel perhaps El Metro angered his
competition but Pon Edmonson and
Interpol use this information to find
the perfect time to
strike El Metro makes an appointment to
make a phone call from a public
phone this is the opportunity interpole
has been waiting
for the officers wait for El Metro to
approach the
phone they check to make certain he is
alone when they are convinced it is safe
they move
in on June 12th 2001 interpole gets
their
man El Metro is arrested and brought
back to Mexico City to stand trial for
drug trafficking but a Mexican Court
releases him citing a lack of evidence
he is then rearrested in March of 2002
and charged again with drug
trafficking he is awaiting trial at the
lapalma federal Maximum Security Prison
outside of Mexico
City years after the arrest of El
Metro billions of dollars of illegal
drugs still cross the Mexican border to
the US each year
so for interpole and law enforcement
agencies in Mexico and the
US the battle continues to try and slow
this deadly
traffic Egypt's magnificent monuments
attract millions of Visitors awed by the
mysteries of its ancient
civilization the story of Egypt
stretches back thousands of years
vestages of her history still stand
above and buried
below Priceless
[Music]
Treasures hundreds of tombs some known
many still undiscovered hold Antiquities
in darkness
[Music]
but tomb robbers and Smugglers ensure
that wealthy collectors around the globe
get what they
want at a
price I come from a long tradition of
Smugglers uh I'm a Devon man and they've
been smuggling for a thousand years and
I'm proud to follow
on Jonathan tokley Perry ex- British
army officer
restorer of Antiquities and to many
unabashed
scoundrel I just regret there aren't
more Smugglers around I perhaps should
start a school not everyone shares The
Smuggler Cavalier attitude to steal an
Arta you steal civilization you are
stealing
history zah General Secretary of the
Egyptian Supreme Council of Antiquities
this monuments do not only belong to
Egypt but belong to the people all over
the world this is the Heritage and the
culture of everyone these monuments May
belong to everyone but HOAs and his
colleagues are determined to keep them
on Egyptian
soil it is not easy when there is lots
to steal and with rampid corruption many
ways to steal it
[Music]
an estimated 70% of Egypt's Antiquities
remain
buried Egyptian law prohibits any newly
discovered items from being traded or
even possessed by Egyptian
citizens in fact if an Egyptian finds an
artifact on his land he must hand it
over to the
government who can in turn seize the
land but in a country where the average
income is less than $2,000 us a year
many people turn to the black market to
keep their property and to make a little
cash if a builder uncovers ancient
artifacts or ruins they must contact the
government who can then shut down their
building
site many reberry the find and seal it
in concrete to protect their building
project
but even with the promise of some easy
cash most Egyptians are content to
protect their property by quietly
hanging on to their
[Music]
finds that is until the Gulf War broke
out in
1991 1991 was a splended year because of
the Gulf
War everybody in Egypt was frightened
they were ConEd Sadam would trundle his
t-72s all the way down to SII and that
Sudan would blow the High Dam and Egypt
would be flooded and everybody wanted
hard currency and that meant that
everybody was trying to sell their
Antiquities tokle Perry and his partner
in Egypt alif farag schemed to take
advantage of the
panic our big break came with the head
Amon hot at the third known as A3
this was brought to us by a building
contractor from asud who said that under
ordinary circumstances because of the
laws he would simply have concreted in
but because this was a Gulf War he was
prepared to to sell
it they quickly settle on a price a
fraction of a3's real
worth the building contractor wanted
$6,000 which would what it was costing
him to evacuate his entire family to
Morocco for the duration of the war and
keep them
safe A3 is a huge score for tole
Perry a piece that can establish him as
a major player in the Antiquities market
right
back it is the break he has dreamed of
for years trained at the best of English
schools tokle Perry graduated from
Cambridge in 1974 with a degree
ironically enough in moral science
but after graduation in Rome he fell in
love with all things
ancient I touched them and you have a a
FR a wonderful feeling coming from
ancient things and once I touched them I
knew I wanted to work with him and to do
that I trained as a restorer and then
eventually um I became a
Smuggler Now The Smuggler has to get his
prize out of
Egypt got to imagine that I was leaving
on the first
flight the country was still under
military alert There Were Soldiers
[Music]
everywhere in his room at the Windsor
Hotel in
Ciro the art restorer uses his skills to
conceal his
crime to prepare something for transport
my first task was to coat it in a
conservation plastic called
b72 this protects it
completely if he can make the ancient
Pharaoh's bust look like a replica
bought it a bizaar he'll slip through
customs on top of the plastic I simply
put on a plaster nose plaster chin
plaster eye then I would gild it with
gold
leaf and then on top I could paint the
decoration the the lines of the eyes the
stripes of the hair and so
[Applause]
on at the airport a customs officer
inspects the
piece these fellows have a nasty habit
of producing car keys and scratching the
surface and I knew that if they scratch
the surface over the face and cheeks
where there was just the plastic and the
gilding they'd find Stone
and that would have buggered me that
would have that would have been the
end so when he produced his key I had to
persuade him to go down and scratch at
the bottom where I put a false base on
specifically for him to scratch okay do
you have it works
perfectly and tole Perry makes off with
a Priceless relic of ancient
Egypt one he believes is better
preserved by collectors in the
west getting A3 through Customs was was
probably the most difficult thing I ever
had to do I have never ever done
anything to harm an Antiquity I have
saved things from Egypt that would be
concreted
in this English guy he's saying
something that doesn't make any sense
you cannot steal and say I'm stealing
this monuments because this country do
not know the value of
it the next day tole Perry is back on
the ground in England ready to restore
A3 when he dips the bust in a mild
acetone bath the gilding paint and
plaster dissolve revealing the treasure
beneath when I brought out
A3 it was clear I had an object that was
wonderful absolutely wonderful it was
way above anything I'd ever had before
and I had no idea how to sell it and no
idea what it was worth and and it was
clear I needed to
contact a dealer in that bracket to find
that dealer tokle Perry looks to New
York Frederick Schulz is considered one
of New York's most prestigious art and
Antiquities
dealers when he hears about A3 he agrees
to help sell
it but he and tokle Perry face a huge
obstacle Egyptian law forbids the sale
of Antiquities Unearthed after
1983 all reputable dealers avoid items
that don't come from a recognized
collection one of the things to do was
to create an old collection that is to
give the idea that these objects had
come from uh a collection that had
suddenly come to
light so tokle Perry invents the Thomas
Al coock
collection Alcock was a relative of
tokle Perry a civil engineer who worked
on several continents in the
1920s it's a game that's played
everybody understands it and I very much
doubt if anybody is ever deceived by old
collections in the Antiquities
World using Victorian era Paper Tags
tokle Perry makes fake collection labels
for A3 and several other pieces
he dabs the labels with tea bags then
bakes them to give them the yellowed and
brittle appearance of
age next the expert restores the pieces
using techniques popular in the 1920s
including the use of a certain type of
shellac the rest is up to Frederick
Schulz in New
York if a piece has been published it
becomes comes easier to sell because it
has an academic description an academic
backing Schulz meets with a renowned
egyptologist if he can get her to
publish A3 it will validate the work as
a piece from a legitimate collection and
make it appear as if it were obtained
legally the woman buys schulz's story
about A3 and the alcok
collection one of the things Fred was
able to do was to get A3 inserted into
the Cleveland exhibition of all the
works of Aman hotep thei which was
published in a in a in a in a very very
swish catalog there was a photograph of
A3 in there as the only one of its class
in in a private collection so that meant
that Fred could refer to the catalog
when he was offering it to a customer it
obviously made life very much easier for
him
after the Cadillac's publication Schultz
sells the head of Aman hotep III to a
South African dealer the price 1.2
million
us Jonathan togle Perry makes the
biggest score of his career pulling off
what he believes is the Perfect
Crime but no crime is ever
perfect Smuggler Jonathan toley Perry
and dealer Frederick Schulz sell a
stolen Egyptian artifact known as A3 for
over a million
doar it's The Smuggler's first big
score now with the million-dollar sale
of A3 he becomes a serious player in the
Antiquities trading
game one minute I was a servant at the
tables of the Rich and then suddenly I
was the Golden Goose I was a much more
important person I was what they call a
source
and it was a very Charming transition I
must say I enjoyed
it he has operated under police radar
for years by maintaining a small
operation and watching every detail but
as The Smuggler's business grows that
becomes impossible he has to bring in
conspirators London England May 1994
a man walks into the British
Museum and asks for an appraisal of a
remarkable
find it's only very rarely that somebody
comes in with a piece which is quite
interesting and
dramatic to museum egyptologist Jeffrey
Spencer the items brought in are very
dramatic
indeed Museum expert recognized the
manuscripts as the so-called demoic
papyri discovered by a colleague 25
years earlier items that should be
locked and under guard at the Egyptian
necropolis of
Sakara when they appeared in London it
was fairly evident that they could not
possibly be here legally they had to be
brought out of Egypt
secretly we then got in touch with
Scotland Yard outs and antique Squad and
they were very interested in the case
particularly of course as we were still
holding the demotic papyri we still had
the stolen goods um and we knew the name
and address of the person who brought
them
in at Scotland Yard Sergeant Richard
Ellis head of the art and Antiquity
Squad investigates Andrew May the man
who brought in the
papyri May lives in
Barnstable in Devon County
[Music]
and the Barnstable police are already
looking into one of May's
neighbors weeks earlier employees of a
local bank noticed this
man Mark Perry had been making regular
deposits of 500 cash every
Monday thinking Perry could be a drug
trafficker laundering money the bank
employees contacted Deon Cornwall
police hello detective Constable Steven
Toms is on the possible drug
case um we conducted some inquiries
initially onto him and couldn't work out
where the money was coming it wasn't
large amounts it was only hundreds of P
but it was a regular thing on a Monday
morning the Devon Cornwall police placed
Perry under surveillance further checks
reveal Perry has been flying back and
forth to Egypt on weekends
well that was not a usual route for drug
trafficking into the UK so we were at a
bit of a loss really as to what was
going
on so where the money was coming from
was a
mystery the mystery unravels with the
call about the demoic
papyri mark Perry's neighbor Andrew May
rents a workshop to Jonathan toley Perry
who police know only as a restorer of
Antiquities who recently reported the
theft of a valuable Egyptian
[Music]
statue hello St Constable Toms puts the
pieces
together we knew that Andrew owned a
large man of house Mark Perry was living
in a cottage
opposite and Jonathan toy Perry rented
his Workshop from Andrew May and all
this is within 100 yards of each other
and we just felt it was too much of a
coincidence with stolen artifacts travel
to Egypt and unexplained cash coming
together in the quiet English Town
Police believe they have uncovered a
smuggling ring likely centered around
tole
Perry it was not a huge leap to uh come
to the conclusion that that Jonathan toy
Perry was the likely source of the
papyrus
Constable Toms assists the Metropolitan
Police in executing
searches the team secures
warrants Sergeant Ellis invites
egyptologist Jeffrey Spencer to join
them then we're not experts in this
field we couldn't tell whether it was a
replica or the real thing but Jeffrey
could the officers find no incriminating
evidence at either May's or Perry's
homes
they searched Jonathan togle Perry's
office and in the filing cabinet rumine
through were all sort of travel
documents to Egypt and there were also
documentation in relation to business
transactions selling uh Egyptian pieces
to America it was decided that the whole
content of the filing cabinet would be
seized and we would investigate each
document so far no Antiquities come back
next they check the restorer's
workshop photographs
here and the first thing that Drew my
eye was several plastic boxes full of
photographs these photographs were of a
man later identified to me as toy parry
and others in Egypt at the tombs uh
inside the tombs chainsaws in hand uh
desecration of tombs
my photos were actually
irrelevant all they showed was that I
was buying pieces in Egypt and
disguising them and smuggling them
out but investigators see it differently
this was his own record uh I've often
likened this to finding bank robbers who
photographed themselves going across the
street to hit the bank uh and then
coming out with the proceeds this
bollocks I was an amateur doing
something very traditional doing
something that my forbears have always
been doing I was oldfashioned I was the
last of the old
type the photos are only the
beginning investigators finally hit pay
dirt and calling Jeffrey
Spencer and well his eyes nearly popped
out of his head and there were pieces of
antiquity lying around which meant
absolutely nothing to us U but meant a
lot to Jeffrey
there was a head of a queen um in a gry
stone quite
[Music]
sizable there were a number of small
Antiquities we found in his Workshop
molds which had been made from genuine
objects which he was then producing
replicas
of the team confiscates everything as
potential
evidence police then move on to tokle
parry's current home 20 M away in it
Isle inside no one is
home someone please to turn off that
BL but investigators quickly discover
more
Antiquities they appear to be genuine
and illegal that we found some more
crucial pieces as regards
evidence two large pieces of stone
relief carving from an Egyptian tomb of
the Old
Kingdom and they were found in Black
wooden
boxes the reliefs are typical of those
found on the false doors of
tombs at the exact moment investigators
are searching tole Perry's home the
suspect is on his way home from the
airport he's just flown in from
Egypt for Jonathan tokley Perry his
timing couldn't be any
worse on June 28th 1994 as British
police search The Cottage of antiquity
Smuggler Jonathan toley Perry their
suspect walks right into the room I'm on
my 65th trip I got back to my Cottage
and and the door was open for me by the
police and I thought I'd been
burgled tole Perry remains calm
convinced he is safe from
prosecution as he speaks with Sergeant
Richard
Ellis he had a suitcase with him and I
got him to open the suitcase and inside
it he had a folder which purported to
show that he was engaged with the
Egyptian government on conservation work
on the tombs that he was some form of
consultant we have in there also inside
the case is a freshly Unearthed
artifact now this was a genuine
Antiquity it bore a Greek stamp and it
is something which Tok Parry admitted to
me then was an object he had
found when he'd been taken to an unknown
tomb in Egypt the day before since he
often buys Goods directly from officials
in Egypt tokle Perry convinces himself
it's perfectly fine to export stolen
Treasures in Egypt I was breaking the
law but I kept very good company Egypt
is a military regime the power lies with
the generals and if the generals are all
selling me Antiquities one has to ask
where the law is this International
Mafia from England from Egypt from
America all of them had the freedom to
do what they want had the freedom to
still states such corruption and the
huge number of Antiquities has made it
difficult for Egypt to stop the
smuggling
trade the Egyptian government hasn't
always been effective in protecting the
Antiquities of the
tombs former director of the US Interpol
office John mhof that a lot of artifacts
have never been properly cataloged the
first people ever to see them were grave
robbers they've moved on to the World
Market without the knowledge of the
Egyptian government so there is this
cache of valuable Antiquities that's out
there in the world that's never been
properly
documented to stem the tide of ancient
stolen artifacts the Egyptians pass an
anti- theft law in
1983 anyone removing items discovered
after 1983 is stealing and can be
prosecuted yet tole Perry is now in
England where there is no no law
expressly prohibiting ownership of
Antiquities I wasn't guilty I hadn't
broken British law quite simply but
British law does prohibit what's called
dishonest handling of goods stolen from
anywhere this man is trying to find an
excuse this is bad and I think this can
prove that this man is a
criminal sir the mass of material that
we had discovered in that one
day uh was certainly sufficient to give
me grounds to believe that tole Perry
was involved in a dishonest handling of
cultural property and for that I
arrested him toley Perry remains defiant
thank you sir I stoutly maintain that
morally I was doing the correct
thing after being charged he makes bail
and is released
[Music]
now authorities turn to the other
suspects they interrogate Mark Perry
about the regular cash deposits he has
been
[Music]
making facing jail time he turns on the
others he admits that tokle Perry pays
him to make the weekend trips to Egypt
and either bring Antiquities back
himself or ship them back to
England tole Perry always buys his plane
ticket and pays him 500 lb per trip back
police know Jonathan tokley Perry is
running a vast smuggling
operation now they must find out exactly
what that operation
entails the photos tell the
story I made about 50 trips by myself
our secret store room was just bulging
especially after the Gulf War we had
bought so much that I literally could
not bring it all back myself that's when
he began using couriers expanding the
operation in a Sprint for
profit Andrew May and Mark Perry were my
couriers Andre May was the first one and
Mark Perry was was the second
one I should never have trusted anybody
because that was what started the the
undoing I regret that I didn't just
carry on doing what I was doing and
doing it apparently successfully if I
hadn't trusted these other people I
wouldn't have got caught up in all the
fuori to break the ring and prove the
dishonest handling charges police need
help at the British museum egyptologist
Jeffrey Spencer tries to identify the
confiscated items and determine their
origin
he starts with the stone reliefs found
under the bed and notes they resemble
reliefs documented in the Tomb of
HPA if he can prove they are an exact
match police can make their case against
the
Smugglers but Spencer runs into
difficulty when looking at the detail
they didn't quite match exactly and that
was a problem
toally Parry must have changed the
appearance of those slams so that we
wouldn't be able to do what I was trying
to do Trace them back to their Source
the tomb of head of
car to confirm the suspected touchup
Museum scientists run a chemical
analysis of the pigments used on the
hieroglyphics the results confirm their
suspicions the hieroglyphs have been
changed and in some cases
toy Parry had made a mistake in that
he'd used modern pigment which was not
known to the ancient
Egyptians but police need to prove the
seized Antiquities recently came from
Egypt to make the case that tokle Parry
handled stolen goods and broke British
law to be legal collectors of Egyptian
artifacts discovered before 1983 must
register them with the
government Interpol helps monitor these
legal collections by coordinating a
worldwide database of stolen
[Music]
artwork but this doesn't help Scotland
Yard nail tole Perry no one has reported
any stolen items from the tomb of
HPA it's possible that no one has
noticed the theft yet but more likely
the Smugglers bribed guards and other
officials to keep the theft
quiet looking for evidence of Egyptian
contacts the art and Antiquity Squad
reviews the recovered files and
photos they know tokle Perry and his two
carriers are involved completely
different in the files they find
references to an Egyptian contact known
only as Ali Ellis asks Egyptian
authorities for help including General
Aziz mlod of the Egyptian Antiquities
unit it was frustrating because all we
knew was that this rign consisted of
three British men and one Egyptian man
called Ali only that one name Ali it
doesn't give police much to go on in a
country of 60
million but this one man could hold the
key to crack open the smuggling ring and
nail Jonathan tole
Parry with the help of interpole police
in Egypt and England team up to
dismantle an Antiquity smuggling rign
headed by Jonathan toley Perry
zahi HOAs of the Egyptian Supreme
Council of
Antiquities we are going to capture all
of them to prove to the world that Egypt
is caring for the first time about the
protection of our monuments but it's not
going to be easy their only lead in
Egypt is a single name
Ali but General aiz mlod has a
plan I started contacting my secret
sources the only way we could bust this
ring was to use informant we had to
place them between the artifacts and the
thieves the informants give them a
name they identify Ali as Ali farag he
comes from a family of suspected
Smugglers but has kept clean himself so
far
the team feels as if they're getting
closer Scotland Yard detective Sergeant
Richard Ellis flies to Egypt to follow
up on the stone reliefs found under tole
Perry's
bed there Ellis joins a multinational
team of police and together they
traveled to the tomb of atepa at the
massive necropolis of
Sakara this tomb is one of the most
precious in Egypt while hpco wasn't a
pharaoh he oversaw the hairdress
addressers to the
Pharaohs an intimate to a royal family
thousands of years
ago it was the first time we had ever
seen a tomb for someone from the general
public this was an extremely rare tomb
that's why the thieves would pay the
dealers and the Smugglers extraordinary
amounts of money to steal from his tomb
there is no evidence of theft and the
doors remain sealed
but once inside their worst fears are
[Music]
realized not only are the reliefs from
the false doors gone nearly everything
else is
too the tomb's guards confessed they
allowed robbers inside in December 1991
[Music]
the investigators believe this must be
how Jonathan tokle Perry got the stone
release they found under his
bed the damage and destruction
contradict tokle Perry's conservationist
claims if you look at the tomb of hetep
car in Egypt after it was looted and you
witnessed the destruction that was
caused as a result of tole Parry wishing
to sell
pieces of the false door you will then
see the destruction that people like
tole Parry cause to the ancient
monuments of this
world and this is the real criminal
activity in order to satisfy the desire
for profit and get a few pieces to sell
destroy an entire fif tomb which has
been there for thousands of years
after emptying the tomb the robbers
resealed the doors and
disappeared to solidify the case against
the robbers and Smugglers Egyptian
Antiquities police look for evidence of
other
thefts they reopen other tombs in Sakara
and find that the looters have been busy
throughout the ancient site
Jonathan tokley Perry may be out on bail
but he is still running his smuggling
operation he gets word that EST stelli a
stone burial slab inscribed with a
tribute to the god of the underworld
Osiris is available on the black
market it is a piece to Perry cannot
pass
[Music]
up he contacts American dealer Frederick
schz they then promis to wire a series
of payments totaling nearly
$100,000 to various
middlemen the sellers blindfold the
Ring's Egyptian contact Ali farag and
drive him through the streets of Cairo
to the place where they secretly hold
the
Stell there farog makes the deal
finalizes payment and arranges shipping
in a container headed to a storage unit
in
Switzerland we paid
$40,000 for that container of which
$3,500 were for the shipping and the
rest
$36,000 went to the Antiquities pleased
for a single sheet of
paper that's how smuggling Works in
Egypt now it's semi-industrial it gives
you an idea of the international nature
of this market and how easy really it is
if you've got the right sort of
connection
to move even large objects because this
is a very piece very big piece of
stone Scotland Yard is trying to keep
toly Parry on British soil by taking
away his
passport but tokle Parry is nothing if
not resourceful he quickly hatches a
scheme to get it back and he made an
application based on uh the death of the
mother of a former fiance who happened
to live in Switzerland and he wished to
have his passport so he could travel to
Switzerland to support the former fiance
and attend the mother's
funeral Ellis calls on Interpol for help
through the international police force
Swiss police check the story and
discover no such death took
place Ellis persuades the courts to deny
the phony
request but tokle Perry doesn't stop
there he substitutes a different family
name secures a passport
then heads to
Switzerland when he gets to his Geneva
storage unit tokle Perry finds a
surprise the Osiris Stelly he and
Frederick Schulz paid
for is not
there after a year-long painstaking
investigation spanning three continents
authorities are ready to
strike the name for their plan operation
bull
rush we were able to piece together um a
complete ring of people involved in the
illicit traffic of of this cultural
property from
Egypt in March 1995 they execute
simultaneous raids in London and in
Cairo operation bullrush nabs five
British art dealers a British police
officer more than two dozen Antiquities
inspectors and several of tokle Perry's
Egyptian accompli including his main
contact Ali
farag Jonathan toley Perry has already
been arrested and charged he remains
free on bond while he awaits his
trial I was so happy and I said this
will encourage me to recover our stolen
artifacts because this cooperation
proved that this is the beginning it was
really the beginning and the beginning
that we will start all of us to
communicate with each other to cooperate
to protect this monuments tokley Perry's
trial begins in early February 1997 in
London but on February 27th tole Perry
mysteriously fails to show up in
court he has checked himself into the
mental health ward of a Deon
Hospital see seeing how the trial has
been going he has his own
plans my Barrister said they will
convict you because they desperately
want a scapegoat to close the market but
we can have it acquitted
immediately he said you'll have to go to
prison but we'll get you out very very
quickly and the whole thing will be
clear but I wasn't prepared to tolerate
that that night the Antiquity Smuggler
chooses a dram itic Escape
Route mixing a concoction of powdered
Hemlock a common method of suicide in
ancient times he drinks it
down I'd had the Queen's commission I'd
served my
country I was very very proud proud of
what I was doing and I wasn't prepared
to be
disgraced with that the daring Smuggler
lies down to die
[Music]
while on bail during his trial notorious
Smuggler Jonathan tokley Perry checks
himself into a mental ward in Devon
England drinks Hemlock and awaits his
death Devon Cornwall police track him
down Mr to Parry wake up Mr Parry wake
up Mr Parry
Mr totally
par Mr per wake
up you're right see up Mr
[Music]
Perry they arrive only minutes after he
drinks the
poison he's still
alive thinking he is merely groggy from
sleep and sedatives they take him
in I was quietly dying contentedly in
hospital knowing that I would be dead
within an hour and a
half and then the police arrived and
said they had to change my bail
conditions so they dragged me down to
the police
station and by the time they got me back
I was um halfway into coma and they took
me into intensive care they had no idea
what was going on Hemlock kills by
slowly paralyzing the body's muscles
when the lungs stop the person suffed
ades at this point to Perry is still
conscious I counted 52 I went black and
I thought well that's that I didn't know
about the the thing called the incubator
which is a tube they put down inside the
lungs to keep the lungs working they
didn't know what was going on but they
kept me alive with this incubator for 3
hours until the hemlock wore
off and I woke up again
not a happy
boy with tokley Perry brought back from
the dead and vowing not to attempt to
take his life again a new trial
begins on June 18th
1997 Jonathan tole Perry is found guilty
of secondary dishonest handling and
sentenced to 6 years in
prison in Egypt he is tried In Absentia
along with 11 codefendants all are found
guilty and senten to 15 years hard labor
which tokle Perry will have to serve if
he ever returns to Egypt I should only
have had 18 months 2 years
sentence but they gave me 6 years to set
an
example Egyptian authorities welcomed
the example and hoped to make it a rule
this is important this is a part of our
heritage but there's a final missing
piece of the
puzzle the Osiris Deli that tole
believed was shipped to
Switzerland this is a piece that came
out uh through the farag Brothers Route
into Switzerland and from there it was
sold um to uh a dealer who subsequently
sold it into France and from France it
made its way to New York New York FBI
agents trace the piece along its winding
path their Pursuit pays off when they
finally find the Stelly at the Fifth
Avenue Apartment of a wealthy
collector he bought it for more than
$200,000 but he never checked on its
legality the agents confiscate the
stelli to take it home to
Egypt sir in 2002 Frederick Schultz the
smuggling Rings New York arm is found
guilty of smuggling stolen
property a federal judge sentences him
to 33 months in prison despite the
relatively light sentences for Schulz
and toley Perry the case has a profound
effect on the world's Antiquities Market
smuggling Antiquities is no longer
tolerated at least in
England as a result of my trial the
London
Market took fright and largely
transferred to Paris and
Switzerland there is effectively no
London market now London had been the
center of the world of the Antiquity of
the world for 200 years it's now gone to
Paris and Switzerland now out of prison
Jonathan tokle Perry maintains that he
broke no laws and is merely carrying on
a proud tradition of bringing beautiful
artifacts out of Egypt for preservation
in the West 100 years ago I would be
kned for what I was doing these days
political correctness is taking a dim
view of it but I'm still doing the right
thing and I wouldn't have done it if I
wasn't convinced of
that I think if Jonathan tole Perry is
hoping to see his name in the honors
missed uh it'll be a very long
wait most of the looted Antiquities have
been returned to their rightful
place I will tell you the first time
when I went and I hold an artifact that
was a stolen and I took
it in my hand like this as if I'm
holding a child my child that he was
away for a long time I'm bringing him
back home many stolen pieces including
the elusive Osiris stelli are part of a
new exhibit at the Cairo
Museum the theme the return of stolen
art Holly Maddox was the oldest child in
a family of
seven she grew up in a middle class home
in the town of Tyler
Texas Holly was very much a the
caretaker big sister kind of surrogate
mom in a lot of ways Holly's sister Meg
Wakeman Holly had a special closeness
with all of us between Holly and I I
think there was a mentorship and there
was a very true big sister kind of a
guide Holly loved the Arts and in 1965
she left her family behind to study at
in Mark College outside of
Philadelphia it is the early
1970s and Philadelphia is a Haven for
artists and freethinkers of all
types most notably among them is Ira
Einhorn a man who Rose to prominence
during the 60s peace movement he taught
at the University of
Pennsylvania a self-styled guru of the
decade of peace and love Einhorn
preaches nonviolence campaigns against
the war and lectures to packed
houses he even claims to have created
Philadelphia's first Earth Day in 1970 a
claim widely disputed
today he's a respected intellectual
revered by the
faithful I think he and although Holly
doesn't know it at first he's very very
dangerous after she graduates from
college meets the man who calls himself
the
Unicorn once he met her he told his
friends he was determined to have her
and quickly won her
over their relationship continues for 5
years but Holly decides it is time for
her to move
on on September 10th
1977 she tells Einhorn she's through
with him why what's wrong why is what I
say that's why but Einhorn is not
through with
Holly where you going to
go no you're not going
no over 1250 Mi away in Texas Holly's
family becomes
concerned didn't she has always kept in
touch with them writing letters
frequently but her last few letters
troubled her
family her letters about Ira were were
always Ira did this and Ira did that and
I think there was something underlying
it that made us Wonder but what about
you wasn't their relationship it was all
about
iron it went into the Dynamics of
possession and I don't believe she knew
at that point how much of a possession
that she was to him and we didn't really
know how to tell her you need to get out
and you need to run as fast as you can
away from this
man but then Holly's letters stop
completely they haven't heard from her
in weeks and she's missed family
birthdays which she never
does here was the early middle of
October no birthday cards for the three
birthdays in October don't trust him
there were no phone calls no letters or
anything birthday here she so this was
very odd we knew that something must
have
happened I'm going Soom tried to call
her the last number they have for Holly
is at Ira Ein
horns hello Mrs Maddox asks if he's seen
Holly recently I just thought maybe you
might know where she is and he said no
he
hadn't and he elaborated just a little
bit and said she went to the store a
couple Sundays ago and and I got out of
the shower and then she was gone she
just never came back and mom thought he
sounded awfully nonchalant but then she
also realized well they had just broken
up so maybe he's you know upset about
that right he hasn't
heard the family reports Holly missing
with Philadelphia police but to the
Philly PD nothing about her
disappearance seems
unusual the police were unable to to do
any type of a search really because
there wasn't any evidence that there was
some crime committed during that Fallen
winter I think we were all holding on to
whatever hope we had that well maybe she
really does just want some time to
herself maybe we're going to hear from
her by Christmas you know maybe
something like
that yet the holiday season arrives with
no word from
Holly in Texas December 1977
Holly's family hires retired FBI special
agent Bob Stevens to investigate her
disappearance to meet you in the private
investigator first wants to know about
Holly she excelled in high school and
college always doing the right thing but
she has always cheed I know a lot of
people characterize Holly as an
All-American Girl and that's still not
quite doing her justice even though she
was so pretty and she was the
cheerleader and and salute atorian and
all of that she kind of went beyond all
of those things she didn't just stay in
a
category she certainly had an aura about
her she had a power that was within that
she had a gentleness and kindness and
goodness the family tells Stevens about
Einhorn the breakups and the subsequent
disappearance a particular card
[Music]
for Holly's sister told Steven about a
school trip to England in
1977 Holly was there on vacation with
Einhorn leave him no matter where they
went in this person's house where they
were staying Ira kept tagging along and
beffy and Holly couldn't have any
private time together and finally Holly
said leave us
alone later when she could talk Holly
told her sister of einhorn's possessive
actions and that he cheated on her with
a number of women you
okay although she was worried what he
would do when she left she was
determined to go Holly already had a
place to stay but it wasn't going to
come open until I believe October 1st so
that was kind of the last we knew we
were waiting for information around
October 1st about what her new phone and
address and contact information would
be it's hard to imagine a famous peace
activist would hurt his girlfriend but
Bob Stevens has to check
he travels to Philadelphia and teams up
with former FBI agent Philly private
investigator TJ
Felding they want to question
Einhorn he is the last person known to
have seen Holly can I help you Mr
Einhorn casually reiterates that Holly
went out around September 10th and never
came back she's not
[Music]
here he appears un phased by the
investigators ago seen why sorry without
his permission or a warrant they can't
enter the
apartment but they can interview
neighbors Felding tracks down two
students who have lived beneath
Einhorn how long been like that for
months the story they tell them is more
ominous in late September
1977 one student recalls hearing loud
thumps and a single scream coming from
einhorn's
apartment Weeks Later the students
noticed a foul odor and a brown fluid
coming from the
ceiling they did their best to get rid
of it scrubbing over and over with
bleach the smell reminded their friends
of a
[Music]
morg the building's landlord tells the
pi the area above is a closet in Ein
horts apartment and that he had tried to
find whatever was causing the smell but
Einhorn refused to let him into his
apartment saying he had important papers
to
protect it all seemed odd to the
landlord but this was Ira Einhorn so he
didn't force the
issue Felding takes the case to
Philadelphia Police homicide detective
Michael ch would know you're as a
missing person the investigation when I
read it was like an Alfred Hitchcock
story there was
suspense there was sex there was
violence and in my opinion there was
murder Chitwood believes Einhorn killed
Holly in the apartment but suspicion
based on a private investigation is not
enough for an arrest especially with
such a high-profile
suspect my job was to reinw everybody
and develop a enough probable cause to
optain a search warrant to go search uh
Ira einhorn's apartment the warrant
application has to be perfect he was a
big deal at Penn he was a big deal at
Harvard he was associated with the Abby
Hoffman's and Jerry Rubin of the world
amidst the political turmoil of the late
'70s false accusation ations against a
leader of the peace movement would
trigger a terrible backlash against the
cops Chitwood compiles witness
statements about the
stain floor plans of the
apartments bank records that show over
$20,000 untouched in Holly's account
since that
September everything suggests she was
killed then and held at one time in
einhorn's
closet but to prove it Chitwood must get
in that apartment and to that
closet March 28th
1979 the search warrant has been
signed investigators hope to find hairs
or traces of
blood 18 months after Holly vanished her
family hopes for
resolution and they are now finally
going to go in and get some answers find
out what happened to Holly
and I think after this long period of
time in a way we knew we were going to
be sensing some relief depart right but
we also knew we were going to be sensing
probably the devastation of
loss Chitwood heads straight for the
closet directly above the stain in the
apartment
below but the door is
padlocked and Einhorn claims there's no
key
is it fine I got a crowbar from the
evidence technician and instead of
breaking the lock I took the hasp off so
where the screws were screwed in I took
that off so that the lock was still
intact and I opened the
door inside the storage closet Chitwood
finds a trunk a suitcase a woman's purse
and notices the faint smell of
[Music]
Decay inside there there were various
pieces of identification of Holly mtic
social security card library card
driver's license uh all types of
property that uh women usually carry in
their
bag the suitcase is Holly's 2o by now
detective Chitwood is sure what he will
find inside the
trunk and I had been homicide detective
for a lot of years and I've seen dead
bodies and I've seen decomposed bodies
this was decomposition this was a dead
body this was death got a key to this
they're only a few more clues away from
solving the mystery of what happened to
Holly madx but that's just the beginning
of the deep Mysteries that surround Ira
Einhorn the peace activist who's showing
a violent side that may have turned
deadly
[Music]
in March
1979 Philadelphia police searched the
apartment of Peace activist Ira Einhorn
after the mysterious disappearance of
his girlfriend Holly
Maddox inside a locked closet they find
a locked trunk Einhorn denies having
keys to both
locks as he did with the door detective
Michael Chitwood forces the hasp on the
trunk
it's packed full on top a Philadelphia
newspaper dated mid-september
1977 that was the date we were focusing
on that's the date she disappeared now
we got a steamer trunk we got this smell
of death and I figured
uhoh this is for real this is
it under more papers a mummified human
hand there's no doubt it's Holly it
almost looked like she was trying to
push
up in my
opinion um like she had been placed in
air and then you know had tried to get
out c tech one in the kitchen Chitwood
spots more possible
evidence a ring of
keys he's on his way the ones Einhorn
denied
having one key fit the pad lock to the
closet
door the other key fit the lock to the
steamer
trunk as far as I was concerned that was
that was the slam dunck that was the
home run because he had the night he had
the keys didn't know where they were in
spite of the overwhelming evidence
police are
shocked never in the million years did
we expect to go in there and find the
body just wasn't feasible just couldn't
happen this was IR horn he was a
garu uh he was a political person so he
was a a cultural icon deci answer
Philadelphia police charge the unicorn
with one count of
murder at autopsy the medical examiner
uses dental records to confirm the body
is Holly
madx yes please she was killed by at
least six severe blows to the head which
caused multiple
fractures the me notes that Holly might
have been still clinging to life when
placed in the Foot
Locker but still the police keep asking
why and why would Einhorn keep the
body forensic psychologist Dr Chris
Mandy believes it's all about control
what I think drove Ira to kill Holly
Maddox was her rejection and leaving him
it was one of these I'll be the one to
say when this relationship ends and How
It Ends and thus he took the control
back that she was trying to
take and then he added another step to
it not only are you not leaving me but
you're not leaving me even after you're
dead I'll show you
[Music]
a year and a half after Holly's
disappearance the madx family finally
gets an
answer now they must cope with the truth
I I couldn't think of how to
react when I found out in the manner
that Holly was killed and then stuffed
in a
trunk I mean just the idea someone being
Beat to Death and then stuffed in a
trunk was so beyond my
imagination Holly was dead I was never
going to see my older sister again she
was never going to be a physical part of
the family again and how on Earth are we
going to get through
this there is some consolation knowing
Holly's killer is in
custody good I'm glad they got him I'm
glad they he didn't
run I guess there's going to be a trial
now but it's not that simple the fiery
activist declares his innocence and
makes an astonishing claim that Holly's
murder was a CIA or KGB conspiracy to
frame him this was big big big news Lyn
Abraham was the Philadelphia district
attorney on the Einhorn case so he made
up the story and CIA conspiracy theories
always are big sellers so a lot of his
gullible friends uh believed it they
never even stopped for a minute to say
hohoh there's a dead body in this guy's
closet oo I better step back from this
no they just ran headlong into into
court ready to stand up for their guy
and say that he was really a wonderful
human
being Einhorn is represented by soon to
be US senator arand
Spectre at his arraignment a wave of
high-profile supporters including
investment bankers University professor
ERS even an Episcopalian Minister
testify on his
behalf the momentum somehow sways a
sympathetic judge who in a shocking move
releases Einhorn on
baale and when that happened and he got
out I said to the DA he's never going to
go to trial he's going to take off
there's no way in the world that this
guy is going to go to trial he's
gone because he had connections all over
the world pre-trial hero ings stretch
from months to
years then on January 14th 1981 Einhorn
fails to appear for a
hearing officers go to bring him in
police open up but he does not answer
his
door what do you know everybody was
everybody was sure exactly what would
happen did happen and it did he skipped
he
disappeared desperate to find him police
track Einhorn last movements they learn
he sold his car and Drew most of his
money from the bank leaving less than a
$10
balance none of Ein Horn's friends know
where he is
gone on the brink of going to trial for
murder einhorn's back in
control after Ira disappeared in January
of 81 um that of course was another
devastating loss
[Applause]
Einhorn has taken his new girlfriend
Anna Joe Williams with him and left the
country police worry that Einhorn is
drawing in another potential
victim Richard De benedetto chief of the
da office's fugitive unit now has the
case he checks into einhorn's
girlfriend a day or so after he fled the
girlfriend friend got a call from him
and her sister drove her to the airport
and she got on a plane now the sister
wasn't sure where she was going but she
thought it might have been either
England or
Ireland because Einhorn likely fled the
state and the country the FBI joins the
case and special agent Michael carbonel
partners with de
benedetto the FBI obtained a warrant for
his arrest it's called unlawful flight
to avoid prosecution and then he became
a federal fugitive which gave us the
authority to look for him anywhere in
the world to best do that the
Philadelphia police and the FBI need
interpole at the time John mhof was the
head of interpole us when I first came
to interpole Ira Einhorn was uh a
premier fugitive from the United States
that we wanted to see brought to Justice
he was a high priority because of the
heinousness of the crime he was somebody
who was in the public eye and uh uh
basically he was thumbing his nose at uh
at Society saying I can do as I'm
pleased because of who I
am right away Interpol issues a red
notice their highest priority fugitive
[Music]
alert the red notice told the world that
the United States on behalf of the
Philadelphia District Attorney's office
was looking for a murderer Ira
Einhorn US Department of Justice interpo
aison Mary Joe grotenrath
it gave them his picture his
fingerprints his physical description as
much as we knew about any habits of his
that might help the police to locate him
de benedetto and carbonel begin with
einhorn's collection of addresses
confiscated during the search of his
apartment second place is Philadelphia
the man hunt won't be easy the famous
fugitive has more than 350 contacts in
over 20 countries Boston uh fugitive
investigations are difficult enough
domestically they're twice as
complicated when you have to deal across
International borders so the officer
needs to have somebody that he can reach
out to and interpole puts his badge out
and makes it an international badge
for but even with interpol's help months
pass
Ira Einhorn is out there somewhere
seducing new supporters perhaps trolling
for new
victims Einhorn is really your
prototypical cult leader personality
he's Charming he's narcissistic he's
Psychopathic in that he's enjoying of
using people and those are the same
characteristics that guys like Jim Jones
David kores Charlie Manson they all have
those types of characteristics feel that
it's okay to use all these people and
they're very Adept at finding people to
use in a way iorn had his own little
cult going on Ira had a unique ability
to attract women I I can't explain
why and he always always always took up
with pretty women who had money he
wasn't interested in poor girls they
were not in his Galaxy of Interest he
always picked up with women who could
support him in this way The Fugitive
remains well funded protected and hidden
from
[Music]
police while the search for reinhorn
continues police delve into his past for
Clues they find ex-girlfriends who tell
of terrible abuse especially when they
try to leave
[Music]
him abusers like Einhorn do not
like
rejection and that moment of deflation
is a very dangerous moment because they
don't like to experience that feeling
they'd rather feel powerful and in
control the only way to restore that in
that moment is to become extremely
violent the Philadelphia police and the
FBI are desperate to catch Einhorn not
just to bring him to trial for Holly's
murder but because he might also kill
Anna Jo Williams if she drives to leave
him
once a person has crossed a threshold of
taking a human life there's nothing
holding him
back he's got no remorse there's nothing
to stop him from doing it the threat to
annael Williams is very real police fear
Ira Einhorn is not yet
finished after police discover the
mummified body of Holly MX in
Philadelphia Interpol and police around
the world search for her suspected
killer famous peace activist Ira Einhorn
who jumped
Bale Philadelphia police and the FBI
comb through evidence collected from
einhorn's
apartment some of the most disturbing
pieces of evidence are Holly's
journals her writing reveals details of
a terrifying and abusive relationship
last night I live in Conant Holly's
sister Mak
wakman the investigators found that the
relationship was more than just Rocky
emotionally they found that it was very
physically abusive and they could see
her withdrawing into the stance that
someone who's abused
takes we don't have
them police also scour einhorn's
journals and discover a chilling
penchant for violence
[Music]
he probably enjoyed writing about
it enjoyed reflecting upon it and
considered it important because he had
done it and thus worth
memorializing some entries seemed to
Muse over the possibility of murder
corroborating the belief that Einhorn
killed Holly to possess and control her
fully it was becoming clear that
einhorn's violence wasn't confined to
Hol interpoles John mhof
law enforcement uh was very intent on
bringing our IR horn to justice but
there was a great deal of concern that
uh he would kill again he quite clearly
uh had no compunction about what he had
done uh when he killed Holly Maddox and
for someone to kill so ruthlessly you
would think it's not a stretch that he
would do it
again Ein Horn's journals provide other
valuable
Clues fugitive tracker Richard De
benedetto
they were helpful in the sense that uh
he talked about different acquaintances
he had in other countries and and how he
had traveled to those countries over a
period of
years Einhorn seems particularly fond of
the UK and police believe he's in
England or
Ireland in fact they are
correct Einhorn and Anna Williams have
settled into Dublin renting an apartment
from Professor Dennis Weir and his
wife The Fugitive uses his real name
though he tells the we he is an American
writer Einhorn R goes out and only
occasionally talks to the we who grow
increasingly uneasy with their new
tenant like there were various things
about his manner which were a little bit
strange but they're very very hard to
Define I'm talking about a look a
mannerism just a way of speaking that
made one a little bit
uncomfortable the madx family worries
for anel
Williams I thought you know does she
know what's going on does she have any
idea that this guy had a dead body in
his closet for a year and a
half is she even thinking about the
possibility that he could kill her for
whatever reason he killed
Harley in April 1981 the we's plan a
trip to
Chicago and so we told Ira that we were
going to go to the
states and he became a little agitated
at that
point and he said to my wife don't talk
about me in the states or you'll get me
extradited um it was obviously a
provocative sort of thing to to to uh to
say and one which would inevitably
excite one's
curiosity once in the US Dennis we asks
around learns his tenant's true identity
and immediately goes to the Chicago FBI
a very fam fug when Philadelphia
authorities learn of the sighting their
relation is
shortlived unfortunately at the time
there was no extradition treaty between
us and the and the Irish government it's
maddening B luck they know where he is
but they can't arrest
him the Irish police are not going to
hold Mr reinhorn because they can't
extradite him back here and since he's
broken no laws in Republic of Ireland
they have really no right by their law
to hold him so we were
stuck Irish police can only escort the
we when they return home and help evict
Einhorn one of the world's most wanted
fugitives simply walks away he off he
went I I remember very well he scurried
off it was a strange feeling in the
Silence of the house uh wondering what
happens next although the we don't
realize it they haven't seen the last of
irra
Einhorn in Philadelphia carbonel and de
benedetto keep
working it was very frustrating when we
discovered that uh IR horn was in
Ireland because we we really couldn't do
anything but by the same token at least
we had uh known where he was so I mean
that was of some help now The Manhunt
has to sharpen its focus investigators
update the interpole red notice hoping
if Einhorn leaves Ireland someone will
spot him entering a country that will
extra it him
[Music]
with einhorn's Trail still hot they
immediately dispatch a detective to
Dublin to ask
questions he cannot act under any
Authority and if he runs into Einhorn he
can't arrest
him no one knows where Einhorn and
Williams are now but one neighbor says
she recently got a letter from
Williams the letter itself contains no
clues but the envelope is postmarked
from where
W investigators have tracked Einhorn
from Philadelphia to Dublin and now to
Wales tipped by a local inkeeper
Scotland Yard tracks Einhorn to a Welsh
Inn the inkeeper recognized dhorn from a
TV program but by the time the
authorities arrive The Fugitive is long
gone and he's left no
trace for Holly maddox's family
it's more terrible
news that was another devastating loss
because there was the potential to have
some type of closure within a reasonable
period of time now they must keep
waiting de benedetto vows not to let the
family down well my gut feeling was that
he was probably still around and some
somewhere in Ireland maybe out in the
countryside at this point or something
at the time Dennis Weir teaches physics
at Dublin's renowned Trinity College
in May of
1985 as he leaves the cafeteria he runs
into the
fugitive I had this direct eye to eye
confrontation with them it
was quite a mental exercise to decide
what to do especially when he simply
brushed straight past me without
acknowledging my presence and started to
walk up the
stairs the professor decides to follow
the suspected murderer no matter the
risk Einhorn refuses to
talk and I actually walked behind him
until we reached the front square of the
college that say exited the building and
and I stood there to watch him walk into
the
distance Professor Weir immediately
contacts Philadelphia authorities by
this time the US has an extradition
treaty with
Ireland detective Michael gorley of the
Irish police launches the offensive in a
matter of hours
but it's too
late by the time we locatedon Horn's
address in Dublin he was gone at that
stage he had
gone the apartment is one of a few
hideaways Einhorn has been
using inhorn has an endless supply of
money Interpol hopes neighbors can
help many know the American couple and
some saw them leave suddenly the day
before well actually I do I spoke to
about a dozen people Everyone of them
described him as a
charmer well read well versed and could
speak about any subject Under the Sun
they knew he hung out at the college and
at local bookshops but not today another
Miss but police won't give
up obviously it was very frustrating
again uh by the same time Tok and I was
somewhat optimistic because now we had
found them twice in a period of four or
five years you know maybe our chances
were getting better here
now but Einhorn remains
elusive then in late
1985 the break police had been waiting
for literally walks in their
door just 6 months after the last Dublin
sighting Anna Joe Williams suddenly
resurfaces in the United States
willing to
talk fugitive and murder suspect Ira
Einhorn is last seen in 1985 in Dublin
Ireland where he lived with his American
girlfriend 6 months later the girlfriend
returns to
Philadelphia alone and comes to the
police on the advice of her lawyer
[Music]
this might be it if Anna Jo Williams
will lead them to
Einhorn she dashes their hopes saying
she doesn't know where he is since they
separated in
Ireland he was becoming more violent
towards her and she got
scared luckily he decided she was a
nuisance to him and he threw her
[Music]
out but she offers police two solid
leads there is a woman one is that
Einhorn kept contact with a rich ays in
Canada the second lead is that Einhorn
spent a lot of time with one particular
friend a man named Nicholas Edwards who
owns a Dublin
bookstore right away Irish police set up
surveillance hoping Einhorn will
show yet again The Fugitive stays
underground interpol's Mary Joe gruten
wrath the reason it was hard to find
Einhorn was he was uh resourceful
himself he was an intelligent man he was
clever he took up with people who would
cover for him and he was on the
move but so are
police FBI special agent Michael
carbonel works with Royal Canadian
Mounted Police to track down the wealthy
arys mentioned by Ein 's girlfriend Mary
Joe
Williams she refused to be
interviewed and then they threatened her
with some legal
action she came to the United States and
provided a
statement the FBI and the Philadelphia
da interrogate the
arys At first she is elusive still
instinctively protective of
Einhorn one of the things that enables a
guy like Einhorn to exist a psychopathic
person who's going to use people is that
normal human beings want to
trust guy like irh horn will engage in
relationships with women seduce them
with what they want to he bring them in
and then gradually get them accustomed
to what the real agenda is which is to
control and
dominate facing prison time she agrees
to
talk she admits to funneling money to
The
Fugitive and that is one of the reason
reasons he was able to live overseas and
to stay ahead of us on the run because
he was actually receiving financial
assistance from this
person but she recently broke ties with
him she supposedly finally realized that
he really did Kill Holly Maddox that he
had been conning her all
along finally the arys tells them what
they want to
know she thinks Einhorn is in Stockholm
Sweden living with a woman named Marie
Val
Borg investigators move from Dublin to
Stockholm working through interpole
Philadelphia authorities have Stockholm
police rush valor's
home in einhorn's room Stockholm police
find a hot cup of coffee and a cigarette
still burning in the
ashray someone must have tipped Einhorn
off someone who knew the Canadian ays
ided him in any case he's
gone you're following a trail and
sometimes that trail is cold sometimes
it's
hot in the ira Einhorn case uh had
several hot trails and they don't come
up that often so when you are real close
and you almost catch somebody huge
frustration they miss him by perhaps
seconds and a massive Sur search in
Stockholm comes up
empty once again Ira Einhorn has
vanished and soon so does Marie
valborg we sent leads to virtually every
European
country Spain Germany Scandinavian
countries and none of the leads ever
panned
out but you know in this business you
keep you know when you develop lead you
send them cuz you never
know now all the FBI and the
Philadelphia police can do is
wait almost 11 years after the brutal
murder of Holly Maddox her killer Ira
Einhorn remains on the
run the grueling Wait For answers takes
its toll on Holly's parents even though
it damaged their health certainly it
took years off their lives it hurt them
so much to the core that they couldn't
even heal from deep
inside we were angry that he kept
getting away both Fred and Elizabeth
Maddox die while their daughter's killer
is still on the
run the family keeps pressuring the
police and in 1993 a Philadelphia jury
convicts Einhorn In Absentia of
murder carbonel and deetto still have to
find find
him weekly we would meet and discuss
what to do cuz some things you just
sometimes you just run out of leads
there you know you done it you've been
over it there's there's nothing it
languishes and we would go back over
and rein people and you know we knew the
guy was still out there now they just
have to find
him finally in 1997 another big break
thanks to authorities attention to the
smallest detail
interpole Sweden runs a check on Einhorn
and his latest girlfriend Marie valborg
and this time they get a
hit a woman named Marie valborg Edwards
has applied for a driver's license in
France police believe she is living in
champan muton
France well when this information came
to us rich and I knew that we had
ironhorn Michael carbonel and Richard De
benedetto have worked together on the
case continuously for about 9
years that's the most excited that both
of us were on the case cuz we were both
convinced that he was in France with her
but there's a problem this house is out
in the
countryside and uh it's kind of isolated
French authorities must go in undercover
to get close what they were doing was
over a period of a few weeks they were
posing as fisherman in a stream by the
house one day they spot someone there
it's
Einhorn it's now or never we were
concerned in IR hord would flee once
again we didn't want that to happen
because we we had never been closer to
him I mean this was this was it on June
13th 1997 French police raid einhorn's
house in shampan muton
[Music]
and capture the fugitive who remains
smug smiling at the
cameras so when the French police
actually laid their hands on him and he
was in handcuffs it was it was a huge
moment it was a huge moment rich and I
were just ecstatic estatic it was uh one
of the more satisfying moments in my
career I felt like justice had been
served and I was especially happy for
the madx family but it's not over yet
France refuses to extradite Einhorn
because he's already been convicted and
they refuse to hand him over if he might
face the death
penalty four years of legal wrangling
commence the US authorities have to
convince the French government they
won't seek the death penalty and they
will retry
Einhorn on July 20th
2001 Ira Einhorn once again sets foot on
American soil in Philadelphia this time
in shackles surrounded by US
Marshals it's been over 20 years since
he jumped bail and
fled it was a huge victory for for
Justice Just in getting him back here
because everything was back on track as
it should have been on October 17th 2002
a jury finds zra Einhorn guilty of
Holly's murder and sentences him to life
in prison without parole thanks to the
police work of agencies around the world
working with interball Ira Einhorn will
never leave prison
alive I wish my parents could have been
alive to be in the courtroom to see the
verdict come down come down and realize
that their daughter's killer was now not
going to have a life of Freedom like he
had enjoyed and flaunted in everyone's
face but I think all of us all feel that
they know it
November 23rd
1985 Athens
[Music]
Greece Athens airport is crowded that
day packed with travelers from dozens of
countries 5 months earlier tww flight
847 was hijacked and one American was
killed airport security is tight
tightened but Anthony Lions an
Australian steel salesman sees something
he doesn't like at the metal
[Music]
detector and the guy stopped him and so
he put his hand in his pocket and he
pulled out the camera showed it to the
guy and the guy never made him go round
back through again he just said oh
okay three young businessmen follow the
man with the camera through the security
checkpoint like Lions they are traveling
from Athens to
Cairo it is a trip they have been
planning for some
time their bags are
X-ray and
cleared Lions arrives at the gate to
find that the flight to Cairo has been
delayed
and notices the three businessmen at the
end of the line seem
[Music]
agitated Elizabeth fiser is
Australian she has been waiting four
hours to fly standby to
Cairo ranita dbby and shos elaz are
Israeli the two friends are traveling to
Asia via Cairo because the fairs are
cheaper Drew William is an American a
fisherman by trade
he is flying to Cairo to see the
sights when the desk finally opened it
was a great Rush of
bodies and in the rush uh there was a a
lady an Australian lady uh who was
pushed out of the line and she'd been
there very early and I didn't like that
EXC M Lions forces one of the
businessmen to return to the back of the
line when I uh intervened uh I don't
think he was happy to go back in the
line cuz obviously he wanted uh a a
particular seat or he wanted to get a
seat in a particular
area the three businessmen finally
present their passports to the ticket
agent Omar mazuki is traveling on a
forged
passport his real name is Omar Muhammad
Al
razak his two accompli shakori Salah
Salim and bu nalin Muhammad are also
traveling with fake
passports all three men are working for
the abun Dal
organization one of the most violent
terrorist groups in the
world in the early 1980s Terror was on a
deadly
rise in 1983 a suicide bomber attacked
the Marine Barracks in
Lebanon in 1985 terrorists hijacked the
cruise ship achil Lao and threw a
disabled American overboard
even with increased security Travelers
still feel
frightened unaware of the danger that
awaits them 91 people board flight
[Music]
648 Anthony Lions is seated in coach
next to Elizabeth
Fischer Zak is seated directly across
the aisle from
them Salim and bused have requested
separate
seats they move to the middle and the
rear of the
aircraft Lions notices rach's
Behavior I didn't sort of pay much
attention to him at first cuz I was
talking to Elizabeth Fischer but after a
while when I turned and looked at him I
noticed that he was perspiring heavily
around the mouth and uh he was staring
straight forward and he was uh clenching
his hands clenching and unclenching them
I thought wow this guy's nervous of
[Music]
flying in the cockpit pilot honey galal
and co-pilot Imad munib go through their
pre-light
checklist coffee gentlemen they are are
anxious to get off the
ground we are late and being late is not
a good thing for a
pilot at 9:03 p.m. Egypt Air flight 648
is finally cleared for
[Music]
takeoff 20 minutes into the flight
Captain galal turns off the no smoking
fastened seat belt sign
good afternoon ladies and
gentlemen makes his
[Music]
Mo Elizabeth fiser shows Anthony Lions
her new
camera all of a sudden she went white
and she was looking past me and she said
what's that I said what's what and then
the unthinkable
happens rosak emerges from the labatory
yelling in both English and Arabic for
the passengers to stay seated he had a
revolver in uh in one hand and an
Eastern block percussion grenade in the
other Egypt Air flight 648 has just been
hijacked Seline and bused threatened the
passengers with pistols and Hand
Grenades razak runs to the cockpit I
heard fast footsteps like someone
running but before I started to
investigate the [__]
door was banged open somebody kicked
it at gunpoint Omar razak orders the
pilot to change
course he orders him to redirect to
[Music]
Malta we don't have enough Captain galal
needs to come up with a plan of his
own your mind usually as a captain
starts to think very fast I mean you
don't stop thinking and Counting and
calculating things
for a second I insisted on going to K
because we have limited
fi he said no alter your course to
Malta my
co-pilot had put a special code on our
transponder giving uh uh signal to
Traffic Control in in Athens that we are
being hijacked
on the radar screen air traffic
controllers can see Egypt airflight 648
change
course in the cabin the terrified
passengers have no idea where they're
going or
why we had an announcement from the
Stuart saying that they had taken over
this aircraft and uh if everybody did
what they were told nobody would be
harmed through the stewardess the
hijackers identify themselves as members
of Egypt's Revolution a violent faction
of abidal's radical Palestinian group
Rak tells the pilot his organization
condemns the Egyptian regime for the
manner in which it had been conducting
its Affairs in the Middle East there's
things you have to realize about being
in an
airplane Panic it's going to do you no
good cuz there's nowhere to go you can't
run anywhere and you can't hide you are
there for whatever's going to
happen Salem orders the passengers to
take out their passports
youport next the hijackers sort the
passengers they collected all the pass
and they started calling people by the
passports and taking them to the front
fisting them get to the put us into some
type of order the Americans the
Australians belgians French they were
all at the front of the
aircraft everybody else uh the Greek
passengers uh the Egyptian passengers
were all kept separated uh further down
the
aircraft and there happened to be two
young Israeli girls on uh on the flight
and they were put at the front of of the
aircraft you you come here come here
Saleem also orders Anthony Lions to take
a seat up
front They confiscated my camera he took
it and he he ripped the film out of it
and then threw the camera hard down
against the bulkhead at the front of the
aircraft he believed that it was that
camera that I had been using and I may
have taken his
[Music]
photograph when the hijackers reach
midhat Mustafa kaml the passenger
produces more than a passport
it all of a sudden all hell broke
loose there were many many
gunshots and the hijacker who was stood
alongside me was firing wildly down the
length of the
[Music]
aircraft Mustafa K is an Egyptian Sky
Marshal
inside the cockpit RAC reacts to the
sound of
[Music]
gunfire they fired wildly at the at the
sky Marshall in so doing they wounded
some other people uh and the sky
Marshall got a number number of bullets
in his
body problem in all a flurry of 27 shots
ripped through the fuselage of the
737 some of the bullets penetrated the
skin of the aircraft and we were losing
pressurization
so I made what we call an emergeny
descent you cannot stay on the altitude
of 33,000 ft or 35,000 ft uh with a hole
in your aircraft because the hole will
get bigger and
bigger pressure the cabin pressure is
dropping pilot galal puts the plane into
a steep
dive he has to get to 14,000 ft fast or
the plane will break
apart and move 30,000 ft over the
Mediterranean
a hijacking turns into a gun
battle bullets tear through
passengers crew
members and the outer wall of the
[Music]
aircraft Anthony Lions fears the
worst the aircraft started to dip and go
into a
dive and the cockpit uh door was
flapping open and closed wildly and uh
as the aircraft was going to this deep
dive the uh oxygen masks all came out
dangling in front of us and we had to
put them
on I didn't know whether we were going
straight on into the to the sea or what
we were
doing that uh I hope this is a control
dive I was thinking about the fact that
I wasn't going to see my kids grow
[Music]
up Captain honey galal struggles to keep
the diving plane stable and his
passengers
alive when you lose pressure you lose
air and people suffocate so you have to
go down as fast as possible to an
altitude where people can breathe
normally from the normal air around
their
thecraft galal levels off at 14 ,000 ft
only to face a new crisis I was flying
very low very low at the time when you
fly low you burn more fi almost one/
thir
more I had to land at
[Music]
Malta he radios the tower at Luca
International Airport on the small
island of
Malta detailing the
situation I told them that uh permission
to land of Malta this said you don't
have
permission the Pilot's only other option
is to ditch the aircraft in the
sea then I start pleading to them in the
name of humanity that let us land
because we will die and you will be
responsible Larry fenich is the
assistant CEO air traffic controller in
Malta the chances of survival of an
aircraft FL that ditching in the ocean
will be very remote uh the people can be
saved from it because of the speed the
aircraft would hit the water the angle
and it would hit the loss of life would
have been high multis authorities don't
want the plane to crash but they don't
want an international incident
either to make Landing impossible they
order the air traffic controllers to
turn off all the runway
lights but galal is so low on fuel he
has no
choice he must risk Landing blind
galal turns the plane in a wide
Arc and descends into the complete
darkness having
landed I have to tell you that the only
feeling I had was I don't want this damn
aircraft to ever take off again I felt
better being on the ground and I'm sure
everybody else felt the same the plane
is ordered to taxi to a remote air
strrip where malti's Security Forces
wait to surround
it in the cockpit rosak is at a
loss with the lead hijacker critically
injured he's got to figure out what to
do
now now all he wants to do is save
himself and the other surviving
hijacker power we need fuel doctor he
demands the aircraft be refueled so they
can take off again
he also wants a doctor to examine his
accomplice and an engineer to inspect
the damage to the
[Music]
plane malte government officials arrive
in the tower to supervise the
negotiations they agree to send in
medical
personnel but only if the hijackers
agree to release some of the
passengers you have to release hostages
before they bring the position and the
refueling rosak returns to the
[Music]
cabin you come be okay baby go the
hijacker orders several Egyptian and
Filipino women to move to the front of
the
[Music]
plane they are released unharmed onto
the
tarmac soon after a doctor came on board
and he uh first of all uh looked at the
uh the hijacker buying a crossroad one
and he shook his head to say that he was
dead and then he uh looked at the sky
Marshal who he found was still alive
although had been shot many
[Music]
times shakori Saleem the lead hijacker
is is
dead as the medical team evacuates the
patient rosak strikes as the sky Marshal
was taken off the
aircraft reac shot him in the back
again he was one of the worst type of
terrorists a brainwashed killing
machine he has absolutely no mercy
nothing in his the so he's capable doing
doing it
again now with only two hijackers on
board razak threatens to execute a
hostage every 15 minutes until the tower
agrees to refuel the
plane authorities decide to call his
bluff they try and negotiate the safe
return of the
hostages the negotiations were hinged on
the fact that they were trying to
the situation not give him fuel um they
didn't want the problem to be
transferred to another country the main
purpose was to get some of the hostages
released you give us hostages and we
give you something else food yes doctors
yes Engineers yes but fuel
no razak responds with a tragic
demonstration we uh had the steart US
come out bring this
and she read a name in it from a
passport and it was a young Israeli
girlby and uh she got up come forward
and uh went to the front she was called
to the
front she gets up there and uh reac
takes her and turns her to go
out and uh he steps out behind
her and we heard
a
shot and it was absolute stunt
silence we couldn't believe
it razak pushes the young woman's body
onto the
tarmac I don't think anybody believe
that he would actually do it but
suddenly we got a call from the people
who were surrounding the the aircraft in
the Strategic positions that had just
shot a person at the door of the
aircraft
somehow ranita dbby survives the shot
and crawls
away but razak is
Relentless and I still remember it I
felt sick you know I you know it was
such a sense of uh of
loss on board the aircraft rosak calls
another Israeli to the front of the
plane so when they uh made the the the
second announcement for the second
Israeli girl to to go to the
front uh this girl obviously knew what
what her fate was going to
be so she never answered and uh the
stewardess kept saying very stridently
there is another Israeli girl on this
flight uh would she please come
forward shos elaz is 23 years
old and terrified
she sort of collapsed in the front uh
part of the aircraft there in front of
the cockpit
door and she wouldn't go out and uh reac
uh kneed her uh with his knee put his
knee into her and pushed her and pro her
and pushed her outside the
door I I started to plead to to to Malta
give us fuel we have to go out let me
take him to where he
wants maltes authorities face an
impossible
decision if they give in Malta could
become a Haven for
hijackers if they refuse an innocent
young woman will
die in Malta a Palestinian hijacker
threatens to shoot a passenger every 15
minutes until authorities refuel the
plane and let him take
offby one woman has already been
shot but mti's authorities still refuse
to negotiate with the terrorists
[Music]
now two young women have been shot in
Cold
[Music]
Blood the stunned malt authorities and
hany galal the pilot share the terror
and outrage of the events never feel
that kind of anger in my life it becomes
like uh shooting some of your family and
you are not being able to do something
about
it malti Security Forces surrounding the
aircraft move
closer rosak spies them from the
cockpit us who are they's going on here
and they gave him a very smart answer is
these forces are here to protect you
because uh the Americans might attack
you from
there rosak screams at the tower to make
the soldiers back off
the soldiers hold their
position authorities tell Rak he has no
choice but to
surrender he has no way
out if the hijackers try to leave the
island American jets based in nearby
Italy will intercept the plane and force
it
down us will the response enrages the
hijacker he pulls on his mask and
returns to to the
[Music]
cabin rosak rifles through the bucket
full of
passports there was a pecking
order in which way people were going to
be called and
executed Americans were very very much
the second in line uh for
execution Drew William an american
commercial fisherman is called to the
front of the
plane he was a very very tall man
probably 6' 6 65 66 something like
that so when they took him to the front
uh he was much much taller than
reac so when he stepped out and reac
stepped out behind him I actually
watched as reac raise the
gun uh to the back of his of his
head and uh there was the
shot and we thought well that's it uh
he's
dead miraculously the defective bullet
does not penetrate William's
skull he lies still until razak closes
the cabin
door and then Lim away from the
aircraft as two more Americans are
called and shot Anthony Lions an
Australian wonders who is next I was
trying to put together a plan in my head
as to what I would do if I was called
for execution I felt that uh if you are
in a situation where reac comes behind
you with a gun I was going to make uh
one step out and then very quickly throw
myself over the side of the stairs no
matter what it took and what the fall
was like I was going to do
that in the morning galal begins to
stall for
time he asks rach's permission to
request food for the passengers and to
have the bodies removed from the
tarmac razak
[Music]
agrees at 8:00 a.m. a catering truck
moves past the soldiers and delivers
food to the steps of the aircraft
[Music]
next an ambulance arrives to remove the
bodies from the
tarmac shashana elaz is
dead reita Dai is critically wounded but
incredibly is still
alive the ambulance takes the bodies to
St Luke's
Hospital although the standoff has gone
on for hours rosak shows no ation of
giving
up the authorities are faced with an
agonizing
decision us and Egyptian authorities
have sent Special Forces Commandos to
Malta to help rescue the
passengers the government of Malta
decides to allow the Egyptian Commandos
to recover their country's
plane they deny US forces permission to
land
nearly 24 hours have passed since flight
648 was hijacked in
Athens Egyptian Commandos begin to plan
their assault of the
plane they have very little information
on how many hijackers are still on board
what they look like or where they are
positioned their mission has only one
simple objective to take out the
terrorists they will create a diversion
by detonating an explosion inside the
cargo bay at the back of the
plane they will then enter the aircraft
Through the Windows over each
Wing at nightfall the Egyptian Commandos
approach the
plane they try to stay in the blind spot
behind the cockpit where rosak can't see
them on board the plane it seems the
hijackers can sense something is going
on I could hear the bullets in his
pockets rattling as he moved and he was
anxious about
something obviously something was a foot
and uh people could see out the out the
windows that there was movement in the
Grass at the side of the
aircraft as the Commandos placed their
explosive charges they are unaware that
a few feet away many of the passengers
are seated directly direct ly over the
cargo
hold on the small island nation of
Malta the hijacking of an egyp air jet
turns
deadly 25 hours into the hijacking
Egyptian Commandos prepare to assault
the plane with a diversionary explosion
in the cargo
[Music]
hold the blast rips the through the back
of the
plane when it it went off uh it exploded
and blew a hole through the floor there
and blew everybody in that area up and
started a fireball which raced down the
inside of the
aircraft bu one of the two remaining
hijackers is incinerated in the
[Music]
blast the Commandos rush into the plane
in the cockpit pilot honey galal is
injured from the
blast he tells his co-pilot to escape
through the cockpit window while he goes
after the
hijacker as rosak emerges from the
cockpit one of the Commandos wounds
[Music]
him galal attacks the hijacker with a
fire axe but Rak escapes through the
cabin
door galal returns to the cockpit now he
must get out of the plane open the the
cockpit and the window and throw myself
[Music]
down nearly 70 passengers are trapped
inside the aircraft
disoriented by the smoke choking on
toxic
fumes and unable to find a way
[Music]
out Lions escapes from the plane by
crawling to the cabin
door and sliding down the
[Music]
stairs he rolls underneath a vehicle to
keep from being shot by the
Commandos when I took my my first uh
breath I held my breath and when I took
my first breath I immediately started
choking on the tarmac galal joins the
rescue
[Applause]
effort the site was
horrible I tried to re-enter the
airplane to get some of the passengers
out but it was impossible
I couldn't get in there and uh that was
a very painful
moment because I have realized that
whatever left in inside the airplane are
[Music]
dead lions tries to run to
safety but an Egyptian Commando points a
gun in his
face the Commandos don't know how many
hijack ERS there are or what they look
[Music]
like Rescuers Rush the wounded from
flight 648 to St Luke's
Hospital malt medical examiners estimate
that of 56 passengers killed in the
rescue attempt tragically four die from
gunshot wounds from automatic assault
rifles carried by the Commandos
over 50 passengers died from inhaling
toxic fumes produced by the burnt
[Music]
insulation malt authorities and gal
quickly identify the remains of one of
the
hijackers Salem was shot to death by the
Egyptian Sky
Marshall bused died in the
explosion only Omar rosat is unaccounted
for hello Mr Lions I'm with m in the
hospital Anthony Lions identifies Omar
razak in the Intensive Care
Unit I said that's one of the hijackers
I said I can end this now I can pull the
tubes and uh you know I felt really
strongly about uh about that seeing
seeing somebody like that and uh they
now knew they had uh they had
Ron anig galal supports Line's
claim it's
razak he was shot uh very seriously I
mean his heart is
wounded and uh I told him in Arabic
while while I was taken there to to
identify him that uh you will heal up
and you will come with me back
uh I deliberately said that to him heal
up because you'll come back with me and
we have a rope ready for
you Omar razak is directly responsible
for the deaths of dozens of
people including one American
[Music]
citizen the United States and the maltes
government both want to try rosak for
murder but the maltes government takes
control of the investigation
the FBI provides forensic experts to
help The Malt analyze the
wreckage they examined the chart plane
Gathering evidence and building their
case against
Rach in the lab examiners positively
identify a fingerprint found on a
cockpit window as belonging to Omar
[Music]
razak back in Malta Captain hany galal
testifies against rar at his
trial when you kill women and children
like
this you know that kind of
violation is
unforgivable he has to brought to
Justice and he has to to be punished for
that in November 1988 Omar razak pleads
guilty to
murder under mti's law he is sentenced
to 25 years in prison in
Malta but it is a sentence the terrorist
will never
complete in 1988 Omar razak is sentenced
to spend 25 years in prison for
murder the blood of 58 innocent people
is on his
hands 7 years years into rak's
imprisonment as part of a general
amnesty program the government of Malta
considers releasing the brutal
terrorist in Washington DC FBI agents
review the rosak case with us prosecutor
Joseph
vder special agent Bob Clifford the
horrific nature the extent of of his
crime to only serve 7even 8 n years in
prison and then be released was
completely unacceptable to the United
States razak has attacked and killed an
American
citizen the United States is determined
to make him pay for his
crimes the challenge before us was to
find a violation of US law which we
could prosecute reac on if when he was
released F and vder meet with malt
officials you f
they get assurances from the government
that rosak probably will not be freed
for at least 3
years 2 Days Later the maltes courts
release rosak from prison special agent
Kevin
fa I felt I'd been lied to we had met
with the authorities in Malta less than
48 hours earlier and we were assured
that we had three years to work on how
we could find a way to bring this man to
the United States to face Justice and
then suddenly he's
gone thoughts that went through my mind
was my God here is a trained committed
terrorist who has conducted this
horrific attack without any type of
remorse being released and being
released into an area of the world that
uh he had known connections to and could
he conduct or organize an attack like
this
again soon after his release malti
authorities lose track of
him to have him go free to have him
disappear would was not an
option absolutely not an option this man
had killed a ruthlessly a lot of
people and one way or another no matter
where no matter how we were going to get
him we had to ethopia those 48 hours
have passed razak could be anywhere in
the world by
now agent Clifford turns to the only
agency with the means to help him
interpole this interpole notice uh was
uh transmitted to uh through our
national Central Bureau of interpool to
all interpole members uh to alert any
country throughout the world if reac was
traveling through to have him stopped
and that the United States in fact would
request provision Vis arrest and
extradition cord by transmitting the
information around the world to the
member nations of interpole
investigators pick up rak's Trail on a
tip from an unlikely
Source EOP according to Russian
intelligence relayed through their
interpole office Rak has reservations
aboard an aeroflot flight Bound for the
Sudan by way of Ghana and
Nigeria he is traveling under an
alias Rak flies to
arrana but local authorities alerted by
the maltes embassy were waiting for
him now the US state department must
wait for Ghana to release
him and that's not
likely one of the passengers who died on
the plane was from
Ghana gone at the time was not quite
sure if they wanted to try him or if
they could try him for the death of
the citizen of Ghana on that aircraft in
1985 the Americans fear that if he is
tried in Ghana razak May again find a
way to escape
Justice this man is a is a an animal
he's a terrorist he's murdered people
he's violated our law give him to us
under existing treaties just give him to
us and we'll take him back to the United
States one day turned into a week a week
turned into two weeks and still Ghana
never came through with the commitment
to allow the FBI to take custody of
reac 4 months later in July
1993 special agent Clifford receives a
startling phone
call the government of Ghana stated
we're going to release
reac we're going to release him in 48
hours and it's up to you to figure out
how you're going to get him if you want
him into of the FBI have we immediately
scrambled put together an arrest team we
knew his next stop was going to be Lagos
Nigeria the arrest team learns early on
of rak's itinerary he will be flying
from Malta to Ghana to Nigeria and
finally to
Sudan the government of Nigeria has
agreed to cooperate but with growing
civil unrest in the country the
situation is unstable and dangerous we
were quite concerned that the same
government that had given us permission
to come in and take this man from them
would still be in power when we landed
and when we
left we knew when we departed Washington
for
Nigeria that if we missed him there we'd
never see him again that was our only
hope is that we could stop him there and
get him because if he was not caught at
that moment if there is even just a
couple of hours of difference in the
flights if something happened to our
aircraft and we might have been uh uh
delayed he'd be gone he'd be
God a short time later rak's flight
touches down in
Lagos Nigerian authorities detain
him but under pressure from the US
Nigerian police hand the hijacker over
to the f
FBI Omar razak is finally in US
[Music]
custody I've arrested many terrorists
and I've dealt with a lot of
terrorists but something about
reac was his
commitment when you're dealing with
someone like that you have to be very
very cautious because they are willing
to
die for what they believe in
on June 21st
1996 Omar Muhammad Ali razak stands
trial before a jury in United States
district court for the District of
Colombia Anthony Lions has been asked to
testify they said uh would you be
willing to help and I said I'll swim
over the first thing he must do is pick
rosak out of a
lineup that's the first time I'd seen
him again was at the lineup I saw his
face and I thought right you're here
you're really here great we've got you
on July 19th
1996 the jury finds Omar Muhammad Ali
razak guilty of one count of air piracy
yeah I was actually in the court uh the
day that the guilty uh verdict was uh
was to be had by reac and uh it was an
amazing feeling absolutely
amazing they sent in him to life in
prison justice has been served reac is
in a Maximum Security Prison he's in
solitary confinement he comes out on a
very limited basis to go into a cell in
which he only has a
skylight but when you
see uh the
horrible brutal acts that he committed I
mean shooting women point blank in the
head uh being absolutely uh
unremorseful for these
crimes uh nothing nothing could be be
better for an animal like
that because of the brutal hijacking of
Egypt Air 648 and other terrorist
detects like it the world no longer
considers terrorism an act of War but a
crime interpole can now bring its vast
resources to find and capture terrorists
wherever they try to hide
[Music]